My semester is going to
be busier than it normally is.
Thanks, you too. I'm going in.
All right.
Just check some stuff here.
So by the time we
said we were going to actually
try to log in the
system, try to code something up,
kind of see what's going on.
As far as I know, this is being recorded,
so we could go back and look at it.
But I mean, you might want
to take notes. I don't know.
I guess what I'm saying is I'm not
going to keep going over this or whatever.
Whatever you think is necessary.
And remember, even though
we're saying we're recording it,
it doesn't mean that it
goes to the glitch or something.
It's not there.
So just letting you know.
All right.
So you probably remember that when
we were on the Expanse user guide.
Let's go to the Expanse user guide here.
Remember there's a portal.
There'll be a web
portal where you can
use the interface, right?
It's 12F.
The portal is this.
And it's literally just, if you
type it in from a new terminal,
it's just portal.expanse.sandview.com.
Or you can just go back to the
guide and do whatever you've got to do.
Now, you see how I'm
at this little thing here?
Now, remember the identity that we used
was step two for creating an account,
which was like it's not tied
to our postal account or anything.
Now, I'm not saying you've got to do this.
But I find that sometimes
if I'm like, yeah, man,
I just want to continue
with my access to whatever.
Sometimes that works.
Sometimes it doesn't.
And because I log in and
communicate to a bunch of different stuff,
I feel like some of the cookies and
stuff is shared to get you checked out.
So I just say, look,
I just want to log out.
Let's just log out.
And I'm going to
click on the portal again.
And then it's going to come and
ask me to log in the normal way.
And I'm like, yeah, well, we've
got to use our access stack things.
We're not doing it through an institution
or a job or a company or whatever.
So we're like, yep,
we're going to do that.
We're going to come and put our
access ID in it along with our password.
And we're going to get
the two-factor authentication
stuff in Duo.
That's a little bit concerning.
You know, I did all this
stuff this morning at 6 a.m. here,
so just to confirm that
everything for today would work.
And that doesn't seem very good.
I'll tell you what, let's see.
Let's see if I'm here.
I'm curious if my eyes ought to work.
Okay.
So it's sitting on the computer.
We'll do that.
All right, so I'm logged in.
And let's suppose that you
had downloaded the zip file
that contained the stuff in the class.
And you navigated to where the stuff was.
So like, for example, I downloaded it.
I guess I should have zipped it
up and gave it to you guys.
But I had to download, you know,
all of the stuff that we had before.
And by putting the Moodle, I went ahead
and got the source files out of there.
That was the source files that came in.
Plus, you can just get these
source files right off the internet
because the publisher's website has it
for students to download the source code.
And I literally moved this hard
GZ, so it's a zip file.
And I used this mechanism here, the file
that I used, to push it up there.
So I went to, like, the directory.
I made a 473 directory.
And the directory went up inside of it.
I said, upload.
I uploaded the thing.
I'm obviously not going to do that
here because of how slow your finger is.
And I got it there.
I didn't unzip it yet.
I did that.
I didn't do it with these next setups.
So I went and went
back to the portal here.
And we had opened up a shell.
I increased the font size so
we could see a bit here.
Also, so that if you're watching the video
at home later, like, if you need it,
you can be more visible, more legible.
If I do a print word
in the directory, look where I'm at.
I'm in the home directory.
If you do an LS, I'll
see the, there's the 473 folder blue.
So I'm going to go ahead and cd to 473.
And there's where I unzipped it before.
But I'm going to pretend
like I haven't done that yet.
So I'm going to delete that folder.
So I'm going to do an rm bash
recursively and force the
directory to be deleted.
And I'm just going
to remove my folder here.
Now, it would be as if I had
just uploaded that tar.gz
file from my desktop
that you had gotten
from the zip talk thing.
Or if you had gotten it through the
code.coast.edu get repo, which
has got all the stuff,
including the source code.
Or if you'd gotten the thing on the
internet from the public,
the Patinko second edition text
and gotten that, that's what the two
means is the
introduction of parallel programming
and processing or whatever it is
in addition to for the Patinko text.
That's what that is.
So then I'm just going to type unzip.
So hold on here now.
I'm doing wrong.
Let's do this.
Is this the deal here?
I don't know what that is.
Just want to make sure there's only one
thing in my directory to start out with.
It's 224 kilobytes.
That seems reasonable.
But now why is it that I can
unzip this file I
could did just earlier today?
Ugh.
That's right.
I bet it's got an unzip.
But I bet there doesn't work with tar.gz.
So let's do tar.xvfz.
And let's unzip it.
We're probably going to see like a bunch
of crap coming out of here on the screen.
Because this thing was
zipped maybe on my Mac.
But it's being unzipped
on its Linux system.
There's probably some file
that you can use
that are not the same because we're using
different file systems.
This is probably using ext4 over there.
This over here is some MacFS file systems.
So there's not all of the
attributes of every
file necessarily match.
But the important part is that when
you get there you've got the folder there.
So we're going to go over there
into that folder and look at what's there.
And we see that.
So it's organized by
chapter and all of this.
And I said we were going
to start with the MPI stuff today.
The MPI parallel programming stuff.
So what I plan to do here is go to
the Hello World program and
use the Hello World program
to motivate what we're going to do
in the slides related to learning MPI.
But we need to be able to at least
prove we can run
a parallel program here, right?
So the MPI stuff is in chapter 3.
So we're going to move
over here to chapter 3.
And the Hello World program, as you
can imagine, is this program right here.
So I want to go look at it.
Yep.
So tellerworld.c uses hello world.
It's even got like a little thing
to say how to compile it here.
So MPI CC means the MPI C compiler.
Dash G means turn on debugging.
Dash W means turn on some warnings.
So which warnings in particular?
All of the warnings.
Now that's not all of the warnings.
It's most of the warnings.
And it says what standard
of the C language do
you want me to assume
that this file is in?
And this thing says the C99 because, you
know, there was one
before that was C89, right?
There's definitely differences
about how four loops
are done and stuff
between those two versions.
Dash O means what is the output file name
of the binary that
we're going to execute here.
So I want to call it MPI Hello.
So that'll be like, if I was on
Windows, that'd be like
MPI underscore Hello dot exe.
But on Linux, of course,
we don't have to do that.
And then finally, the following file,
which is the Hello World program.
So yeah, the contrast and that's not
particularly great on the board, is it?
I wonder if there's another theme
here that would make it look cooler.
Let's see.
Is that better?
Okay.
And it says how we're going
to execute it, it has this.
So now I'm just going to
follow directions of what it says.
It says compile the thing I'm going to do.
Now when you're at this
little terminal on their portal,
when you highlight something and
let go of the mouse,
you see how it pops that thing over there?
Well, watch the screen when I do like that
and I let go of the left mouse button.
That means it just
copied that to the clipboard.
I don't have to hit
control C or any of this.
It's already in the clipboard.
Alright, so I'm going to get
back out of the file here.
And I'm going to try to compile it.
See, so I hit control B.
I hit enter.
And it says there's a problem.
It says I have, it
says so the GNU C compiler
says I don't know what you
mean by standard equals to C99.
Did you mean little C99?
Yep, we did.
You know, when they wrote
this whatever system he was on
had a compiler that assumed that
the thing was a capital letter.
But it's not.
For this compiler we're
using, it's a lowercase letter.
So I hit the up arrow and I
come back over here,
change this to little C.
Okay, so it came back.
And I said why did it
take so long to compile it?
It says hell of a
world, it shouldn't take very long.
I bet if I were
to run this again, it's fast.
Because the pretty first time it has
to cache up those binaries and pass it.
So I have to figure out what's going on.
So now, I'm going to do an ls-lar dh.
So l for a long list, all
the attributes r, t means diverse time.
And h means to put
the size of human readable format.
I like it in a
reverse time order because when I
just compile it, that binary will
be the most recently generated file.
And if you've got an error
with a craft ton of stuff in
it, you come over here and
you see right there, look at that.
You know, it's down here at
the bottom so I can see it.
So it's about 25 kilobytes
and it was just generated here.
Now you might look at this
timestamp and say,
that doesn't make sense.
It's not 8 o'clock in
the morning, I was 28.
But this is on the Pacific
Coast, the San
Diego Sewer Computing Center.
So three hours earlier there is here.
So one thing about it,
if you start moving files around,
you can get issues where the
timestamps aren't going to mash up
because they're in a different time zone,
you know, and you can have some issues.
Just FYI, if you ever wonder what the
hell is going on, that can be an issue.
Especially if you were
doing, like, some sort of
distributive type make situation
where it uses access times
and modification times to
understand how the tree works.
You shouldn't be doing that.
You can do it all on
this system or all on another system.
Because if you compile something
like a computer, you move
parts of those and compile
things over to the other system,
that doesn't work.
Because you might have
the same architecture, the same
version of libraries and all
this other sort of stuff.
So do it all
here, all there, all wherever.
Do it all from scratch, wherever it is.
Now I'm going to try to
run it like I would a
regular C program without all this
MPI stuff that I'm talking about.
I'm going to go here and
I'm going to say, alright, MPI, hello.
And I'm like, oh my god.
I've got a bunch
of stuff that's popped out.
I've got some of this stuff.
I'm going to tell all that is.
I do see that the print statement
that was in the file where it says,
greetings in the print,
you know, it's version of
hello world to the screen,
that seemed to come out.
And so did a bunch of other crap.
Now I remember the other day I said, um,
don't, uh, don't run
stuff on the head, no.
That's a hello world part, not a big deal.
But we're using MPI.
MPI is generally used when you're
trying to do
a high performance computation.
MPI is generally used when it's
going to take a long time.
So to prevent people from trying to even
use, I believe is why they did this.
Try to even do stuff
with MPI on the head node.
They're like, you're not going to be
able to run this on a head node.
But it could be that we didn't use
the command they said to run it with.
Let's try that.
What about if we said we let it in there.
Now remember, we could go back in
here and look at it like this.
We could say, all right, let
me go back into the program itself.
And, and okay.
MPI EXDC.
That's how I say I
want to execute the program.
I'm just using something called
MPI run instead of MPI exec.
But let's try this thing.
So MPI exec dash in
the number of processes on it.
That's why we're doing it parallel.
So we're going to kick off the spot
on processes and try to do the hello.
Okay, cool.
So let me try that.
MPI EX and then I hit tab.
You tab complete.
Sure enough, that program
is available on your somewhere.
So dash in.
Let's just do two processes.
Okay.
And let's try to run it.
MPI hello.
And I got some other stuff.
So I'm getting this feeling that
like, I'm either doing something wrong
or I shouldn't have been running it
to begin with on the head node.
Let's assume that until I actually get
on a node other than the head node,
we'll start debugging from there.
So the question is, how do you
get from the login server on this
to one of what they
call the back end computational nodes?
How do you do that?
All right.
Well, if you go back
over to the user guide,
it's not everything you need
to know in this guide.
It's a huge guide,
but everything's in there.
Now listen, I hate the shit they've done.
You're going to probably have
got to do them like this.
This is obnoxious.
God.
Let's go back up to the top of here
and look at what's at
the top of this page.
Running jobs.
That's what we're trying to do.
We're trying to run a job.
It's not running on the
head node for some reason,
so let me try to run it
on something that's not a head node.
So we get rid of running jobs.
And it says, now, running jobs
on Expanse uses a program called SLURM,
simple utility, the English
utility for user management
or whatever, resource management.
It says, remember
that computationally intensive jobs
should only run on the compute
nodes and not on the login nodes.
And that could be that we just don't
have the right modules
loaded for doing MPI.
I don't know.
Let's see what happens if we
get on one of these backend nodes.
Now it says, okay, now, when
you go to run a job,
you've got to tell it, where
do you want to run it?
Because remember, this thing's
got some GPU nodes.
It's got some regular CPU nodes.
It's got some 2
terabyte large memory nodes.
And in each one of those classes,
it has the following types of things.
Check it out.
We're going to be looking
for what's called the partition name
because when we go to
try to run this thing,
we have to tell them all
partition we want to run on.
That's like, got this big 800 node system
to partition our individual little pieces,
kind of think of it like that.
Now, partition name is called compute.
You could run a job
that lasts up to 48 hours.
One might be able to do that.
You're not going to do that because
if you did that for very much,
like we would run out
of all of our credits
and then nobody would
be able to run anything.
We're talking about order
of minutes, not hours.
You could run 32 nodes.
We're just trying to run this
on one node right now, all right?
We could only have 32
jobs running at the same time.
It looks like we're running one job.
And it says, and
this is important right here,
exclusive access.
So that means when you get one of these,
250 gigabyte RAM, 128 core machines,
you're going to be the only one
off when it gives it to you.
It won't be anybody else choosing it.
Now, let's say you stay
on it for 30 minutes, right?
Because that's the amount of time it
takes you to debug this thing or whatever.
What we're going to do is we're
going to do it at the command line
where we're playing around.
But now, you're not using one core.
You might only be using it yourself,
but because you've asked for
it to be on this petition,
it's giving you 128 cores all at once,
even if you're only going to use one.
But because it's exclusive.
So 30 minutes, so in
other words, a half an hour,
and 128 cores is like
using 64 cores for an hour.
32 cores for two hours.
And that's how they charge us.
They charge us as a
product of the number of cores
multiplied by the number of nodes,
multiplied by the amount of time.
So we would needlessly get
charged, say, for 64 surface units,
which is the number
of cores times the time,
even though you don't
need all those things.
Well, let's keep going.
Industry compute nodes.
We're not in industry.
Shared nodes.
Single node jobs that use less than
128 cores run 48 hours a week.
Industry shared.
Again, we're not in industry.
GDU.
We dang sure ain't going to use that.
Nothing in here about CUDA
or any other kind of thing.
And this is probably the
most expensive nodes on the system.
The number of surface units
are a lot for that.
Industry node.
This, I don't even know what this is.
This one wasn't even here the last time.
I get less than a plus.
This is some new news.
Whatever that is, whatever
kind of GPUs those are.
GDU shared.
We're not using that.
Industry GPU shared.
No.
Whatever kind of weird
answer GPUs that is.
Shared memory.
We're not doing it.
Oh, here we go.
We're going to be doing it to some bug.
We're just playing around right now.
So you can run a job for 30 minutes.
And it says you
get shared access to nodes.
That's good because I'm only going to
get charged for what I asked for.
I don't need all those cores, right?
All right, cool.
So, how do you get on one of these nodes?
Now, if you're going to want to
be sitting in a terminal debugging stuff,
looking at errors while
it's happening, trying stuff,
you want to be
what's called an interactive mode.
And that's what this thing is.
So the command we're going
to use to request interactive access
to one of the
nodes in that partition debug
is we're going to
use this thing down here.
So let's look at all
the pieces of this thing
before we just start
copying and pasting, okay?
It says here,
srun means slurm run.
If you're using slurm, that's
what they use to get access.
There's no way to
log into those other nodes
except for using things related to slurm.
Now, the partition is equal to debug.
That's what we want.
Don't worry about what this is, okay?
Now, the account is equal to
the project number we're dealing with.
Now, what project are we talking about?
It's the one that I added you guys
to when I added you to the allocation.
All right, now, let's step back.
What about if I didn't
know, like, I was you.
I was sitting in a command line.
I have no idea what my project codes are.
I don't know what they are.
How would you figure that out?
I'll come back up here to the
top and we can look for, let's see,
account management.
What is this?
It's a client managing your account.
It says here, now, if I'm on, you know,
what kind of modules do
I typically need to do stuff?
It says here that I need to
load the San Diego Energy Reducing Module,
which is kind of like it sets
up a bunch of stuff in your path
that you could do some
common things that they would do.
Now, I don't know if
that module might already be loaded.
I don't know.
If something doesn't work, we
might want to load that module.
It says here, if I want to know
what project that me as a particular user
is in, that I need to run this command,
expanse client user dash r expanse.
All right, so let's just see what happens.
If I scroll C and I scroll the B,
all right, so now
my shell is gone already.
Somebody go over here
and ask for another shell.
I'm going to scroll B that thing.
I'm going to scroll B that over here.
It says cool.
It says that W Jones is
currently allowed to be on the system
and the project code is CCU 108.
We started way back in the
day and it was CCU 101.
Now we're up to 108.
All right, so that's
the account that we need.
Okay, cool.
So go back over here.
Go back to running jobs.
Go back down here.
It says cool.
So the account is CCU 108.
How many nodes do we want?
The minimum number of
nodes you ask was one.
We don't want any more than
one right now because we're just playing.
Now, how many, what about this?
The number of tasks per node.
Okay.
Now, I want you to kind of think like,
we'll get more into this later.
But like, if I want to run
my program and I want to run, say,
several different tasks,
different numbers of
threading and all this kind of stuff,
there's different parameters that
we might want to use.
And it says it's four here.
So let's just ask for that.
Mind of memory, we need eight gigabytes.
That's actually a lot
more than we really need.
Now, how did that be used if I learn?
Well, remember, we're sharing a machine.
So it uses this stuff like,
if I ask for a bunch of tasks,
that is going to limit the
number of cores to everybody else.
So like, they can look and
see how many cores are left.
Oh, he can go here.
He can go there.
Oh, well, there's only four
gigabytes of RAM left on here.
And they need eight.
Well, I can't put him on this node.
I'm going to have to put it on the node.
That's called scheduling.
So Slurm is the scheduler
to try to schedule different stuff.
Dash t means what is the maximum amount
of time I expect my job to run?
Well, for debugging, it only lets
you run it for 30 minutes.
So you can say 30 minutes.
And then we would say, I
don't want to wait at all.
I want you to get me
in there as soon as you can.
Dash dash export means
all of my environment variables,
I want you to export them so
that they're equal over their own access
into whatever they are on the head node.
And finally, what do I
want you to run over there?
Like, you're telling me to run something.
What do you want me to run?
I want you to run a terminal.
So the batch terminal, so that I
can be sitting there in the terminal
and interact with the system.
Does that make sense?
Let's try this.
Let's just see what happens.
I'm going to go up to here, hit Control-C.
I'm going to look over here.
Control-V, the account is CCU 108.
All right, now what's the next?
Let's go back over here.
Number of nodes is this.
Let's just get all that.
And you can imagine that you
want to have yourself a little thing
where you can keep track
of some of these things, right?
So you go, OK, I don't
want to have you digging around.
I'll keep a list of
some common things I typically do.
All right, so go over here.
Control-V, this thing over there, space.
Let's see anything else I want to do.
Yep.
The memory, runtime, and terminal.
Cool.
I'm going to go here, put that in there.
Let's see what happens.
And there we go.
Now listen to what it said.
It said, all right, so Slurm is
going to try to run a job.
And this job is literally like
it's an index
that just keeps incrementing.
Every time somebody
does something with Slurm,
it increments it so that
everybody's got a unique job ID
that they're trying to run.
It says, OK, I'm trying to queue my job.
What in the hell am I talking about?
This one, where you
said, give me a terminal.
That's a job.
It's waiting for resources.
Oh, cool.
Now it's got some resources.
And the resources that it
allocated to my job, OK, cool.
I found a machine to run it on.
Which machine?
This server right here, exp-9-55.
If I'd run it again here, I
might have to get another number to do.
That's just a, even where
it's got 700 nodes or so.
It leads to, there's some mapping
between that name and those node numbers
and MAC addresses and
IP addresses and all that.
There's something behind the scenes
handling all that for us, OK?
So now, I'm over there and
I'm on a completely different node.
I'm going to do a framework and directory,
and I'm still in the home directory here.
So I'm going to move over to 473.
I'm going to move over to the
directory with the source code in it.
And I'm going to try to MPI-CC my program.
So MPI-CC-G for the warnings,
or excuse me, the debugging,
dash W to all, dash
over to the output file.
You can call this anything you
want, like you can call it crap.
And then what I want to compile up,
I want to compile
up the MPI-LO program, right?
Then I want to see if that
file is there now to do an LS.
Sure enough, there's
the binary executable.
How can I tell that it's an executable?
Well, it's green, number one.
But number two, if
I look at this permissions,
everything, you know, so user group world,
so everybody got
execute permissions on this.
That's kind of weird.
But anyway, let's try to run it.
We got something kind of weird here, OK?
Well, we'll try to run it
to what he said in mine.
MPI exec dash N2 and the program, right?
And then hit ran.
Clear the screen.
Hit up arrow, run it again.
There it is.
It executed two copies of my program
because I'm asking it
to generate two processes.
And then it kicked them all,
going to print some stuff to the screen.
What about if I asked
her to run three processes?
What about if I asked for four?
All right, now what about
if I asked for five?
Let's see.
Oh, why is that?
How many tasks did we ask for?
Four.
There aren't.
That's five tasks, not four.
So if I needed a
degree of heroism using MPI
that required five things,
meaning I want five
cores to be involved, say,
I had to specify that,
but you don't want to
have that to be any bigger
than it needs to be.
So four is good enough for
us to be playing around here, right?
OK, now another thing you
can do is you can say,
look, just oversubscribe the cores.
Instead of running one task per core,
let's just go ahead and run it faster 5.0.
I'll go ahead and just run more
than one on one of those things.
I'm going to kind of overload it.
I'm going to overbook it, if you will.
Like, the same way your computer
has got thousands of processes running,
but there's not thousands of cores, right?
It handles it.
So if we come back over here and we say,
what it says
here, dash dash oversubscribe,
and then we try to run this.
So I ran it.
But remember, we're running more processes
than we actually have resources here.
But it's OK.
We're not looking for performance.
We're just looking for
does it work logically?
OK.
Everybody good?
You see how to log into the system?
All right.
Now, I wonder if MPI run would work.
MPI run, dash MP2.
Now, notice, with MPI exact, it's dash N.
With MPI run, it's dash
MP, number of processes, 2.
So I could have used run as well.
So if you've seen using run,
that's because that's what
I typically used back
in the day when I was in college.
But I mean, they got these things.
Are they the same thing?
There's some differences.
But the things we're playing with
right now really
don't make any difference.
So now, let's jump back over and
let's look at the slides that come along
with the thing that explains what the
hell is going on in that zebra.
Come over here.
Come back over there.
How many of you already know
how to run an MPI job?
Excuse me, not an MPI job.
To get into a slur on
my nose, like we're just doing.
How do I show hands?
Like this.
All right.
So we're doing
distributed memory programming.
It's called distributed because that means
that we're on more than one node
at the same time.
And we are using messages
to send messages back and forth.
This is called explicit message passing.
All right.
The opposite of that
would be shared memory.
That means that all the threads
can see the same memory thing.
And you can use things like MPI
to send messages back
and forth between processes,
whether or not those processes
are all on the same computer
or if those processes
are spread across computers.
You see what I mean?
So, like, you know, I
could be on my computer,
and one process right in
here can share, you know,
you could send a message
back and forth, processes on here.
It's probably like what you've
done before with, say, like,
with some of the stuff you
did in, say, multi-process with your U6.
But when you do the MPI run, depending
on how you ask the servers to start it,
it'll actually watch your program across
if you ask for 10 nodes
and you want to ask
for, say, 10 tasks per node,
it'll do 10 processes on this
node, 10 processes on this node.
And they'll make it all
be communicating with each other
across network connection.
You can't do that
with just standard straight-up threads
because it's not shared across computers.
All right.
This is the kind
of thing we're talking about.
That's a node, a node, a node, and a node,
and they're only connected
together through
the interconnection network,
like, you know, Infiniband or
Ethernet or something like that.
And so, let's look at
our basic Hello World program.
Now, you've all done
C program before, right?
I mean, everybody does C program,
and this is what you're used to.
So, now, what is MPI?
Well, MPI is not another language.
It's just a library.
It's just, like, some of the API
calls that can be made from C.
And, by the way, there's
bindings for MPI in other languages.
Now, the only ones
that are officially supported
by the MPI Standards
Committee is C and Fortran.
But if you look it
up, you see MPI and Python.
You get an MPI of
a bunch of different things.
But that standard doesn't match.
Like, if you do it one way in Python,
it ain't going to
be that same way necessarily.
Python's had its own
issues for a long time,
a year or two, where
there was a global interpreter lock
on your computer, and
it couldn't be multi-threaded anyway.
So, there was some issues with that.
All right.
How do we tell which process to switch?
When you ask for ten processes,
each process is going to be started,
and it's going to
know which process it is.
And they're going to
be, whatever's launching it,
that MPI run that, it's going to say,
it's going to tell
everybody, I am launching you?
By the way, you're in the next spot.
So, there are going to be
numbers of zero to p minus 1.
And here's that program that
we were looking at here.
All right.
Now, I'm going to get out of full
screen so we can zoom in here a bit.
All right.
So, you include your standard
IO.h for being open print.
You include your string.h,
probably because we're going to do
a string copy or something like that.
And we're including your PI.h because
that way it has the prototypes
for these MPI calls
we're going to be making,
this library essentially, to
sit on top of C
that we can use
to achieve this parallelism.
All right.
So, we've got a concept here,
integer that's probably string length.
So, the max string length is 100.
And then down here,
how about this is as bad
as it looked at, didn't it?
I'll just move this thing around.
You know, we've got a, you know,
a character array that's this long.
And what these, what this
program is going to be doing
is it's going to be sending
a message from one process to another.
And the message is going
to be a string message.
That's why they're creating an
array to hold the strings.
Now, we'll wait for this for a second.
Just come down here
and look at these lines.
13, 12, 12, 13, 14.
The very first MPI call that you
have to make in every MPI program
is MPI init.
That's initializing the MPI subsystem.
That doesn't mean it has to
be the first thing in your program.
But it has to be the
first MPI call in your program.
Now, in this case, it's
passing it two null pointers here.
We won't generally be doing that,
but they probably wanted to
avoid a bunch of complexity here.
So, they're just saying we're not
passing any parameters
to those two things.
And then this call 13 and 14.
Okay, here we go.
All right.
We'll pretend that William has
been a process that's been executed.
William is like loading up.
He's starting up.
He's like, all right, cool.
I got this.
I initialized my stuff.
How does William know which process he is?
You know how I said
that when MPI started, it said,
hey, you're process five.
You're process six.
Well, how does the
program figure that out?
Well, it has to ask for its rank.
So, that's how you
figure out, hey, remember,
if you ask for 10 processes,
10 copies of this
exact same program are running.
The only thing to differentiate those
programs is which rank it is.
And you have to then determine
what you want each process to do
as a function of its rank.
In this program here, what are they doing?
One process is sent into another process.
That means that one process
can only be due as Sydney.
And the other process can
only be due as receiving.
Well, how does that process
know which process he is?
By doing this matter right here,
doing this call, it says, hey,
give me the size of my communicator.
Excuse me.
Give me the size of my communicator.
That means how many
processes are there total?
And when you did like dashy
enter, dashy empty, we said 10.
So, the communicator size is 10.
So, now, notice communicator
size is an integer variable.
But the prototype for this C
function indicates that
it takes two parameters,
the name of the communicator.
And by the way, you
think of communicator like a group.
And for nine tenths of our class,
this communicator is always
under the MPI com world.
It means it's all the processes.
So, that will always be
that for the first parameter.
What is the second parameter?
It needs to be a pointer
to where you can write the data
for the number of processes.
So, you have to take the
address of operator here to do that.
So, when you call this function,
it's going to go and put
into the memory of this process,
this particular process is running,
how many processes there are total.
So, like, if there
are 10 processes running,
they're all going to have
a variable called com size,
and it's going to be equal to 10.
But now, when he calls this, it says,
give me my rank inside that 10.
That's what this com rank does.
And again, you're passing
the address to us.
With this stuff in this class,
if you worked real good
with pointers and stuff before,
that's going to be a problem in here.
Because everything we're doing is
in C in this class,
except for some plotting, and
we'll do that in Python.
But, like, the actual stuff is in C.
So, we're going to
be doing pointers like this,
and you're crazy.
Not just one star,
but multiple, multiple stars.
Okay, so, you know,
stars, stars, stars, stars.
It's going to be crazy.
So, I'm just letting you
know that the assumption is
you know that because
356 is a prerequisite,
and it's in C.
Okay?
So, that's what's happening here.
So, now, this process knows, hey,
there's 10 processes, and
I'm the fifth one.
Cool.
Then it says, hey, now,
if my rank is not zero,
so, like, the fifth guy would be like,
so, I'm not, I'm not going to be zero.
Cool.
Well, then, I'm going to...
S print F means string print F.
That's what S stands for.
So, string print F says, take this string
with these two specifiers or placeholders
to hold the value of
this integer and this integer.
So, what does that do in C?
It literally says that this percent D
is going to end this string.
It's going to put
an integer representation of this,
of that int in this place in the string
that's going to put an
integer representation in this string.
Apparently, it looks like
there's no carriage return here.
So, it's taking this string,
it's building the string up,
and it's putting a copy
of that string into greeting.
Well, what is greeting?
Well, greeting is the actual
array that holds the strings.
All right.
And you might say, well, why
the hell are they doing that?
Well, it's because the
string isn't known in runtime.
In compile time, you don't know
what that string is going to be.
You don't know which
process it's going to be.
You can't hard code that.
So, it's saying, all right, I'm
going to build me a string,
and I'll put that string into this buffer,
this string buffer.
And then, I'm going to send.
So, I'm going to send
that string to somebody else.
Now, look at how
exam parameters this thing has.
You might be, you know, how
do I know all this stuff?
First thing is in your book.
It tells you what all the parameters are.
Number two, there's a
thing called the MPI specification.
I'm going to show you where that is.
Any and everything you could
possibly want to know about,
every one of these functions, and
every little weird nuance about it
is in a book, okay?
This first parameter says, where is
the buffer that I want to send?
So, in other words,
greeting is a character array,
but that means that
greeting is actually a pointer
because arrays are pointers in C, right?
So, this first parameter in this
is always a pointer, all right?
Now, the next parameter is, how
many items do I want to send?
Items do I want to send.
String link says it's
the length of string, okay?
So, it's going to get the
length of the string over here,
and this string here
doesn't have any kind of,
it looks like it's got
a character term on here.
It also, it's like, where's
the end of the string?
The end of the string
is one at beyond the end.
Remember the slash zero
that means the string terminator?
That's why they're saying that
the length of the string plus,
yeah, by the way, one more element,
which is the null-terminating
character of the string.
And so, I'm like, cool, and that's
the number of elements I want to send,
but what is the data type of each element?
Oh, there are characters.
Now, inside there, right, something
would have to be like,
well, now, I know the
number of elements there are.
I know the number of bytes there are.
Excuse me, the number of,
the type of each element.
So, the number of bytes is equal to
this times the number
of bytes per whatever
this element is.
Now, a character in C happens to be what?
One byte wide.
All right, because this was a float,
maybe it's 32 bits wide, four bytes.
Or if it was a float, a double,
maybe it's 64 bits or eight bytes wide.
So, think about when you go to
send something from one place to another,
the dance center has to know how big it
is because it has to know how far down
in this buffer to read.
Hell, there might be things in
that buffer you don't want to send.
You just want to
send the first few things.
So, this is getting you to figure out
how many of the things you want to send.
Now, what is all this stuff?
Well, to be honest with you, I
don't remember the
difference between this parameter
and this one.
I don't remember right now.
But I know that one of these parameters
has to be the person I'm sending it to.
So, the way they've done this program is
you could start it
with, say, ten processes.
But this is if statement.
There's only two possible combinations.
I'm either going to, if I'm not
ranked zero, I'm going to send some stuff.
And else, if I am
zero, then what is it doing?
It's doing the buster receives.
How many receives?
It's inside of a for loop,
whatever the size of the communicator is.
So, like, let's say it was ten.
That would mean that I have process zero,
one, two, three, four,
five, six, seven, eight, nine.
It says, if I'm not zero, I'm
going to send my crap to zero.
Else, if I am zero,
I'm going to receive one
message after another inside of
a tightly nested for loop,
starting with process one, because I'm
not going to receive for myself.
I'm going to start receiving
from the other people, okay?
And then I'm going to go up to less
than ten, which will go
up to nine, all right?
And I'm going to do a receive, and
where am I going to be receiving it?
Now, remember, every one of these
processes is a copy of each other.
So, remember how there was
a character in the right greeting?
There are ten arrays in it.
So, over here, there's
a greeting, greeting, greeting, greeting.
Each one is 100 bytes long.
And this guy has a greeting array,
too, and it's exactly the same length.
Why? Because at the top
of the code, it hard-coded a
size that was based on
the max length of 100, right?
And then the thing is, in here, there's
a string that says,
hello from process one.
This one says, hello from
process two, hello from process three.
And this guy is going
to receive them what I've chosen.
And that for loop is going
to receive something from this one.
All right, now receive
something from that one.
something from this one.
And every time it does it, it receives
it and puts it in the same buffer.
Now, that means it's
overriding itself every time that
loop is putting it on top of each other.
But apparently, whatever they want
to do, they just want to
print out the string that
was just receiving in this buffer,
and then go receive that from that way.
Process zero will just be
like, I received something from
this guy, this guy, this
guy, this guy, this guy,
just to prove that, like, you
know, if you think about it,
I was able to run a multi-process
job and get something
different from every process,
and I've got processes
communicating with each other, right?
That's why it's called
your IDC, your process communication.
Does that make sense?
So that's what's happening here.
Now, I don't remember, like, which
of those, zero, the other one.
I don't remember. Let's just see
if we can figure this out, okay?
Now, what about if I was over there?
Look at that. It's hard
to close the thing over here.
And that seems to have been
30 minutes since that internal hazard.
Maybe it has. I feel like
something's up in my network today.
It's not great.
Let's go look at this.
We're going to come over here. We're
going to look for the MPI specification.
All right, so we're going
to go to MPI documents.
It's at the MPI form.org.
It just gives you a little history.
I think MPI came
out somewhere around 1995.
Let's see. Does it tell us in here?
Let's go back to the beginning.
We don't have it all
the way back to the beginning.
But I really came out around 1995.
I say that because I
graduated bachelor's degree in 1999,
and when I got to grad school, the
very first thing was, right, an MPI firm.
I was like, what the hell is this?
They'd only been out for a little bit.
And there were some standards before this.
You know, it's kind
of like Blu-ray versus HDD.
Like, some technology went out, and you
know, the MPI went out for this stuff.
Are there other things?
Sure, but it's not nearly why
it is accepted as an MPI.
So, apparently, 5.0 is out.
My God. That's crazy to think.
So, let's go ahead and get
inside the PDF document for this.
Now, this thing is gigantic.
I mean, not only is this PDF big,
but like, MPI, as
a justification, is enormous.
MPI can do a lot of things.
But they're pretty much all surroundings.
It all is about trying to support
sending stuff from
one computer to another,
or from many computers
to many computers, or
from one to many, or from many to one.
A lot of different scenarios.
Depending on how you're breaking data
up, how you want to send, whatever.
But what we're trying to find
here is MPI send and receive.
And that's part of
a thing
called point-to-point communication.
Because you're going to
go from one process
to another process, and that's all it is.
So, if we were to come in here
and look, and let's
go look from Control-F, point-to-point.
Find that. Point-to-point messages.
Oh, yeah, there we go.
First release came out in 1994.
All right, I was off by a little bit.
If we go and look in here, so we've
got terms and conventions, and
all this sort of stuff,
and language
binding, point-to-point communication.
Chapter three.
All right, cool.
So, send and receive.
Blocking, unblocking, yada, yada, yada.
Why don't we just go down to
chapter three and see what we see.
Oh, my God, look at this.
This is like the Hello
World program we're talking about.
There's a message that says
we'll only be 20 here.
Everybody's got what their rank is.
Now, look at that.
With their init, they're
doing a little bit
of a different kind of init than we did.
We passed the null pointer here, but
they're passing the address
to the argument count
and the address of the
argument vector that comes down.
Let's not worry about that for right now.
And it says, okay, cool.
Let me find out what my rank is.
And if I'm process zero,
then I'm going to string copy.
Now, you remember how our program
context was good at s-print app.
It printed one string
into another string dynamically.
Well, this thing is just saying, look,
copy this string is hard coded on others.
It's not building it up
as a function of other parameters.
And it's just copying
that string into here.
Now, why are they doing that?
Because they're trying to point
out that when you're sending stuff,
you need to have a buffer to
be sending things into and out of.
This is a hard coded string, which
means it's not actually in a buffer.
It's probably off the
stack inside your process.
Well, for that matter,
this is probably just two.
But it's like, what is
the name of the string?
There is no name in that string.
That's a hard coded
variable right inside the program.
Like, if I wanted to try to get
access to this string hello here, I can't.
I can't do that, right?
It doesn't have a name.
Well, that's what they're doing here.
They're like, cool.
Give it a name.
Take that string.
Put it inside that buffer.
And then send that buffer.
So send the message that you had
just put into here, the length of it,
plus one more byte
for the little terminating character,
sending MPI characters.
Now, notice they chose these
parameters here, 1 and 99.
So now it's clear to
me what these parameters are.
This means if I am rank 0, I
am going to send a message to rank 1.
And if I'm rank 1, I'm going
to receive a message from rank 0.
So in other words, I can now tell
from kind of, we'll
look at the prototype later,
but I can kind of tell here that
if you're sending, you
need to have a receiver.
And if you're receiving, you
need to have a sender.
And that has to match, right?
Like, that didn't match.
And this thing with deadlocks, you should
be trying to wait to receive something
from somebody that never sent anything.
You see what I mean?
So what in the hell is 99?
Let's go down here
and look at the prototype.
So it says, hey, now, in general, this
is what all parameters to MPI send are.
And then C, that looks like this.
And in FORTRAN, it looks like this.
They're not in here.
They don't know
the language there, because
that's the only one that are actually
supported and guaranteed to, you know, if
you say, I match the 5.0 specification,
that means that you exactly
match the stuff that's in here.
So the first parameter is when you're
sending, it's the address of the beginning
of the letter that you want to send.
This is the number of
things that you want to send.
This is the type of
each thing you want to send.
This is the destination of
where you want to send it.
So which process is going to get it?
And that thing right
there, that's called that tag.
That zero in our, that other zero that was
in the book and the 99 that was in the
example up there, that's called a tag.
Now, I want you
to imagine this, all right?
Say, say you got three processes.
Zero is going to receive from one,
and it's going to receive from two.
One of the things that you can do is
you can say, look, I want to receive from
anybody.
I'll receive from anybody.
As long as it's the data I'm looking for.
So think about that tag as a way of
being like, I don't know
who it might be coming
from, but if the tag matches
99, it's the information I'm looking for.
It gives you another ability to say, not
only do I want to send from this person,
but I only want to receive right
now stuff that's related
to this subject, 99.
So that's got to match.
Tags have got to match if you
want your senders and
receivers to pair up.
Now, there are some parameters in there.
You say, I'll receive from any process.
I'll receive from any tag.
All right, but what do we typically do?
We're going to do this for the
time being until
we get more sophisticated.
We're going to have to note to
who and from whom
we're sending and receiving,
respectively.
And the tags, we're just going
to make sure that the tags match.
Okay?
You can also make it
do stuff like in priority order.
Like, you could be like, well, I want
to receive all tags
of zeroes because that's
the highest priority.
And then I'll go to
one because that's lower priority.
You can do stuff like that if you
want to handle stuff
according to some priority
thing.
So we look at it.
The first thing's a pointer.
The second thing's an int because it's the
number of items, the type of each item,
the rank destination, the
tag that has to match.
And then finally, this rank is a
rank with respect to
some group of processes.
And you might say, why do I
even need to save the common world?
Well, right now, in this
example here, this is common world.
It's everybody.
So rank five is rank
five with respect to this group.
But I could put another communicator here.
I could put
another communicator that's just
these four or five and are just these
five.
And now, let's say I call this
communicator Will and I
call this communicator Jones.
There's a thing for
you to create communicators.
You can, communicators
can obviously really
include processes that are part of the
whole, all of processes.
Well, now, what would the rank
of this process be in Will?
It'll still be zero to four.
Now, with respect to common world,
the ranks are one through nine.
But for this Jones communicator, process
five is actually ranked zero, one, two,
three, four like this.
So when you send and receive, you
have to mean with
respect to which grouping,
which naming convention
am I talking about?
You're like, well, it's everybody.
I'm just talking
about the standard everybody.
And that's what that last
parameter is right
there, the communicator.
Like I said, nine times out of
ten for everything we're
doing right now, that's
just going to be MPI Comm World.
It's just because we're not going to
be creating our own communigators on the
process.
But that's typically what you do
later when you
get into collective communications,
sending to just some people but not
others or some weird patterns or whatever.
Does that kind of make sense?
Now, in this interface that we were
at over here, as I mentioned, you know,
you can edit files straight
in this little web page.
You don't have to use VI or
Emacs or whatever to do it over there.
Hell, you could be doing it on
your own computer, pushing it up there,
trying to run it, doing all your things.
You could be using
a Git repo somewhere and
push it to a Git repo and then pull
it down over there on the other side.
Or you could literally, if it wasn't
too complicated, you could just sit here,
you could say, all right, cool, I'm
going to open up my home directory.
I'm going to go into 473.
I'm going to go into the source directory.
I'm going to go into this directory.
And I'm going to open
up the Hello World program.
And I'm going to look at it
here so I can look at it.
But what about if I want to edit it?
I'm going to come back over here.
I'm going to edit it.
Here it opens up
a little crappy text editor.
You can edit right here.
You can just save, and that's going to
write it back out over to the file
system over there on the cluster.
So you can do that.
Does that make sense?
So whatever is good for you.
Git repos, pushing and
pulling, SEP-ing, stuff globalists.
You can do it through here if you want to.
You've got five or six files you
need to edit at the same time,
but then you'd have to have
five or six tabs over here.
And maybe you get your thing set
up on your own computer with MDI
so you can do all your work
kind of locally to make sure it works.
And then later, you just got to
remember it's got to work on expanse
because that's where I'm going to run it.
It's on expanse.
Then you copy it up there.
See it makes sure it works up there.
Prove that it works.
Cool, there you go.
Or it's not even
about proving that it works.
We're doing this for performance analysis.
Well, if we want to run
up something up to 128 cores,
you don't have 128
cores in your laptop probably.
If you did, you probably
wouldn't be in this classroom.
The...
It sounds bad, but I just
feel like I don't even have...
There's all things that
are in the laptop's number
that's going to get cores right now.
But my...
The other point is, if
you're going to do tiny analysis,
you have to run it on a
computer that has the
right number of resources
so that you can figure out how fast it is,
how slow it is, how
long it's going to scale,
how long it's going to do this,
how long it's going to do that.
Does that make sense?
So now, I had said, I
want you to read chapter two
in the book in that rehab that I sent.
Keep saying, I want you to read.
If you haven't read chapter
two, just please read it.
It's not really that long, okay?
But one of the things
that it talks about here,
we're going to kind of be...
Like, I like a
lot of the theoretical stuff,
but I get it a lot of students don't.
And if you hear a bunch of theory stuff
before you actually run
any programs, you're like,
you don't have any idea
what we're talking about, right?
So I'm going to try
to, in this semester, mix it
where we're going to do
a little bit of theory,
a little bit of writing a
program that improves
what we're talking about,
a little bit more theory in
our program, you know what I mean?
Like that, rather than
talking about all this theory
and then showing you
the thing on the computer.
That makes sense.
So to that end, one of the next
things I'm going to want to show you
is a program that
actually does something real
and then a way to time
it to see how it's doing,
so it's just putting
in some time and stuff,
and then be able to compare that timing
to what we would have
expected the timing to be
based on the theory of it.
Does that make sense?
Now, they talk about that, what do
we expect it to be in Chapter 2?
So let's go to Chapter 2 down to
the part where they
start talking about that.
There we go.
So they say, okay, let's
suppose the number of processes
or whatever we're talking about,
maybe it's the number of cores,
the number of nodes,
the number of threads,
it's wherever the
parallelism is coming from.
It's P, and the serial runtime is T serial
and the parallel runtime is T parallel.
Let's say they call it that, all right?
And let's do a real example
while they're doing this over here.
We'll kind of play around with this.
Let's suppose, you know, I'm in, you know,
say quicksort, and we run it, and we
find that it takes 35 seconds to run.
All right.
So, serial, that means that
P is the number one,
meaning that there's only one node,
only one thread, only one core.
All right.
And we run our program,
and for P equals one,
so in other words, the serial time,
we found that it was 35 seconds.
Then, using what we're
going to learn in here,
we figure out how to
write a parallel version of quicksort,
and we run it.
Okay?
What are we hoping that when we run it,
we hope that T will be
less than or greater than 35?
Less, because that was on point.
Doing it parallel is
going to take less time.
Right?
So, let's say that on, say,
T on, where P equals two,
we hit this thing, and it
turns out to be 20 seconds.
So, we're like, ooh, that's
less than 35, that's good.
That's what they're talking about here.
All right.
Now, in an ideal world, in an ideal world,
the amount of time that
you would take in parallel
would just be the amount of time
it takes when it's on one process
divided by the number
of processes that there are.
Right?
Because, you know, the
original thing, you know,
took one hour on one core.
You hoped that it would take
half an hour on two cores.
Right?
You agree?
So, that's right.
I mean, that's what you expect.
So, like, in a, this
is ideally, okay, well, now,
what would, if we applied that to this,
that would mean that
the time on two, ideally,
should have been 35 divided by two.
Now, what is 35 divided by two?
How much is that?
17.5.
This is like the shortest time
that we expect it would ever take.
That's the best case scenario.
Did it actually run in 17.5 seconds?
No, it ran a little bit longer than that.
So, does that mean it's
as good as the ideal case?
No, but it's pretty close.
It's pretty close, right?
Everybody getting it so far?
Okay, whoa.
Now, speed up.
Speed up.
It's equal to the time
it takes on one process
to divide it by the
time it takes on p processes.
But, like, if you were
actually running it in real life,
you would measure how long it
takes to run on one core.
You would measure how long it
takes to run on two cores.
And you would then take this and say,
the speed up on p processes is
the time that I measure for one process
divided by the time
I measured on p processes.
And I would divide them and
I would get an experimentally determined,
experimentally determined,
you measured it.
And then you get one over here.
Well, the time on one
process, our other example, is 35.
The time we got when we ran
it on two processes experimentally was 20.
Now, somebody said, what
is 35 divided by 20?
1.75.
All right, is it 1.75?
Let's see.
1.75 times.
1.75 x.
Perfect.
So, 1.75.
That sounds pretty good.
Like, if I was making 1.75
times the amount of money issued
that I made last year, I would be happy.
But how much money, in an ideal
case, if I had
the same analysis situation,
I would make it twice as much.
So, in an ideal case,
so speed up, ideally,
is supposed to be equal to time on one
divided by the time on P.
The time on P, ideally, is that.
So, it's T1 divided by P.
Well, if I do that out,
that's T1 times P over T1.
T1 cancel out, and I get P left.
So, the speed up should be equal
to the number of resources I'm using,
like P threads or P
cores or P nodes, right?
So, it should then, in this case,
so ideally, it should
have been equal to P,
which P was equal to 2, which would
have meant that the speed up on 2
ideally should have been 2x.
But it wasn't.
It was 1.5x, and it
was slightly worse than that, right?
So, you get this graph of,
you've got the speed up over here,
you've got the number of processes, cores,
whatever it is,
resources we're talking about.
And if you've got one core,
then, you know, that speed
up factor is a 1.
You know, if it's 2,
then ideally it should be 2,
because that's what it says here.
Ideally, it would be ideally.
So, in an ideal world, it
would literally be a straight line.
Your speed up would be exactly equal
to the number of processes you've had.
So, it was over here,
and this was 100 processes.
This would mean that
it was 100 times faster.
But you will never get that in real life.
It will be something less than that.
Put an asterisk right there,
but sometimes you will get that.
Sometimes we can get better than that.
You'll wonder what's going on,
and there's other explanations for that.
But in general, this is
the best you can get.
Now, what did we just
get when we went to 2?
When we went to 2, we looked
at the experimental
thing that we measured.
It only came up to 1.75.
And 1.75 will maybe be like right here.
So, the curve might go over here, and
then what might happen
when we go over here,
it might start doing like this.
And eventually, you're going to
actually start doing something like that.
So, this would be like maybe the
real, this is the
experimentally determined speed up.
And this is the ideal
speed up, the max speed up.
And really, you want this curve to be as
close to that curve as it possibly can be,
because the further they are apart from
one another, the worse it is, right?
That's like how far you are from getting
the max that you
should have been getting, right?
Does that make sense?
Now, you will almost always see that
if you pump P up far enough,
this will start having like a
slope that's getting less and less
until such a time as it becomes negative.
But it would really be
cool, even if there was
a gap here, if the gap was a linear gap.
Let's say this, another program
had this speed up curve.
Now, this slope is going
to be less than that slope.
That means that the gap
here is actually getting bigger,
but it's getting bigger at
the same rate that P is.
So this would be ideal speed up.
This would be like a linear
speed up, because it's a line.
But a line is pretty damn good.
That means that there's like
no need of the curve.
It never goes like this.
It starts going down.
If you've got enough cores, it
just keeps your right eye going up.
That would be really scalable, like if
you could really scale your problem up.
This is not scalable.
Look at this.
Imagine in your computer
you have 100,000 cores.
So 100 cores is not really
that much out of 100,000, right?
But that 100,000 doesn't
do anything for you
if the best you ever get is right there
and after that starts going down.
It doesn't matter that you've
got 1,000 times more resources
to bring to bear on the problem.
It doesn't help you in fact.
It hurts you.
You see what I mean?
So the only way that you can make use of
all your resources is if
the speed up keeps going up,
hopefully at the same rate.
Now, some of them might say
like, we're at the end of class.
They might say, why don't
you get this ideal speed up?
Well, that's because the only way
you could get the ideal speed up
is if you actually did half the
work in each process and didn't get it.
But think about that NPI program.
Even if you have like an array
where you have to work on one,
you have to work on the
other, and did
they exchange some information?
The sequential version of the
program never exchanged any information.
You didn't need to.
That's extra stuff that
your other program never did.
That means that there's always going
to be some kind of overhead
that's making it not be as good
as it would be by simply just saying,
it's not going to be one
piece the amount of time a day.
It's never going to be PX faster because
there's work that you
weren't even doing before.
It's less like apples and apples.
It's like, hey, you know, I
was able to lift, you know,
this many bags into the truck
and there's two students and, you know,
it's like, yeah, but the two
students didn't have to separate the bags
and they did all this stuff.
It's like, it's not twice as fast
because there's extra
stuff that's going on
that never had to go on to begin with.
The students had to talk to each other to
figure out who's going
to pick up this bag,
who's going to do that.
It's like, you don't have to do
any of that when you've got one court.
There's only one court
and there's only one process.
There's only one threat of execution.
So that's why this stuff happens.
That's going to be a subject of discussion
if you hit this over and over again
about, like, what are all
the limiting factors for scalability?
So I'm going to get a small
assignment up there by just, you know,
running a little one of these
little, something a
little more complicated
in the hello world that we have there,
just to prove that
you got into the system,
you did some stuff, took some
screenshots, you tried a couple of things,
you put it into a Word document
and you submit it along with your code.
Like, it's just kind of a proof of, like,
you're into the system and you can do so.
That's the idea.
See you guys next time, all right?
Remember, read Chapter 2 if you
haven't read it and come prepared
to have a small quiz
at the beginning of the class.
One question from Chapter 2, all right?
For next thoughts?
Yep.
Okay.
It's not letting me get any Spanish here.
So I'm going to actually go on the portal.
Yep.
This is the right world, right?
I can't see your screen. I'm sorry.
Sorry, I didn't go in.
All right, so here's the thing.
Show me that you can get into Access.
And they've come down to my office
and we'll take a look at that, too.
Do you have time right now?
Yeah, I've got some time.
All right.
I think this is Access CR right here.
Yeah.
Let's see.
All right.
Let's come down here and see
what we can figure out, all right?
Let's see.
We can try a couple of things.
Like, we can try it on my computer.
We can try it on your computer.
We can see, like, with your account.
And just see, like, is
it something going on with yours?
Is it the cookies?
Do we need to erase the browser history?
Can you remember when you were in the
class when I said
I have problems sometimes?
Yeah.
I have to find a
community sub-out because
whatever they do,
they need to call that stuff together.
It doesn't seem to be real reliable.
At least in my opinion.
You got an email with
the user name, though, right?
Yeah.
Did I respond to
you and said, thanks, right?
Carbon faded and pasted the thing, too.
You wrote your back and
said, did I do that?
And I'm asking.
I don't think so.
All right.
Let's take a look.
That could be a problem, too.
All right.
But I do remember you sending
me an email where you got it.
And what I tried to do
on every student that sent me one,
I said, you know, thanks.
And I copied and pasted it, proof
that I had added it in the system.
If I didn't do that for
you, then maybe I didn't do it.
So let's go see if
that's what the issue is.
It could be.
Let's see.