Yeah, thanks for having us. Don't worry.
I'm not sick. I got you understood.
Uh, how's everybody doing today?
Sounds great. Just seriously. Uh, you can
go around the room and just ask,
like, uh, the questions we've seen here by
like, uh, did you work a job last
summer and it's a what
was it, uh, what was that?
Like, look, like, where was
it? Virtual online and person.
Cool. Uh, Anthony,
uh, my analytics, analytics.
Okay. Is the my analyst thing is
in person job. Yeah. All right. Uh,
yeah. What is your first name? Colleen.
Colleen. What, uh, what did you do this
past summer in terms of job
here in the beach or back home?
And what's your name? Adrian radius. Yeah.
All right. Uh, what did you do?
I left in the hotel. Okay. Will you
did a remote work for a tax company?
Was it cool? Yeah. It was nice. Awesome.
What, uh, what kind of environment is
it primarily? And like,
what was the framework
or whatever? Uh, it
was an individual studio
and they did a C sharp. I see.
So the classes you had
here probably helped some for that.
I guess a three 30 with
Cox almost exactly like it. Awesome.
I'm really going to try and
get better. What is your name? Okay.
What did you do?
Okay. Is that, is that the place
that we have that
relationship with with the
college of human performance
business and all that?
Was it good?
I can't hear you. Well,
dog room. What was that like?
Well, I was a high school teacher, but
she was saying like, I'll be a dog
grammar. I'm like, okay.
That sounds, that sounds cool.
I'm thinking though,
that like these aspects
of it, just like any job, there's
going to be good things and bad things.
But yeah, I see that. Was it
like a thing where
people would like schedule
it alone advanced or they
would just bring in like walk-ins?
Let's see.
I just want to get a
car wash. Car wash. All right.
Next student. What did you do?
What about over here?
How was that?
Pretty slow.
It's pretty slow because
I don't have to wait.
Basically.
Some days.
Like two days.
So they didn't have like a test
server versus a
production server that they
would stage at first to test
to see what happened or what.
I could, I could test on my
own, but it was hard to do that.
I had to work with like two databases.
The one version of my machine was like my
S3 on the end and in production it was
EB2.
So what we were doing on my
machine and you know, I'd be like, okay,
there's just too many issues and
we'll work on the EB2 in production.
That's cool.
What about you?
Yes, sir.
Where it is.
It's cool, man.
That was your second summer.
Okay, that's really cool.
So I gotta say
between last time we were in here and
this time I met with one of the division
leaders there about the idea of like,
hey, you know, we've got some folks that
are like finding positions here.
It was already like I'd love for them
to like do like, come on campus to
recruiting because they're only three
and a half hours away.
And so they were, they're super minimal.
See, I didn't like coming out
to career fair and all this stuff.
So I'm hoping that
we get them actually here.
I know you've already got something
lined up with them anyway, but I'm
thinking like the rest of our students
like to learn more about what the
opportunities are, you know,
like this sort of stuff.
I think, how many of you
know, like know
what Savannah River National
Lab is or Savannah River Site is?
So I mean, it's like, yeah.
They were talking about that this year.
I didn't get to figure out.
There's already this
hospital there's going
to be like, USB clubs and
going to take orders.
And I know the main
focus schools, you know, the U.S.
can make a difference right there.
Of course, of all the
women there, I know these persons.
And I hope people even form by Canada.
Yeah.
I feel like given our proximity to
them, that there should be like more
because of the growth that they're
going to probably experience over the
next five to seven years is
going to necessitate a bigger workforce.
So I'm thinking Coastal might as
well be a player in that, right?
Getting our students having
cool jobs there and stuff.
Yeah, there should be.
I don't know who's in, we
haven't hired them in the same time.
Yeah, I mean, it's going
to be a huge change, right?
I mean, you know, they have
that data center that they're going to
build there, which is, think about it.
That's one of the only five sites
that the Department of Energy or the
building a data
center on federal property.
And number two, the production that
they're going to be trying to
ramp up there.
That's going to be a gigantic
effort and that's going to necessitate
like probably these huge numbers that
he's talking about to be hired.
I mean, those kind of numbers would make
it be up there at the top of some
of the biggest national
labs in our country.
So there's a lot of growth here
if you wanted to stay in this area.
One of our students that graduated a
year ago, he just got a full-time job
there is like an N.L. engineer.
And he just sent her new solutions.
He's loving it, you know.
What's that?
Okay, well, there's two people now.
I'm thinking about a G.E.S. laws.
Do you remember him?
A G.E. got there.
What is Avion doing?
I know you're working on it.
Okay.
I mean, I don't know.
To me, it's a cool connection
that we should be trying to exploit.
Cool summer.
What about you?
I got you.
Work here or are they not really
doing that as much as they used to?
I know that they've, you know, hired
some before, but it's not clear to me,
like, obviously, there's not
enough position for everybody.
What about you?
Yes, I did work with
both of you over the summer.
Okay.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
I've been seeing the posts
about that and traveling and stuff.
That looks cool.
What about you?
Graduating this semester?
Mike, what about you?
Oh, you weren't here for the question.
What did you do this past summer?
And where did you do it?
Yeah, I worked at
a local data analytics company.
What's it called?
My analyst.
Oh, so that's the same
one that Anthony works on?
Oh, okay.
Was that your first time there?
Cool.
All right.
I just wanted to kind of get a sense
of who else doing what,
you know, this past summer.
So, yeah, you know, as
the semester goes on, I
mean, you know, if you
want to talk about, like, you
know, some of the opportunities
that are at places like
SR now and SRS and
Los Alamos and Argonne and Oak
Ridge and T and the Nell and all the other
19 other sites that there
are, there's, there's, you're not stuck
to a particular geographic location
and you're a U.S. citizen
and there's a lot of
opportunity at some of these places.
Some that doesn't
require citizenship maybe
requires permanent residence
or green card status.
But like, you know, generally some of the
ones that are more
of national security require citizenship.
But, you know, 90% of students
that come to Coastal are U.S. citizens.
So, like, that's a
free, you know, rich, fake
demographic of folks because
if you look at some
of these other schools,
especially in the graduate program,
I mean, U.S. citizenship is
very, very low, super low.
Like, I mean, I bet
right now Carnegie Mellon, there's less
than 1% of their graduate students
in computing that are U.S. citizens.
So, that's a big sector of the job market
that, that, you know, kind
of narrows things down, right?
I mean, so that's something we want to do.
Let me know and we can try to
talk about how to look those things up.
So, what the log in here to access EI and
show you what I see when I look at this.
So, let's see here, we got the
two-factor authentication mass,
which hopefully will work.
Oh, I got my phone silence, so
it doesn't want to pop up there.
Let's see, Duo, Prove.
Oh, and that's not up there.
Okay, here we go.
Sorry, I thought it was, I
thought that the screen was up there.
There we go.
So, log in here to the
allocations that we have on the platform.
And so, we have this
allocation of resources to the 2026.
So, get us through
this academic school year
that we've got, you
know, 100,000 credits available.
We've got 48,000 credits on
the San Diego Superimputing Center.
Superimputing are called Expanse, which is
the name of the fifth year.
And then we've got some
storage or whatever as well.
And then you've got, you know,
our students here that are here.
So, come over here.
These are the people that
are currently in the system.
So, I think, you know, I've tried to add
as many of you
guys who've written your stuff,
add them to the list here.
And typically, there's about
a 24-hour lag between
the time that you, well, let me be clear.
The time that I read your email
and I interview you into this thing.
So, after you make an account, but
after I add you to this thing,
it might be about 24 hours after
that that you can then use the system.
It's not instantaneous for
whatever reason, because that
just seems to be the way it is.
So, anyway, I want to talk about
this, the resource we have access to.
The only thing about access CI is
the thing that, you
know, brings together allocations
on lots of different
supercomputers across the nation.
We've historically, Coastal always
worked with San Diego.
There's no reason for that.
It was one of the first places that had,
like, a bunch of free
credits that we could use.
And we just keep pumping
them for resources every year.
So, my thought is, like, why
change something if this is work?
So, I want you to take a look, we go over
to Google, and we type
in the San Diego Supercomputing Center,
Expanse User Guide.
So, that's the, Expanse is the name of the
supercomputer there that we're
going to be dealing with.
They're writing our parallel jobs on and
running it and all this sort of stuff.
But it'll bring up this user guide here.
And when you come in
here, and I see the format
has changed here a little bit
from what it used to be.
You kind of read a
little bit about what it is.
You know, it's a Dell supercomputer.
It's got 5.16 petaflops.
So, it's got, let's see, the compute
nodes by these processors, this much RAM,
these Nvidia cards, you kind
of get like a list
of all of this stuff
and how it works or whatever.
So, it's got 728 nodes in it,
each of which has this in it.
So, two sockets,
128 cores per motherboard.
You know, not a huge amount
of RAM, but, you know, decent.
It's got a local SSD
card that's NDME PCIe SSD device,
which means you got really fast read
and write speeds locally on the node.
But that's not really
where your data stuff lies.
Like that would be like a
temporary place you could put some stuff.
The GPU nodes, 52 of these Nvidia V100
CPUs that are in the Xeon and Intel.
And then there are some
large memory machines like, for example,
it has four nodes that each
of which have two terabytes of RAM.
So, those are called
your large shared memory nodes.
But we're probably not
going to mess with those.
As you can see, there's
not very many of those.
So, we don't need to play with
that to do the stuff we're doing.
The network that it
has is pretty fast here.
It's high data
rate, infinite band, interconnect.
So, this is that thing I was
talking about, super high
bandwidth, super low latency.
The network, you know,
2.5 terabytes a second.
I mean, that's a lot.
It uses network file system and Seth.
It's got 12 petabyte local storage.
That's a lot.
And it's running Linux.
And you can come down in here and read
about what you've got to do to access it
and all this sort of stuff.
This is going to be
your go-to guide when you
can't figure out how to
do something on this machine.
Like, this will be kind
of the place to look.
There's a lot here. You can
see the way the scroll art is.
There's a lot of stuff here.
But if you look at the
top, we should have, let's see.
Let's do a control F for the word portal.
The exchange user portal.
So, I'm going to go in. Let's
see. Open this in a new tab.
All right. So, let's
see what we've got here.
Just wanted to look up our organization.
Now, let's see if it's got access.
A-C-C-E-X-S-E-I.
So, the way we, when I asked you
to use method two to create an account,
that means it wasn't
tied to, like, Coastal.
It wasn't tied to anything.
It was tied to your Coastal email address,
but it wasn't tied
to Coastal's authentication system.
Not that, maybe that works nowadays.
Historically, I found that, like, that
federated authentication with
Coastal didn't work,
because Coastal didn't have some stuff set
up, exactly correct, to make that happen.
So, that's why I said use method two.
Method two means I don't have it
associated with anybody other
than the access people.
All right. So, let's try
this and see what happens.
I don't know if this
is even going to work.
I haven't tried it since a year
ago when I was teaching this class.
And, of course,
accessing Expanse won't work
until I've added you to the thing, right?
Even if you've got the
Access CI login, what you send
it to me, I add it
to the system 24 hours later,
then you'd be able to get into the system.
And it appears to be that
we're, you know, in the system here.
Our login is wmjones.
That's my, that's my user ID on Access CI.
And you can kind of see there's
a number of things that you could do.
For example, I didn't open up a shell.
You know, I can go over
here and look around in here.
I can open up my file system over
there and push things
up there, pull things down,
rather than having to use some
other methods that are for loading files,
like using what's called Globus, which
is kind of a thing like,
I can kind of imagine it
as being this really fancy FTP-type thing,
but with all kinds of security.
You can actually just open it up in
your browser and push
and pull things down,
you know, from your web browser.
But eventually, you know,
you'll come over to,
you know, be able to open up a shell,
you know, and right now
we're almost called the login node.
This is really critical.
Okay, I want to make sure
I, make sure I explain this.
I think they have maybe four login nodes,
and depending on how loaded each one is,
it will automatically forge you to
a particular one of those nodes, right?
If you think about, like, once
you think about this is the supercomputer
that we have access to, these
login nodes, like login is zero one,
login is zero two, da da da.
You log in from the
outside world into one of these,
but you do not run anything on those.
You don't run anything on
that, because if you do,
they're going to come in here and they're
going to lock you out of the system.
Here's why.
How many people do you think are
actually logged into this thing right now?
If you're going to go and run a
program, it's going to
take 25 minutes to run,
it's going to hog up the CPUs.
Does that sound like a good idea
that it's a shared
system, what everybody else?
I don't know.
So let's see how many
people there are on this thing.
So we're going to do a who there.
So let's see, pipes,
word count, that shell.
So 128 people will log in right now.
If we were to run something
really computationally expensive
on this node,
that possibly screws up
their ability to even
just be sitting there
doing little basic commands, right?
You do that enough,
they will lock you out.
And there isn't anything
I can do about it.
That's violating their
terms and conditions.
Now, does that mean if you run, like,
a little Hello World
program, that's a problem?
No, it's not a problem.
But if you hit enter
and it doesn't more or
less come back in two
or three seconds, that's too long.
Especially if you're talking about
on the order of minutes.
They have a little thing that monitors
how long everybody's
process has been running
and how much CPU
has been consumed and they
get a little report
and a little notification send.
Depending on how egregious it is, the
human being gets involved
or gets too egregious
and they're shooting the dead.
They just go and kill it and just kill it
and lock the account up,
you know, that's what you do.
So this is, like,
what would be considered a
login note where we
could do some basic stuff.
You know, we can come in there
and see, like, what's in our directory.
We can run some compilers, like, we
can then run, like, our GCC compiler.
We can do some
basic little things in here.
But when we go to
get ready to actually run
one of the programs, it's
going to take a long time,
then we're going to need
to go and figure out
how do we submit jobs
to run in SLURM, okay?
And right now, we're not
going to worry about that.
And not everybody even has
accounts in this thing yet.
But that's why I'm telling you that it's
important to go in and get this account
because we need to just get
our feet wet, even accessing the computer,
much less trying to run
a real program and do something.
Just logging in and getting all the pieces
of parts is going to take a bit, okay?
So please, if you haven't
already gotten me that, please
get it to me by the end of the day today.
And I know that not everybody's got
it because I haven't gotten enough emails
if they're equal to the
number of people within the class.
So that's, you know, I
know we've got a problem.
I'd rather, the first
time we play with it,
that everybody be able to follow
along and, like,
actually see what's happening
if you want to
bring your laptop or whatever.
Remember, these things
are being recorded, and
did anybody check to see whether or not
you could actually see the
YouTube videos from the first class?
It worked. All right, cool.
So I'm also going to try to have
it where I have a summary for everyone,
so it's easy to figure out, like,
what do we talk about there each time?
But also inside of YouTube, you
know, it does have the transcripts,
so take that, do a
summary, post it on our page,
and then you can go back and figure out
which one to switch,
and that sort of thing.
All right, so let's get back to the book.
All right, now, I put,
like, a version of the repo.
I put it on inside
the file directory on Moodle,
so you can download source
code, you can download the slides.
Late yesterday, I got a set of
updated slides that
were from Professor Hickman,
Megan Hickman, that she taught 473
last semester when I wasn't here,
and she made some cool improvements to
them, and she handed them to me.
Now, I tried to upload this thing,
it was only 670 megabytes this morning,
and it sat there forever. Now,
the other stuff I've loaded at home,
so I don't know if there's something going
on here at Coastal or what, but I can't.
I just sat there for 20 minutes and it
never came back, so
I don't know what's happening.
I'll get those up there so
you can have the new slides.
What's in there? There's
the slides for the book,
and then there's what's
called some guided practice
things that the author
has to get together.
My stuff has that in it, too,
but, you know, we're going to use hers
because I guess she's
made some changes or whatever.
Plus, I like the fact that
there's some cooler imagery in this,
and I thought I had
some, so we'll use that.
So, let's go in here into
Chapter 2 and look at this.
Now, the way this is organized
is that Chapter 2 says, hey, now,
you've got your software,
you've got your hardware, here's
the reason why there's
some issues with this stuff.
Here's how kind of parallelism works.
Then in Chapter 3, they go, okay, one
way to do parallelism
is with message passing,
and they're going to introduce you to
something called the MPI,
the message passing interface,
which is the standard that's commonly
used 99% of the world for multi-node,
high performance computing
for scientific applications
and all this sort of stuff.
Then they do, I think, P threads.
Let's see. Is that what it is?
Yes, they do P threads, so
multi-threaded programming for
a shared memory system.
After that, then they
do what's called OpenMP.
And I think that this year, I'm
going to do it in that order.
I don't normally, I normally go and
do P threads, then MPI, then this,
but let's do it in the
order that the book has to.
It's got its pros
and cons, because there's some
things that are really
challenging about MPI up front
to even get it working that you don't have
with the threads, but
the threads are super limited.
I want to just give
you this little idea here.
If you talk about the amount of effort it
takes for you to
write a program in parallel
and the resulting performance that you're
going to get out of it,
like the bang for your buck, if you
will, and the effort you put into it,
the graph looks kind of like this.
So this is performance,
and this is your effort.
With OpenMP, you can just put
in a little bit of effort,
and you can get a lot of performance out,
and in some way it kind of tickers off.
You can't really do it more with OpenMP.
On the P threads, it
generally takes a bit more effort,
but you can do some things
in here you can't do over here,
and you kind of get to
the same kind of level here.
With MPI, MPI is a lot harder to
use, but it's more or less like this.
You can do things with
MPI, because this is multiple nodes.
P threads and OpenMP by themselves,
that only works on one node.
So, you know, that
expanse machine with 700 nodes,
you would never be able to use all
700 nodes writing just a P thread program
or just an OpenMP program.
But if you wrote a MPI
program, you could use all of those.
But writing an MPI
program is way harder to
get the same sort
of performance out of it.
And then later, you add all
these together, like this plus this,
and you get some kind
of thing that's like that.
You get the best of overalls.
Sometimes you use OpenMP for
doing work inside of a node,
and you use MPI to do
work a month of a node.
Then, of course, you add in things like
CUDA and other kinds of video type stuff,
and then you get the best of
overalls for using the CPUs and the GPUs.
But those two
things are heterogeneous, right?
Like the stuff that
you're doing on the GPUs
is different than what
you're doing on a CPU,
but that turns out to be a problem.
Remember that problem we did
the other day where we said,
that's why we ran into pieces?
Well, how are you going to split that
between the two cores and also the GPU?
Does it even make sense to do that?
The GPU might be doing it one way,
the other things with it some other way.
The GPU's faster, maybe.
So how do your load balance?
If you do it all of a
sudden, the GPU is done with this part,
but the CPU is still sitting
there chugging and
it's not doing anything.
Now the GPU is sitting unused, right?
So there's this hybrid nature that what we
would really like to be able to do
is use the CPU plus the GPU
to solve a problem across many nodes
using all of those things.
That's kind of like the holy grail, right?
A lot of times
it's not actually worth trying
to write something that
uses all of that hardware.
It might be like, you know what?
We're just going to use
the GPUs across multiple nodes
and we're not going to use any kind
of CPU except for to orchestrate the work.
The holy grail would be the two things
on the GPU that are good for GPUs
and do things on CPUs that suck on
a GPU and divide the work up that way.
So let's go ahead and
get started with chapter two.
You know, these are
going to be some slides.
Let's talk about this.
You know, when you run the...
I know you know a
lot of this stuff already, okay?
I'm just trying to go over it here.
Your program runs a lot
of different programs all the time.
If you open a task list or
task manager or looking at our processes,
we all know that
the operating system, you know,
is allowing multiple programs
to run at the
same time and have
access to this shared resource,
like your shared CPU, your shared
memory and all this sort of stuff.
And it tasks switches between them so
that it kind of uses this illusion
of multiple things running
at the same time,
maintains interactivity with the computer.
And the typical von Neumann architecture,
which is also sometimes referred
to as the stored program computer.
Now, this should be a little bit
of a review, at least from 210,
because in 210 we
talked about von Neumann,
our bottleneck and all this sort of stuff.
Remember, you've got your CPU over here.
It's connected to some sort
of bus, so a interconnection network.
And maybe that network is literally
like on the motherboard, you know?
And so we're not saying it's a network.
It's got ethernet cables
hanging out of it.
But like the
motherboard itself has networks
on it inside of the chip tab,
networks inside of the
chips, so things communicate.
It's just not a network like this
where wires are hanging out, you know?
And then you've got your RAM over here.
And you know how it is, right?
You fetch instruction from memory.
You bring that into the CPU.
The CPU decodes that thing.
It loads your registers up with
the appropriate things from any memory.
It executes that stuff,
and when it gets answers,
it sticks it back out here to make memory.
And the thing is, right, if the
CPU is being used
and there's multiple CPUs,
you've got multiple ones and these
things all happening at the same time,
all accessing this
main memory here, right?
So you can imagine that like at some
point you can't have
so many things running
at the same time, and all
of a sudden this becomes the bottleneck
because you just can't.
It's too much stuff trying to read
and write memory at the same time
and the whole system slows down.
And we've probably
experienced that, right,
when we run something that's
computationally expensive on our computer
and other stuff starts
sucking on the computer.
That's kind of the deal.
So, you know, you fetch the instructions.
You store the stuff back out of memory.
That's why they call it a bottleneck
because it's constantly
moving back and forth
between the CPU and the memory.
It's not great.
You know, how could you speed this up?
Well, you know, one way that
you can speed it up is,
by the stuff you learned about in 356,
you can have all these
separate processes that are running
in your context switching.
And, for example, you give a little
bit of time to the first process,
a little bit of time,
and you round rob it between these things.
Now, you could just do it as
a fixed policy like that and say,
you get one millisecond,
and you get another millisecond
and just go around like this.
But now the problem is
that some of these processes
probably have stuff that
they're not blocking on.
They're not waiting on
stuff from the file system.
stuff from the network.
They have instructions ready
to run right now.
So that's why you have, like,
the run queue and the ready queue
and the waiting queue and all
that sort of stuff back in 356,
because there's no reason to
task a switch between processes
that are waiting on
something in their block.
They may as well be
woken back up whenever whatever's ready
for them to go do their next thing, right?
So there's just different levels of that.
You learned all that.
And that's kind of a
type of parallelism here, right?
There's multiple things going
on at the same time,
but, like, the way this is drawn here is,
it's not really happening
at the same time.
Like, this process, you
know, it doesn't do anything
until this one is done.
So there's kind of this illusion, right?
And it's doing it so
fast that everything kind of seems
to be running at the same time.
It's not really, right?
It's multitasking.
But then, like, what you could do,
like in the class you learned about,
that same process comes out here.
It can spawn some threads.
And these threads can be
working at the same time.
So you form them.
You join them together.
Those are the terms that
you learned about at 356.
And this could be doing something
at exactly the same time as this.
And if there were multiple
functional units or multiple cores,
the sets of instructions and
data associated with this area
can gain access to processes at
the same time as this one.
And the good part about it is,
is that threads inside the same process
all have access to the same memory.
So, like, if you
have a variable in general,
like, let's say you
had an array over here,
and that was in this process A of 100,
over here, that thread
can access this array,
and so could this one.
In fact, if you want them to be different,
you have to do some
things so that they don't share.
But in general,
they share these locations.
Because they have the
same virtual address space,
because they're all inside the process.
And the memory manager
in the operating system
is only doing virtual address spacing
on a per-process basis,
not down to the
per-thread basis generally, right?
So, they come along, like I said,
they got multiple cores here,
so they got two CPUs,
both attached to a single RAM slot here.
And there's all a bunch
of stuff in here, right?
There's the sets of registers in here,
and there's this cache.
Now, how many people
know what cache memory is
and what it's for?
Surely somebody's saying
that, isn't that right?
Okay.
All right.
You've got the Von Neumann.
You've got your CPU,
and you've got your memory over here.
And let's say in that memory,
there's an array that you have here.
And you've got a tidiness of for loop.
It's just traversing every
element of that array,
doing some operation on it.
So, it's like, I'm going
to get A sub zero,
bring it over here,
do some work with it,
and put an answer back out of here.
I'm going to go grab the next one,
bring it over here,
and do some work to it,
and put it back out of here.
Well, that's stupid,
because if you're in an array,
and you're doing it one after another,
you know you're going to be executing
the very next instruction
that's going to execute on
the very next data thing.
Why don't you just go ahead
and bring a big block of this
and bring it from RAM all at once
so that the next time you use that array,
you don't have to get it from a memory.
You can store it in a
little place in here called the cache.
So, it's just like the cache,
like say, like your browser cache.
The other thing is browser cache, why?
What's the benefit of that?
So, it doesn't have to grab it again
pulling it across the internet?
Because why?
Because the internet's slow
compared to your hard drive over here.
Well, the same thing's true here.
This is very slow
compared to, say, stuff in here.
So, they break it up into what's called
the memory hierarchy, all right?
That's typically drawn like this.
They'll do like a little thing like this,
and over here might
be like your hard drive,
and then your RAM,
and then your level three cache,
and then your level two cache,
and then your level one cache,
where what's happening is,
in this direction,
it's getting a lot faster.
But it's also so fast,
but it's also expensive,
and it's also small.
Like, if this is
on the order of gigabytes,
then this will probably be on the order
of several, several nags.
This might be a matter or less,
and then you get down here,
and that's not gonna order a kilobytes.
Okay, like, if you
could have gigabytes in here,
you'd do that, but you can't.
You know, it's just, physically,
that doesn't work.
You can't put all of that stuff
down here in this level.
You gotta have a hierarchy.
So, the idea is,
that when you have that array in here,
if you're accessing it,
it takes like, say, like
a chunk of this array,
bring it up and copy it in here.
And it may be like a chunk of this array,
gets brought into here.
And then some chunk of that array
gets brought in here.
So, when the CPU access is A of I,
if that happens to be in this chunk,
and how do you know that?
That stuff is beyond
the scope of this class.
However, in 3.10,
if you take that as an elective,
they talk exactly how that works.
Right now, all we hear is,
conceptually, how it works.
Then, you can just grab
this out of this cache,
bring it up into some registers.
The cores interact
directly with the registers,
and when it's time for the answer
to be written back out of memory,
well, it can be written back out to this.
But then later, that can
be purged down into here.
And then later, that can go here.
And then sometime later,
when it's not being used,
it goes back in here.
Does that make sense?
That's kind of the way.
So, really big and cheap.
Like, the cost per byte inside of RAM
is cause for timing.
.0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0,
or what's sent, pinning, right?
I mean, per byte.
And then when you get up in here,
the cost per byte is way more.
And you finally get in here,
and the register is,
oh, there might only be,
like, a kilobyte or two registers.
So, that's really expensive, okay?
So, that's the reason why.
You can't have your cake,
you need two, so to speak, right?
That's what it's for.
so that, that thing we were
talking about by
accessing data, that's called
locality, principle of locality. And
there's two different types of locality.
There's what's called spatial locality
and temporal locality. Alright, like
imagine this loop. We've
got a thousand floats
in an array Z. We've got a running
sum. All this things doing is just going
from, you know, say the beginning of this
to the end of this plus equals the
element and it's making a sum. So we've
got, this is a big O of N, kind of
loop here. And, you know,
the very first element gets
access to this. The
very next element that gets
access to this. We know
that. If we look at
the loop structure, we can tell that,
right? So locality means, is it going to
access this same thing again sometime
soon? Is it going to access something
next to it soon? So spatial
means closer with
respect to location. Temporal
means close with respect to time. Okay? So
the idea would be is that the cause
you're doing, like we're saying, you're
accessing, if say right now you access
this location, there's a good chance
you're going to access something close
to it. Right? And then you
might say, well no, I mean,
no, not at all. Like in
that example you gave, there's a good
chance. But like in general, is there a
good chance? Let me think about it. Let me
ask you something. How
many programs have actually done
anything useful? Have done
something without arrays or data
structures or something? Nothing. They all
process data. The reason you write a
program is to process data.
That's not always true, right? I
mean, it's like a little microprocessor
inside of your microwave. That's not
the system we're talking about. That's
not how most of the people
don't care about that. The human
and the loop kind of things
that don't really matter. What matters
is, is that most everything deals
with stuff that has arrays or
structures, collections of
data that are close
to each other. Think about when
you do like data encapsulation in a
language. You're putting all those things
together. And those things couldn't be all
located in memory next to each
other. Meaning that when you access
it, if you just access an
element of the structure, is there a
good chance that in that class
you're going to access other things in
that class? So the instance of
that class might
actually have stuff packed
together in memory, you might
as well bring that whole thing
up close. Because your program exhibits
the locality. Now, if you have
a program that the way it
works is it just randomly accesses
everything everywhere all
over the computer.
Well, then it ain't going to
have a lot of new
locality. How many programs have you
ever had like that? That where
every instruction is some random thing
that's not related completely to any
other thing in the whole thing.
It's not, right? So nine times
out of ten, programs have locality.
So therefore, if a program
has locality, then it benefits
from this memory hierarchy. If
it doesn't have any locality,
it doesn't really benefit from
it. It actually, it hurts
it a little bit, not
much. But the thing is,
if 90% of your programs
have locality, only 10%, there's
hundreds of times speed up
having the thing for those
90% and only a very
small slowdown for the ones
that don't, that it's in
your best interest to have locality.
It's a computer that
has this memory hierarchy, okay?
That's kind of what
they're saying. This is also
referred to as like, you know, one of the
primary concepts in computer
organization, computer
architecture, that these
cash blocks exploit the
fact that your program has
locality. And if it
doesn't, it's not really that
big of a deal. But if it does have
that locality, you benefit
from it a lot, okay?
So when you have a
cash hit, what does the cash
hit mean? It means that the
thing you're looking for is actually
found in cash. Like, for
example, say you have a cash
here, this is cash you want
to draw on top of it,
this one over here, and
you ask for some sort of
variable x. Well, let's suppose that
x was in, it's obviously going
out here in RAM, so
this is RAM. But let's say
this x is not in here
and it's not in there, okay?
It hasn't been executed recently, it
hasn't been accessed recently, so it's not
in there. So whenever your CPU
goes and says, hey, give me x,
it goes in here and it
looks and says, hey, is x in
there? Ah, no. That's called a cash
miss, okay? Then it says, oh, it's
not in there. Let me go
check in here. Ah, no, it's not
in there. That's a cash miss.
Well, then if it's not in cash
and this is cash and this
is RAM over here, well, then obviously
it's going to be in RAM. Actually,
that's not true. Where might it be?
On this, that's something
that you learned about in
356. It has to first be moved from this
in RAM, right? It might, hell, it might be
in a database that you're
waiting to pull across the
network, for God's sake.
But what we're saying is,
eventually it's in RAM
on the computer. Does that
make sense? You moved it up out of the
file and you grabbed it
from the network or whatever.
So it comes down here, grabs that x and
let's say x, this x value is 7. So
it's going to come over here and put that
7 here and it's going to put that 7
here. And now the
next time that you access
x, if it hasn't
been ejected from these caches,
it will come down here and look for x,
like say this variable
sum, you know, plus equals.
Well, you're going to
need that every, every,
every time, right? It's going to be a hit
here as soon as it goes here. So that
first time it took some delta t amount of
time to grow here, then delta t amount of
time that didn't find it here and this is
some delta t amount of time of year. So
in other words, a long time to grab it.
But after it gets
copied back over here, now
it's only this amount
of time right here that
it took just delta
t. Now I'm pretending like
these delta t's are all
the same that they're not.
But like this total
amount of time would be
3 delta t amount of time. This is only
delta t amount of
time and obviously delta t
is a lot less than 3 delta t, right?
But now the truth of the matter is it's
orders of magnitude. It's like
this might be, this might
be 10 units of time,
this might be 100 units
of time and this might
be 5,000 units of time.
Ram is much slower
than the other things, orders
of magnitude, okay? So you
want to have as many
cache hits as you can, right? You want to,
you hope your cache hits
are more of a cost.
If you have a cache hit, it only takes
delta t amount of time. If you have a
cache misses, it might all have to go all
the way down in here, might be 3 delta t.
I'm just making up t values here, whatever
that time is, right?
That's what these things are.
So it's in main memory, you try to
fetch it, you know,
it goes back over here.
But the truth is
like in most computers, like
we have in our laptops
here, our servers, like this
thing's here, you actually can't
control the caches. You can't
control how they get updated.
That's the hardware doing that.
Now, there are some like
cutting edge types of devices
that you can buy that
you can set those things.
But for 99% of the rest of us,
you don't want to
be screwing with that. You
just say, I want the computer to work.
I'm assuming you're doing
it in a good way.
It is always going to be doing one
particular type of operation
and that doesn't benefit
from this policy. Then you might want to
have a specialized device
that you can control.
But remember, these
computers, they're what they
call general purpose
computers. They're supposed to
run anything, right? That means they don't
necessarily do great at
running any one thing.
Because, you know, if you've
only got one thing you got
to do, you can build
a circuit and it does it
thousands of times faster than
the computer does it. But that
circuit can only do that one
thing. It can't do arbitrary things.
All right. Now, we got all these caches
here, right? So we
got some sort of variable
x over here. What
about if this array executes
x? So it grabs x, it comes in here.
I'm just going to imagine,
like, what about if x is
in here and x is in
here? And then now this thread
tries to access x. Now,
imagine it was 7, 7, 7,
7, and this goes to access
x and it's like, okay, cool.
I didn't find it here.
But, oh, I did find it there. It's a 7.
So I'm going to go put, you know, my x
is 7 and x is 7 in here. And let's
say it changes into 8.
Wait a minute now. You've
got a problem here because
you've got x in multiple
locations strung out all throughout
the memory hierarchy and they
don't all have the same
value now. You see that?
Like, if you go and
say that this is 8, well,
wait a minute. If this guy
is accessing x, he still thinks
it's 7. This guy thinks
it's 8. They don't even have
a clear picture of it. I
mean, this happens in databases, right?
Like, if one user tries
to modify a value in
a database and it's time
that another user tries to
modify a database, what does
the database typically do, not
always, but typically try to
do to keep that from happening?
Databases have these properties called
the ACID properties, right? What is
it? Atomicity, concurrency, durability. I
don't remember all the various properties.
That was the other course
I didn't want to teach when
I came here. Only wanted to
teach you one time, thank goodness.
My point of it is,
you typically lock a value,
right? It's transactional based. So
if a person gets their transaction
in a database first, this
other person is an atomic
operation, atomicity. If everything goes
and says x is equal to
10 and you're shoving 10
into a database where x
is at, if somebody else
tries to modify x, it's going
to stop and it's going
to finish this thing right
here and then it's going
to do the other one, right?
Now, who issued their
database changed first? Is
it guaranteed that whoever
issued it first is
going to change it first and the other
guy's going to overwrite it on top of it?
You know, there's a lot of issues here
that have to do
with concurrent access to stuff.
Concurrent access to shared
data. That's the same problem
here because this is
memory. This is share, right?
So if you go ahead, if everybody
reads this x, no big deal. Reading stuff
doesn't change anything, right?
But modifying a value,
that changes it. So you have to make
sure that you take some kind of policy
that makes sure that
when things change, everybody
becomes aware of that
change and they're not
operating on an old version of the data.
And that's what's this idea of
like this cache coherency issue. So
coherency and ultimately referred to as
also there's a
related subject called consistency.
So coherency, consistency,
you know, you've
got this variable here and other people
are, you know, got different values
to it. How can we fix it?
So there's a thing called
a directory based
cache coherency protocol,
so the directory and Snoopy cache
coherency protocol. Snoopy
means, hey, there's
a little hardware device over here
that's constantly looking at the stuff
going across this bus and looking
at what variables are being changed.
And it's looking and it
sees that if somebody changes
it, because it's constantly looking,
it's like, oh, hold on, that
thing just changed. So this
is not valid anymore. Let
me let me go update
this thing. So it's constantly looking.
There's directory based where there's an
actual directory that is maintained to do
that same thing. Alright, this is
more important. Like, for example, if this
interconnection network is
taking place across
like a really slow network across a,
you know, multiple computers, which is
why normally we don't worry about this.
We don't try to have there to be what's
called distributed shared memory with
the types of stuff we're
doing. Are there things
like that where literally variables
are shared? There's an X
on that computer in RAM
over there. That's the same X's in my RAM.
Can you do that? Yes, you can do that sort
of thing. But then there has to be this
same thing that globally keeps
track of this consistency stuff.
The same kind of stuff that
distributed database service
have to do the
same thing. It's got multiple clients that
could be reading and writing the same
data at the same time. These same
sorts of problems you have in say
225 and 425 here, these are the
same problems you
have inside the computer.
It's just that instead of it being like,
say, something that's being
controlled via software, this
stuff being controlled via
hardware, right? And it's
being done for us.
We're not controlling it, right?
So you got those same kind of problems
with concurrent access to
stuff. Now there's different types
of parallelism. This class
is called introduction to parallel
programming. What kind of
parallelism are we talking about?
Well, you can have parallelism
at the instruction level. This
is often called ILP, instruction
level parallelism, right? That can
happen by saying, hey, I
want to execute my instruction
on a pipeline, which is
one type of instruction level parallelism.
Or I want to issue literally more than one
instruction at exactly the
same time. Now these are
both happening at the
same time, but they're not
quite the same thing, right?
Talk about this one later.
I want you to think about the
height lining. And I think they're using
the close example in here, which makes
sense because this is
the example that's used
in chapter 5 of our textbook, which
we don't ever get to in say 210.
But if you put it in 310,
it starts with chapter 4 and then 5.
Imagine you're at home, you're going to
wash your clothes. So you take your
dirty clothes, you put it in the
washing machine. After that's
done, then you put
it in the dryer. After that's done,
you take them out and you fold them.
And then after that, say you put
them back in the closet or the drawers.
Look, you know, I'm
trying to imagine, like, maybe
this took 30 minutes,
30 minutes, 30 minutes, you
know, and you can figure out how long it
would take to do
one load of clothes, right?
But now, if you and
your siblings, say, are at
the house, you could put
your load in here first, wash
it. As soon as your
load gets to the dryer, the
sibling can start using this,
resourcing at exactly the same time.
Now, that means that there are two
different clothes washings going
on at the same
time. They're in different
stages of execution. One
is drying while the other one is washing.
And as long as you got, say, two
pieces of equipment that
are separated like this, you
can do it. And if you've got multiple
human beings down here,
then you know what I'm
saying? You could be,
like, folding one load
of clothes while another
one's drying while another one's
being washed. That's three
things going on at the
same time. So instead
of it going like this,
you're going to, you know, wash,
dry, fold. Then your sibling is
going to do wash, dry, fold.
What could you do? You could start
here and say, I'm going to
wash, dry, fold. But as soon as
I start drying, the other person
can come in here and start washing.
So now instead of it being that
it takes this long to complete two
things, it only takes this long to
complete two things. The amount of time is
now shorter. And this is not a
new concept. I mean,
ever since the conveyor
belts were made on the first assembly
line, that's what an
assembly line is, right?
You got to roll parts
rolling now, and you add
your part to it, it goes on to the next
station. You add your parts
to it at the same
time everybody else is adding
their parts to their things.
Pipeline around, ever since the Industrial
Revolution started from a mechanized way.
Does that make sense? You're just
asking your computer to do that.
Same sort of thing. Divide the
execution of an instruction into pieces
and then start working on an
instruction before the
previous one is finished.
Start working on the next load of
laundry before the previous
load has even finished.
And that's fine because normally you and
your siblings clothing
are completely independent of
each other. They don't depend on the
same thing, right? Not in a computer,
not in my. Like if I said
something like, x is equal to y
plus z, and then I came down
here and said that w plus equals x.
Wait a minute. The answer of
this instruction feeds into the next one.
These are not independent of each
other. That might be a problem because
I might not be able to
get an answer before the next instruction
starts, but if these two things
are independent, this
analogy here works perfectly.
Okay, basically, how does
that actually happen? That's another
thing. Let's take a
look at their example here.
Yeah, so that, oh, the
example on these notes, I
see Professor Hickman has these
things taking different amounts of time.
Washer takes 30 minutes. The driver
takes 40 minutes.
That's pretty realistic, right?
I find that the driver takes
longer than the washer. That's not great,
though, is it? They're not the
same because that means that the washing
machine is sitting idle for 10 minutes
before the net, the dryer load finishes.
So you are always,
your pipeline is always limited
to the weakest link, and in this case, the
dryer is the weakest
link. See that? And the
folding, I mean, you can
get that done pretty fast.
But then whoever's folding closed,
they're waiting there 20 minutes
because when this load comes
out of the dryer and they
come over here and works,
this is happening for 20
minutes while the next dryer
is working on the next load.
But then for the last
half of this 20 minutes, this
person's not doing anything. They're
sitting there idle. That's not great.
But that is, in fact, the way it is in the
computer or something set up. So
you have to think about it.
This parallelism via pipelining
has a lot of benefits,
but it also has a
lot of limitations, like not
every stage takes the
same amount of time. If
there's data
dependencies between instructions,
then that's a problem, too.
So they kind of show this
here, washing, drying,
folding, washing, drying, folding.
And this would be if you
had to finish this whole process before
the next one could start, before
the next one could start, before the
next one could start, it would take
this amount of time to do it.
But if you allow it to be
done in a pipeline fashion, then that
gets reduced by a heck of a
lot here, right? Because the fact that
this is happening at the same time
as that, that and that's happening at
the same time, you know, that, that
and that's happening at the same time.
So you get like a lot of
stuff happening at the same time. But now,
when you first start,
all the equipment's unused,
right, except for the
washing machine is used.
So those other two
things are sitting idle. The
next thing, the washing
machine and the dryer are
used, but the folder
person is still sitting there
not doing anything. Now,
initially, the, you know, this
might not be necessarily
a great diagram of the
way it's drawn out,
but you could imagine at
some point here, because
there's three stages, all three
stages would be in use at the same time.
But now, at the very
end, as it starts filtering
out at the end, you
also have this thing where
not everything is being used
at the same time, right?
Anytime something's sitting idle, that's
a, that's a source of inefficiency.
So when you have a
pipeline, at the very beginning,
when the pipeline, when you
first start a pipeline, that's called
the warm up phase. And
at the end, when the stuff
dribbles out at the end,
that's called the cool down phase.
But in the middle,
when the pipeline is full,
that's when it's rocking
it at full speed, right?
And generally, the warm up period is
very short compared to
the entire time, right?
Like, let's just say
that's a couple of nanoseconds,
but your program's running
for minutes. That's not a
big deal, right? It's
that little bit at the
beginning, and it's a
little bit at the end.
That warm up and cool down
doesn't affect it much. But with
a little example like this, does
it affect it? Yes, a lot, because
it represents a big fraction of
the overall amount of time, because
this thing only shows what is
this, four loads of laundry being done?
But if there were 100,000 loads of
laundry being done, at the very beginning,
at the very end, nobody would care
about that. That's just
noise at that point.
Your pipeline is
predominantly to determine how
well it's working after it's warmed up and
before it cools down, which is normally
not quite an understand
of its execution time.
But what can it be limited by? Data
dependencies among instructions, and
there's an imbalance in
the amount of time it takes for each
phase. Like here, the
dryer is the weakest link.
So your total proof of instructions,
like how many instructions per second you
can get done, is going to depend
on the one that takes the longest.
And they just go and show
this. Like, for example, there is a
part in the computer that adds floating
point numbers down. It's inside the ALU.
And when you're trying
to add two floating points
together, they're saying that
a pipelining example that involves
floating point numbers inside
that thing, you've got to
first fetch the things from
memory that are being added.
And then, with the way floating point
numbers are actually done in the computer,
which you probably haven't done before, it
actually has to do stuff where it looks
at the exponents first, and then it
has to do some shifting, and then
it adds, and then it normalizes, and
then it rounds, and
then it stores results.
So that pipeline might have like
seven stages here. So there's several,
seven little chunks of things that
could be happening at the same time.
So this previous pipeline,
it had three stages, wash,
dry, and fold. Here, this
thing got seven stages. So
inside, like a typical
Intel x86 computer, there might
be some pipelines that are
20 or 30 stages long.
Now, you might say,
well, why don't you just
make lower stages be gigantic?
Because that sounds better, right?
Yes, but the problem with dependencies
get worse and worse, the longer
and deeper the pipeline is. So
there's some sweet spot for pipeline link.
All right. They go and talk
more about pipelining here. I'd rather
move on to the next type
of parallelism that
they're talking about here.
But they do the same thing.
They show it in a loop, right?
They're like, hey, I'm going to
add a thousand
floating point numbers together.
So I'm going to add a thousand, so
maybe a thousand of
these things to dispatch. But
in one moment, there's
all of these things, all
of these stages are
happening at the same time.
You know what I'm saying? So like,
you know, across here,
this is happening. One's
in one stage, one's in another, one's in
another. So that's kind
of what's happening here.
Now, the other type of parallelism
that was called
instruction level parallelism. One
was, it was instruction level because we
were dispatching instructions
offset by one slot.
Here we're saying, no, actually,
I'm going to actually dispatch
two different ads at exactly
the same time. So like, before
it'd be like, let me do an ad, and then
let me do an ad
like this in stages. That's pipeline.
Here, multiple issue means I am literally
going to do an ad, and I'm
going to start the other ad at
exactly the same time as the first ad.
You might say, well, when
does that, how could you do
that? That would be like
saying, I'm going to wash two
loads of laundry at the
same time. The only way you
can do that is if
you have two washing machines, right?
Now, that pipeline, you only have
to have one copy of every
resource. You only got to have
one washer, one dryer, one folder, right?
But if you wanted to do
three loads of laundry at the
same time, you'd have to have
three washers, three
dryers, three folders, right?
That's what they're saying
here. You want to do
two ads at the exact
same time, like from say
210, you remember like, you
know, ad R1, R2, R3,
and you also want to do ad R5, R6, R7.
Then there has to be
two adders inside the ALU
that can do those two
ads at the same time.
So you can imagine that the
more you want to issue it at
the same time, the more copies you
have to have of every functional unit.
What about if I want
to do two multiplies at
the same time? Then I
got to have two multipliers.
But if I want to do
a combination of two ads and
two multipliers at the same time,
I got to have copies of both.
I can't even have copies of
however many things. At some point
you're like, you know, you got
too much stuff going on there.
So there's also, same thing, the
depth of the pipeline is going
to be limited. The width of
the multiple issues is called width.
How wide? This is like
say, you know, two at a
time. But what about you
can issue four at a time?
So two at a time, four
at a time. Well, now in
this, in this thing right here,
look at this, look at this code.
Listen, what is the
maximum number of things
you could actually do at the same time?
Let's look at this. You
got an array of memory X.
It has to be added
to another array of memory Y.
So we got X, we got Y, and that's
B. And it's just
doing an element-wise addition, right?
And this is C. So like that plus that
is going here. That
plus that is going there.
But none of those
additions have anything to
do with any of the other ones, right?
Like you could do every iteration
of this for loop at exactly
the same time you don't even
need a for loop, do you?
I could write a program that has I
hard-coded into every one
of these things here.
And it's like I could add this
at the same time that that's being added.
So for example, if I had two
adders and I had two sets of
registers, I could
literally do this instruction
and this instruction at the same time.
And if I could do two
at a time every time I
do it in the loop, instead
of this loop executing a thousand times,
this loop would only
have to execute 500 times
because it was doing
two instructions every time, right?
But to do that, I got
to have adder number one and
adder number two inside the ALU
to be able to do that.
And if I want to
do that with every combination of
instructions, I got to have replications
of all of that computer hardware.
Does that kind of
make sense? What's happening here?
You could do this, but
it's going to cost you that.
You could do this, but it's
going to cost you that, right?
Like, that's kind of the
way this is going here.
So those are these two things here.
Now, the difference between,
say, fine-grained,
coarse-grained, and simultaneous
multi-threading, I don't want us
to worry a whole lot.
I don't want us to get all raised
up talking about what
the difference of this is.
In fact, I don't think I want us
to talk about that at all right now.
But why don't we do some threading
first, and then we can go back and
look at it and be like, what kind
of threading was this that we just did?
And you've got to feel for it, because you
actually start things from writing
a program with it, right?
So we'll worry about that later.
Parallel hardware. Okay, this is
an important taxonomy, Flynn's taxonomy.
And this is not
a perfect taxonomy, because
there are things that
don't fit into this taxonomy.
But in general, you've
got these four things.
So it's single instruction, single data.
So you can do one instruction on one
piece of data, and that's how you do it.
Or you could have single instructions
happen on multiple pieces of data.
Like, for example, in that previous
example that we just gave, we had
an array, and we wanted to
have the array to be added together.
It was the smallest array you
could add really, like, that makes sense.
So imagine that what was in this
array was 1, 2, 3, 4, like this.
We're going to add it.
Well, now, what we're doing is add, right?
The stream of
instructions is, there's only
one thing I want to do in add.
But it's happening to this piece of data
at the same time as this piece of data.
So there's multiple streams
of data, but there's only
one instruction I may
be doing to it, right?
This thing over here,
multiple instructions, single data, we're
not going to worry
about that in this course.
And then finally, this one,
multiple instructions and multiple data.
Well, now, that's basically like the way
everything is on
our computer already, right?
Like, if you run Microsoft
Word on your computer, the
same thing as PowerPoint, Microsoft
Word has got, you know,
lots of different instructions that are
happening on different pieces of data.
At the same time
that PowerPoint is working on
lots of different instructions
on different pieces of data,
literally, they're in
two different processes.
They don't have anything
to do with each other,
except for, you know,
even better than each other.
But other than that, you know, that is
kind of like what
we've been doing all along,
except for Word and
PowerPoint aren't trying to
solve the same problem at the same time.
But what we're going to be trying
to do is use multiple instruction streams
and multiple data streams at the same
time to solve a single problem faster.
That's what parallelism we're
talking about here is.
Solve one problem in
a shorter period of time.
The scientist needs to do matrix
multiplication, and it took ten seconds.
Wouldn't it be better
if it took one second?
So that's kind of
what we're talking about here.
So, SYSD, SIMD, and MMD, those are the
two, those are the
three things that we did.
We're going to be talking
about inside of Flynn's Taxonomy.
And if you go back and look at the
history of the instructions
that are in your computers,
like in your AMD
or your silicon type processors
or your x86 or your
ARM or whatever you got,
there'll be some
specialized instructions in there
that will do
what's called vector instructions,
where it'll do the
same math operation, but
instead of on two
individual numbers at a time,
it'll do it on eight individual numbers at
one time, or sixteen
numbers at the same time.
That's what this is.
And that started back in like
mid to late nineties, I guess.
They started doing that.
That's a weird name storm back then
that actually had the word SIMD in it,
and of course it's the community
that might back us regular consumers,
and what the hell does that even mean?
They don't need to worry about it.
You probably don't even
think about it, right?
When you buy something
today, you don't worry
about what kind of
vector extensions the thing has,
unless you're running an application that
you wrote that needs those things,
that you better buy a
product that provides it, right?
Like that's nine times out
of ten, you're just like, whatever.
I can still compile a program.
I can still run it on it.
It just might be slower.
That's the only issue.
Now, that first chapter I
said we're going to do MPI,
that's going to be
this type of parallelism.
Okay, let's see, let's
not worry about this.
Okay, any time data is transmitted,
we're interested in how long it takes
to get the data to reach its destination.
We talked about that last time, right?
Like if we said the amount of time
it takes to transfer
some data across the network
is equal to the size
of the data that you have,
divided by the bandwidth,
plus the latency, right?
That's something like this.
Latency is the time it takes
for when the first byte is sent
to when the first byte is received.
That's the lambda, right?
But then after the first byte is received,
the rest of the bytes have to be received.
That's the additional time that it
takes is S divided by V.
You think about it.
Like, for example, if I throw
this phone at your face, say,
in that hypothetical world,
and we say how much of this phone,
let's say this is the
first inch of the phone,
second, third, fourth, or whatever, here,
that's the bandwidth.
How many inches per second is it applying?
But it still takes, say, two
seconds to get to your face.
And then after that, another,
however many, to go by it.
So the bandwidth has to do with how
long it takes to
transfer that entire payload,
but the latency takes is how
long it takes for that packet
to initially get from here to there.
But then after that
first package is received,
then the rest of the
file has to be received,
or the rest of the
message has to be received.
And that's where the bandwidth comes in.
That's why you want, if you've
got size divided
by bandwidth plus latency,
you want this number to be small
because you want the time to be small.
In order to make this
small, this needs to be small
and this needs to be small.
But for that to be
small, this needs to be big.
So if this goes to
infinity, this term goes to zero.
If this goes to zero, then
both of these things are zero.
The problem is, having your
case and meeting it, too,
something that's got a really
great latency at the same time
is a really great bandwidth.
Typically there are
diametrically opposed objectives,
and that's why these
networks that we're talking about,
like Infiniband and all
these like spirit specialized things
that Create Computer makes,
some of these areas network,
and all this kind of stuff,
it is like hundreds of thousands
of dollars, say, for like a switch.
It's not a set of thousands of dollars,
it's hundreds of thousands
of stuff because it's specialized.
There's only however many
super-dudes in the world, right?
We don't need that.
Coastal doesn't need that in
their data center downstairs, right?
It's got a typical,
you know, 10 gig ethernet,
or 40 gig ethernet might work, right?
You don't need all this other stuff.
So we've got five minutes left.
I want us to talk about what you
need to get done
between now and next time.
You need to get your access CI done.
Get that thing to you.
If you don't have the book,
somehow or another, like Pacheco Text,
you get it because that's
where any slides are coming from,
Pacheco Text.
Then we're going to be in a
position to start playing
around with some stuff.
Now here's the thing.
How many people in here
have a Windows computer, okay?
How many people have a Mac computer, okay?
How many people have
a Linux machine right here?
All right.
So if you're a Mac person, you
know, just right up front, you know,
you can open up a
terminal and start doing so.
If you're on Linux, of
course, you can do that.
And in Windows, you know, you've
got Windows subsystem for Linux too
and some other types of things.
So all this stuff that
we're getting ready to talk about,
at least preliminarily, to play
with some little tiny parallel programs,
we won't need to be running
on the CI project or Expanse
just to play with some tiny, right?
So it would be really good that,
you know, if you're a Mac person,
you know, start thinking about like
the fact that you're going to be
executing stuff probably in the
command line of the computer.
How do you install things from
the command line on your Mac, okay?
On your Mac, for example,
you want to install something
that's not already on your
computer at the command line.
There's some library you need.
There's some compiler you need.
There's some whatever you need.
You know, you need OpenMP.
You need MPI.
You need this or that.
How do you do it?
What's the package manager that
most people use on the Mac
to install things in the command line?
It's called BRU, okay?
What about in Linux?
What is it?
Well, it depends on what
flavor of Linux you've got.
You've got the package managers, right?
Those are the kind of things.
And what about in Windows?
Well, you could use those same
package managers inside a flavor of Linux
that came with your WSL.
So those, a lot of
people are in here in Windows.
How many of you in Windows
have run stuff in the command line
like I'm talking about
where it's in the WSL?
How many of you have not?
Okay, so if you've never
done that kind of stuff before,
you need to start reading.
Like, how do I run
this stuff on my computer?
Start Googling around about that.
This class is not about that.
Like, you've got the computer you've got.
They're all capable of running these
parallel programs from the command line.
Figure out how to get the command
line up so that we can run GCC
and we can run these various things.
And we're going to
have to install special stuff.
We're going to have to install NPI.
We're going to have
to install whatever, if
we want to do it on our computers.
And I say, if we want to.
There's nowhere in here that
you're going to be required
to run it on your computer,
because the stuff you turn in
has to work on expense, okay?
But do you constantly want to
be working on some remote thing
where every time you change something and
all this is on some remote thing?
Probably not.
Probably want to play with
it on your own computer.
And for the first several
things we do in here,
you'll run it on your computer
is all you need to do.
So I'm just encouraging you to figure out
how to get it to the command line
and do some basic stuff and
compile the C program using GCC.
I would say that.
If you can get a hello world, world.c,
at the command line on
your computer, GCC, and run,
then you're probably at a point where
we can start playing this stuff, okay?
So that's pretty much it.
So I hope everybody has a great day.
We're going to have a, we're going to do
one more thing when we come back in here
on Tuesday, and then we're going
to start with our first NPI program
and talking about NPI, okay?
Have a good day.
Yes, sir, you do the same.
Thank you.
Yeah.
I still didn't see, like,
all that time you started playing.
Yeah.
It's going to be okay.
I promise you.
It's going to be all right.
Like, there are some students that haven't
even been entered at all in the system,
and it's my understanding that the person,
so imagine, like, when I put
in a request for the department,
the department puts a thing in,
the human resources puts a thing in,
and then as the
supervisor, I approve that thing,
and then it goes to a sequence of people.
Like, for example, in this case,
it's charging, say, like, an account.
That account is being
controlled by the research people,
so it goes to the research.
That person is sick, say, yesterday.
They don't get back until today,
so it literally doesn't go anywhere,
and then that person approves it,
then it goes to the college,
and then it goes to the provost
and the dean and all this stuff,
and it's like, everybody has
to sign off on it,
so it takes days if all those
people aren't sitting
right on their computer,
but don't worry, like, this
is going to totally be okay.
Like, either electronically
or after the fact,
you just have a piece of
paper, put your things on it,
and they go process it retroactively.
You know, like, say five weeks from now,
something blew up in the computer system,
it doesn't really happen in
a minute, but that's fine.
Last five weeks, you just do
it on a sheet of paper,
then payroll goes to put
it in there and fixes it.
It's just, hopefully we don't get to that.
It's just that for some reason, a lot
of the people that
are involved in this thing
have been sick at each stage,
or either on travel or whatever,
and there's only one person in each
of these places that
approve it or whatever,
so it's...
Okay, I should just keep track of my time.
Just keep track of it, and,
like, that's all you've got to do.
If it went, when the
thing comes to go one by,
if it goes back to the early of the 18th,
cool, we'll do it there.
If it doesn't, then we just go
do it on what's called paper form
and put it in there,
and, like, literally, it's like,
this date, this date, this
date, five hours, three hours,
two hours, one hour,
and just go like that,
and do it in the name form.
You know, unfortunately, you know, like,
that might mean a particular paycheck.
I have two papers, and instead of one,
it's just a little while to do it.
That's basically how it works.
Yeah, man, you do the same, dude.
What class is this?
I'm trying to search the site.
Okay, is that the 303?
Yeah.
Oh, okay.
Who's teaching that?
Okay, cool.