If you fix up the little things we mentioned, it'd be good to go.
Clean up that.
Yeah, man.
But like, do I?
OK, never mind.
I think we talked about it.
Yeah.
All right.
Yeah, no problem.
You can get up with it, all right?
Yeah, and feel free to grab one of these if you want it.
What questions?
You said, all right, cool.
Awesome.
This is in position for a undergraduate job
with a fact sheet, who just left it
over far from the things that you want those to figure out.
Cool.
That's good.
All right.
So we had NPIs year zero one that was there.
Anybody feel good about this time, going to do a good job?
Any of the people that did a good job feel comfortable showing
your back and go look at your report on the screen?
Anybody volunteer?
Everybody show hands.
I don't know.
There's no pressure.
Mike, so let me get out of this screen.
Now, let me pull this stuff up first here to make sure that we've got issues here.
OK, cool, all right, here we go.
All right, so let's take a look at what Mike submitted.
All right, so we've got the code, the data, the presentation, and the report.
Let's take a look at the report.
So we've got the whole project.
Cool.
That's cleaned up, too.
That's cool.
And then if I could recompile it, I could load it into that overlay
if I wanted to to see what it looked like.
But, you know, if I'm primarily going to hit this first,
so let's see, let me just look kind of at what this looks like.
So you've got your home computer that expands.
You've got some to-do code.
You've got command line parameters of all what they do.
Monospace font here, which looks nice because it's typically
the way you have the code's monospace fonts.
This is showing the Python program.
Let's see, and then what from, you know, because we integrate from 10 to 20,
these problem sizes, you have eight cores on your chain?
OK, so go from one to eight cores and increment by one.
So you modified the sweep thing a little bit.
Cool.
Oh, and this is on Expanse.
OK, is that all right?
So go from one to 128.
Now, what does this do here?
That was supposed to be so, like, starting at 32,
processes that had to increment by 16, not the one that you get.
Oh, OK, so from one to 32, do one processor at a time.
But then from 32 to the end, do 16 at a time?
Is that more or less?
Yeah, and then before that, well, I added the powers of two.
OK, and let's make sure everybody's good on that.
So Mike's saying, like, he didn't do, like, you know, one, two, three, no, 128.
He didn't even do, like, two, four, six, eight, all of 128.
He did it from one to 32, the powers of two, inclusive of 32?
Yeah.
OK, so I'll say so, like, one, two, four, eight, 16, 32.
And then after that, you went from 32 to 128 by 16 each time.
But why did you do that?
It was a little, a little complex to, like, kind of explain why, but kind of just,
there wasn't enough data between, like, 64 and 128.
So just so we had more data, it was, like, a reasonable amount of, you know.
So let me, I want to just explore that for a second.
If I understand what you're saying is, you know, hey, like, I know I'm going to be plotting this stuff now.
Just a second ago, this marker was working fine, I guess, in the 10 seconds at the top
wasn't on it, and just to move out here.
Let's see, how about this one?
Oh, nice.
All right, so I don't know, for example, for either timing or whatever it is,
we're going to have, like, an x-axis that repeats.
Now, if you did from one to 128, one at a time, what would happen?
If the prop sizes they gave you, it would take more than 30 minutes to run it.
You know, when we said, okay, cool, we need to run fewer things.
And we still need to sweep this range.
So one thing would be to do is, like, powers two, like, so, like, one, two, four, eight.
And, like, the further you get, like, you've got these really big jumps where you go from, like, 64 to 128.
What's happening between 64 and 128?
Maybe there's an interesting phenomenon there.
You know, like, let's suppose that you did your speed up, and your speed up was, like,
and then from going from 64 to 128, it was like this.
Like, does this still keep going up here, and they go down?
Does it go down immediately?
Like, you don't know what's happening between here and here, and I think what I hear Mike saying is,
he said, all right, this is pretty dense in here.
But then when we get to, like, 16, so 16 would be twice eight, so, and then when I'm 32,
I'm going to go do it more frequently in here so I get more data points.
Is that what I'm hearing?
Okay.
So that way is not a bunch of gaps.
Now, a lot of times you'll see people do the following whenever they run these performance things on the computer.
They'll have the problem size go up by two every time, and they'll have the number of processes go up by two every time.
So doubling the problem size and doubling the number of processes.
Now, one reason that it happens is a lot of parallel programs only work if this stuff's powered to two,
because they've been written in a way where it won't work if it's not evenly divisible by the power of two or it isn't powered to.
But the other reason is that, like, you need to be able to deal with small sizes and extreme sizes,
and this means you don't have to test every combination between what Mike apparently said.
I didn't like the fact that as I got closer to the end, I didn't have very many data points because there was nothing between 64 and 128 if I did that.
So he chose to have a parameter that said how much you would jump by, okay, of the plots.
It's hard sometimes to be able to take, put the plots where you want them.
Like, I was just getting here and looking, I was like, we're at the conclusion, but I haven't seen any results.
Anyway, okay, now, actually, I don't want to have this speak to the screen like this because it can't, okay, cool.
Come on, now, I'm getting a ctrl plus, aren't I? Oh, I'm not hitting another button.
No, let's see. Okay, so the left-hand column is your computer. The right-hand column is expanse.
Okay. So the problem sizes were the same.
So from 100 million to 1.9 billion, 100 million to 1.9 billion, it was like the same data, same sizes.
Now, here's, I'm going to provide some feedback, if that's okay.
You see how the y-axis here, is the scale of this y-axis the same as the scale of this y-axis?
In terms of second-short vote.
In terms of total range, right. Now, this is just me saying, like, hey, this is looking pretty good.
Like, here's, here's the feedback I would give to somebody.
Let's suppose that I was like, let's look at how much rainfall happens in South Carolina versus California over the top.
We had, like, South Carolina inches per day. We had California inches per day.
And this thing was like this.
And over here, it was like, I mean, it's a lot more variable in South Carolina.
And it's like, no, like, let's suppose this was 100 inches, 200 inches, and this was 3 inches, and this was 2 inches.
Well, it's only buried by, like, 1 inch here. If I hear it's hundreds of, and it's 50s of inches.
The scale, now, this is ridiculous, I mean, but, like, the thing is, one thing I wonder is, like,
you know, is his computer faster than his fans? I don't know.
Like, you can't tell me, remember, just the scale, at least here, that is almost the same.
So, like, if that was 2, then 6 is probably somewhere here, but 6 over there is there.
Especially when you go side by side visually, you would want to figure out what is the maximum value
that y value could be between the two related graphs and set it from 0 to that max value.
So that when you compare this with your eyes and this with your eyes, it's apples to apples.
That's all I'm going to say.
Now, obviously, the x-axis here, that might not be the same, because you didn't test the same parameters in.
You would needlessly, like, and you could, you could have this go up to 128,
but then you'd only have data, like, right in here, and it would probably look similar to the way this is.
But, yeah, especially with the y values, it comes up a lot.
Because it forces the user, like, they're like, my salary versus your salary.
It's like, well, hold on, are the scales even the same? You can't compare them directly if the scales aren't the same.
Okay, cool. So that's trending downward.
And I'm guessing, I was just looking here, when we got to 128, the screen line,
like, some weird things are, you know, like, it's all I'm thinking is, hey,
you know, it looks like the green line actually took more time than this,
which I guess that extent is bigger, but it also seems like it, like, it went up here.
I mean, I can't tell, but, like, that would, that would not be a good thing, right?
I don't mean to promote that it's not a good thing for your homework assignment, but, I mean, it's not good as general.
Like, if you use more processes and it actually gets slower, like, that would not be considered a good thing,
in general, right? Like, you would probably say, then I'm not going to do that.
I'm not going to run twice in any process because I'm going to burn up.
It's twice as much energy, twice as much core hour, but you don't mind getting anything bored.
In fact, it's worse, right? Like, I don't know, we can't tell that yet.
You know, go down here and look a little further. So speed up.
Okay, well, now, one thing you have here that I didn't say you had to have,
but it's cool that you put it here, because I don't think I'd say it.
Why don't you have the ideal line in here?
Because that represents normally what would be considered the maximum speed up one we'd expect to get,
because you can't give a speed up more than the number of processes.
Like, I, you know, two students could do it in an hour, but four students could do it in ten seconds.
It's like, well, that doesn't make sense. Could that happen?
Not generally in real life with people, generally more people get involved.
It gets worse to coordinate something.
But it happened in the computer for some reason.
So we probably see, like right over here, that there are some of these things that seem to be bigger than ideal.
We're going to talk about that later.
But data is what the data is. I'm going to plot it out, and that's what it is.
It looks like on this computer, let's see.
Now, the one that appears to have, like, for example, an A-course,
the one that appears to have achieved the maximum speed up
is actually the one that's smaller.
Here, right, Mike? Is that the way you read this?
And the ones that had the worst speed up at A-cores was actually the one that was around in here.
And then this one was somewhere in the middle, like it was somewhere in here.
But either way, like, if we're using A-cores, we're getting at least even all the problem sizes,
and we're getting more than six times speed up.
So, I mean, that's, that's kind of cool, you know.
Like, this is faster. I mean, we're talking about that when we did this thing in parallel,
you know, we went on the order of, for one core, if you hadn't written this like the way you would have a regular program
that you've always written, it would have taken six seconds or whatever.
And writing it this way, you can make it take less than a second.
So that's what this class is about, okay?
Now, this was trivial because it's easy to parallelize, and not all are,
but that's how we're starting with it. You get the flow, the workflow.
Then let's see, look at it in expanse.
Now, this is more like what I was kind of expecting, is this thing, look at this.
The one that had the worst speed up is the one that has the smallest problem size.
Because generally, at least I think it is.
I can't tell which, if there's a difference between this black hole and that black hole.
But either way, these are the smallest.
And the smallest sizes seem to have had the worst speed up.
Now, why is that?
Well, there's a lot of reasons for it.
One is the overhead of just doing this stuff is kind of a fixed cost.
And if you don't have that much work to do, that fixed cost represents a big fraction of the overall cost.
But if you're doing a really big problem, that fixed cost,
some of that stuff really doesn't matter that much.
That sandals all right there.
So typically, the bigger the problem, the better speed up that you can get.
And that also makes sense.
Like, if you can already do a problem really fast, why would you parallelize it?
I mean, like, according to this thing, if we were just going to do 100 million,
I mean, 100 million was going to be right there anyway.
How much faster can you get it?
You only have this amount to improve.
But when your problem takes this amount, you've got this big range of stuff you can possibly improve.
So it makes sense that typically the ones that are the smaller problem sizes
will see the least gains as p gets larger.
And then which one saw the best?
Looks like the biggest problem size was always increasing.
In fact, it looks like it even increased there a little bit.
The next, some of the next ones, I don't know which one this one is.
But now, some of them definitely were worse.
So like, if you were going to run a problem that was 100 million,
you might say, well, I'll stop right here.
I'll stop right there because any further is worse, right?
But you'll see that also is not a good idea, okay?
Because like, what about if all these were the same?
Say, oh, those three points were the same.
Would you want to go here or would you want to stop here?
Would you stop here?
Because this is only using that many cores.
And you're being charged when you use cloud services
based on the core hours and stuff.
So like, why would you use more resources and not get any better speed up?
You wouldn't.
In fact, you probably wouldn't even change it.
And you definitely go to here.
You'd go to there because you're getting on the side and you'll speed up.
But now, right here, that's the turning point.
That's like the median curve.
Oh, whoa, like when you add it from here to here,
you didn't keep up because this gap started widening, right?
So if we go and look at the efficiency,
we can see that like, we're maintaining something pretty close up here
near 100% efficiency.
But when we get to right here, it's like, oh my God, a huge drop.
And every time you keep doing it, it keeps getting less and less efficient, right?
And it's nice to get less efficient all the way from the very beginning.
Except for some weird just to happen right here,
which is also that thing about being faster than the fastest or whatever.
But like, you know, you might be willing to do this
because every time we move to this point right here,
like, let's say that this is, is this 80?
Probably 90.
This is 16 per processes.
Yeah, I can't see.
What is that number right there?
Is that 32?
That'll be 48.
Oh, it'll be 48.
So this is 48.
And what was this?
32?
So 32.
So what is, somebody just tell me real quick on a calculator.
What's 48 divided by 32?
1.5.
So you used 1.5 times the number of resources to do that, right?
Going from 32 to 48.
All right.
But when you went from 32 to 48, what was the difference in the time?
We can't see that over here because it's too, it's too hard to tell.
But over here, when we went from 32 to 48, the speed up brought up,
we went back to that other thing.
What we would find that I've seen is if we just stuck with 32,
it might have taken this long to run.
So like 32 processes running for this amount of time,
not in the product of the number of cores times the amount of time
represents the amount of work that's done.
So this is the work that is done.
And the work is proportional to the cost because it's like,
I want to use 100 servers for 10 hours.
So, you know, like persons, you know,
per-people hours or code, node hours or core hours.
The product of the number of resources multiplied by the amount of time
they're engaged is directly proportional to the cost you're going to pay for it
in a cloud environment.
And even though it's faster, you used 1.5 times.
Now, this went up by a factor of, you know,
like, you know, basically 50% here, factor 1.5.
The only way that would be useful to go to like 48, let's say it went to 48.
How fast, in other words, what would the new time,
this is the new time and this is the old time,
what would the new time have to be so that it was worthwhile to do this?
But in an ideal case, the product of this times this
would be equal to the product of that times that.
So, the area would have to be the same.
That would be the same amount of work that gets done.
But we know it ain't going to be that because that only works
if it's perfectly good about our losses.
But when we see it, it's not as inefficient.
That means you're actually, say, running this thing for this.
So, yeah, the time got shorter, but you did a lot more work.
So, you got a lot more cost.
So, you have to decide, like, where does the burden vary even more?
I'm trying to take this back.
This isn't just a play around, see what happens.
It's like it's directly related to what the cost is going to be to run this thing.
Because, you know, if you've got thousands of users running hundreds of jobs,
that's going to put a, you know, look at how big expense is.
And look at the number of people running at any one time on there.
You know, how many petaflosses is the machine?
I can't remember.
I mean, it's not a tiny amount, right?
It's a pretty significant computer.
So, this is kind of, you know, this helps us analyze what's going on.
Whereas, like, for example, for 1.9 million,
you might be able to be like, hey, I'm going to go all the way up there
because it's pretty much a straight line here.
Now, here, you might say, I'm not doing that.
I mean, I didn't hardly get any faster, and I used more resources.
Does that make sense?
Okay.
Now, I mean, how can we be more than 100%?
Well, this is that thing that we're saying that you can actually be more
than twice as fast as something when you go from one to two, for example.
I am not going to worry about explaining that right now
because that's not going to – you can look it up.
We're going to talk about it.
But for now, it's just what we got.
Okay.
It's what happened.
But in general, like, as you can see,
as this keeps getting a lot higher, you know,
we're weighing – you know, our efficiency is going down.
Now, let's see.
So, the original parameters we – that was asked to be done
both fit within 30 minutes.
The examples that I provided about accessing the debug partition
obviously showed that the largest amount of time you could run was 30 minutes
because that's not something I set.
That's the setting for the machines.
But the example I had was using – what was it?
Is it eight gigs or eight bags or something gigs of RAM?
But, like, well, yeah, the ones we didn't class
could only find up a couple of processes.
But here, like, we're spending up 128.
Will that fit within that amount of memory?
No.
You need to have more memory.
Now, you know, like, if you Google messages that you get
and you ask chatTQT, like, all right, and you can tell it.
I'm on the Expanse server at the San Diego Supervision Center.
Here's a link to the user guide to getting this message.
What are the possible explanations of this?
Well, it could be that your account doesn't have this.
It could be that or that.
It could be that they don't have a memory.
Oh, memory.
The other thing that you could do is you could run your programs
and collect additional log file information.
So, like, for example, what probably was happening there
is the operating system was killing the processes
based on an out of memory error.
You know, and so you could get the logs from that and do that.
I had just had this conversation with the people in the previous class,
the students in the previous class, you know,
almost said the same thing here, which is,
I haven't explained how to do everything.
I shouldn't have to.
This is the capstone course.
This is the end of the road.
A lot of the stuff in these capstone classes that are the IS and IT,
they're not teaching at all.
They're only doing projects, not saying anything, all on you.
I'm explaining some stuff, but I'm expecting that
with every resource you have available, all of my recorded stuff,
the book, chat GPT, MNI, Claude, co-pilot, Google,
you can figure out how to do this.
But you have to start on a well ahead of time.
Like, I don't know.
So, Mike, when did you start with this original assignment?
Like, before we had the update about the size of it.
Like, how long it would be between the time
that I mentioned it in class, that you actually started messing with it?
On Sunday.
So, the Sunday we just had.
So now, let's take a look here at the allocations that we've used here so far.
I'm going to go over here and look at something real quick.
I thought they had this on this webpage, but I guess they don't.
Because they tell us over here what the total situation is.
Do the thing at the command line to see what it is.
You can filter by project ID.
Okay.
Let's do this here too.
She's graduated.
He graduated.
Mike.
717 core hours.
So, let's talk about one quick question about something here.
It's more like a statement, but it is a question.
When you ask for 128 cores, whether it's on a compute node or a debug node,
it means you've got the whole node, right?
It doesn't matter how much RAM you ask for at that point.
Because no one else can use it.
So, you're not really being charged for the RAM because you've already used the whole machine.
Let's say you ask for four cores and 128 gigs of RAM.
How many gigs do they have?
I can't remember.
It's 108.
256.
So, you'd be charged for half the node.
Because which one is the biggest fraction?
128 out of 256, which is 50% or 4 out of 128?
So, the amount of core hours you get charged by is the bigger of those two factions
multiplied by the amount of time that you use it for.
So, if you're already asking for all the cores, it doesn't matter how much RAM you ask for at that point.
Now, if you're only asking for one core, then yeah, don't ask for all the RAM unless you need it.
Because if you're only asking for one core, you're only using one 128th of it.
That means that when you say you use one core for, let's say, two gigs of RAM.
So, that'd be two gigs out of 256, which is like one out of 128.
Which is like saying it's about one percent of the machine, right?
But then when you say for one core out of 128, that's the same fraction here.
Alright, so it's about one percent.
And let's suppose you used it for one hour.
Then you'd get charged for one core hour because they don't round now.
So, it'd be like one core hour.
But, like, if you were using all of the RAM for two things, for like two hours,
then it'd be two and then four.
It depends on how big the biggest one is.
So, the idea is if you're going to use exclusive access, just go use all the RAM.
It doesn't matter.
But if you're not using all of the node, then try to be thoughtful about how much RAM you use
because that's how this thing is.
But even you can see, like, people that have already graduated and went through this
and probably used it on more than one course.
They probably used it on three then.
You know, they were around, you know, say 15,000 over a couple of courses.
You know, now, let's suppose we all in here were at 15,000.
That would blow through the budget that we have.
Now, you may say, alright, well, cool.
Here's what I'm going to blow through the budget, and that way we won't have to do this anymore.
Like I said, if you go and do...
I already have an idea of what it already took every other student to ever do this stuff,
historically, since we got this thing.
So, I know what's a normal amount.
If there's something in here that's, you know, I get 50,000 for one student, for one assignment,
then you have it in responsibly, either through not being responsible or for purposely doing it.
Does that make sense?
So, please don't be abusive of the system, but use what is needed to do what you need to do.
Explore that space.
Alright, now, let's go back to the command line.
What about this report here?
Now, the report got voiceover in it?
The presentation I mean?
No.
Okay.
Let's just look and see what this looks like.
Now, I'm going to give some feedback.
You see this screenshot?
Even the full screen on this board, I can't.
I can't.
You can't hardly read what's there.
The fonts are so small.
You know, you saw how Mike went when he did the presentation.
Excuse me.
The report.
He put line continuations here, which is kind of cool because it made it instead, you know,
fit in this column, you know.
Do something like where you don't take a, let's say, a screenshot.
You're going to copy and paste the text, put it in monospace font, and then, like, put
the multiple rows in hand way so that you can actually read this thing better.
That would be better, you know.
This isn't as bad.
It's not quite as wide.
But I'd argue that, like, why don't we put a line continuation character here and another
one there.
And that way, everything would fit here.
And then, the font would have been about maybe this big.
The other thing I don't, and this must be you guys' machines, because none of the screenshots
I do ever work like this.
Every screenshot I take has aspect ratio locked.
So, when I take a corner, there's none of this squishing and squashing.
I don't know what's up, however you all do this stuff, but I don't know how you manage
to make it like that.
I can't make any of my screenshots allow you to do that crap, unless you come over here
and do that.
I don't know what it is about things.
Like, I would just say, don't ever change.
Like, I mean, not that Mike did.
He kept it more or less rectangular here.
But, like, I had a student this morning that had screenshots like this.
It's just like, don't do that.
But, like, I had to make it fit.
Like, okay, well, cool.
It fits.
Mike can't read it.
So, there's that.
Not like this kind of thing.
Like, when you start highlighting what it is that the issue is.
And that'll be cool, too, when you record over it.
Because as you're talking and as you're clicking, this thing will be popping up there
and it'll be dropping.
And I don't mean animation necessarily.
I just mean that it'll be flow.
It'll help direct the eyes of the thing that you're talking about.
So, let's see.
So, Mike did what I did, which I noticed that not everybody did this.
But, they're like, okay, cool.
I'm doing something with Python.
So, I'm going to load up Anaconda and I'm going to either create an environment
or use the one that's there to do something with an Anaconda
because that's the typical way you do stuff with Python.
Use some sort of package manager type of environment to create environments.
Not that you had to.
But, I mean, that's what I did.
That's what he did.
I think if you go and even ask, like, chat GPT and say, hey, you know,
I'm using this cluster here and I need to use Python on a remote node
and what are some of the things that we could do?
What might you do?
So, I went ahead and I had a thing that set it up here, ran the stuff.
So, these are the same results.
Now, me personally, this is me talking.
Like, we would make this full screen.
There's an awful lot of white space left on this thing that is usable.
Now, maybe not usable as is, but it's usable.
What can I do?
I don't know.
What could you do?
What about if instead of us having done this, let's say we did something like this.
Let's say we take this out of there, we take the top out of here
and we make this smaller.
I see it's one of these text boxes that bases at font size
based on the size of the thing as opposed to it's got an absolute font size.
It's just a resizable thing here.
Like, maybe we did something, I don't know what we could do here.
Let's get this out of the way.
Now, oh, we got these, that's a great show.
It's not the same, but whatever.
I would say, like, I don't know.
Maybe, like, try to have these plots be a little bit bigger.
Maybe use whatever fraction.
You can see them better.
Maybe put, like, the explanation below that.
Try to use the screen real estate that's there.
Imagine you're going to present it on the screen.
There's no reason not to use space if you can use it.
Because when we were looking at this report a minute ago,
we had it blown up looking at one plot.
It was a lot easier to think about stuff when we're using that screen real estate.
I'd say the same thing about this.
Now, one thing I do like about the way he did this is
every slide is parallel in a sense.
Like, I control Z and unmake those changes that I made.
It's like the format as I go from, like, here, one, two, three,
that's the exact same parallel format.
I mean, I think that's visually appealing to have it
so that it's not, like, well, it's alternating.
It's here this way.
I mean, it's uniform.
It's self-consistent.
All right.
So, questions about that particular assignment?
Now, let's go over here.
All right.
So, let's go to Moodle.
173.
Let's see.
Matrix vector.
Let's download that thing.
Talk about it in a second.
Now, let's see.
So, MPI, matrix vector, mobile machine,
atomic span, some short PBT, but no report.
And that's because we're not done yet with the milestones
that are going to even be done on this project.
But you need to be working on it right now.
I might even make this thing like it is right now.
I might even say this is a snapshot.
That's an assignment.
Keep moving on it.
Those are snapshots.
We're going to build up here a bit.
So, let's take a look at what this thing says.
I'm assuming Word will load here.
So, now, we're doing matrix vector,
which we were talking about in class, right?
We're doing that.
Please make use of these videos.
If there's things that, like, we went over,
don't ask me a question that I recorded.
Go back and find it.
Look at it.
That's what they're there for, okay?
So, reproduce things, replicate it on your own computer.
You need to capture some results.
Anybody got fewer than four cores in here?
Only got two or what cores?
What's the fewest cores anybody got?
You might want to save it.
What's the most cores anybody got on their machine?
Anybody got 32 on their machine?
Anybody got 16?
Anybody got 12?
Yeah, so, you know, 8 to 12, 6 to 12,
somewhere in there, right?
So, you can see some kind of results.
Let's see.
Now, oh, and one thing I would say about Mike's report,
because, well, let's wait until we look at this assignment
here right here.
So, we need to introduce the makefile here,
so we're going to make it, and we can run it.
And, you know, we've got a new Conda.
I highly recommend using Conda if I were you
on some of this stuff.
By the time it takes, run it, put the results out,
results are written out, efficiency is seen up.
See, we don't even have to have n being that big here,
because it's a square matrix, right?
And so, it's doubly nested four loops, so it's n squared.
Things are taking a lot more time here.
So, this guy might be the kind of thing that really would be parallelized.
And, in fact, that's the case.
Like, if you download and you use a matrix multiplication,
like, see, when you're insane, you're using, like,
a GPU-accelerated version of Python.
And it's got, in the NumPy thing, you've got a matrix multiplication routine.
Then it's the opportunity of saying, well, look,
actually, it'll do that in parallel, say, on your hardware.
And they can be parallel a lot of different ways.
Like, you could use the vector instructions that are on your CPU,
just a regular CPU that has vector instructions
that will operate on more than one piece of data at the same time.
70, or 70, they're probably 512-bit 70 instructions on your machine.
Which means that it could do, like, say, you know,
whatever it is, it could do four floating points at the same time,
or eight integers at the same time,
or whatever else that's inside a CPU, much less,
like, if you're on, say, on a Mac, and you've got an M1, M2, and M3,
then you've got the, what is it called?
The MPS, the metal, whatever, accelerator,
their version of an accelerator that's built in,
or if you're on, say, something's got a GPU.
Then it's going to have a GPU that may be a version of matrix multiplication
that could be linked in there.
The idea is, at least, that's the possibility that it would be doing it.
But what we're doing here is we're writing it in an NDI.
Because the idea is that that's transformable across nodes.
Now, we're doing it all in one node right now.
But we could be doing it in a distributed shared memory,
excuse me, distributed memory fashion.
Keep the time.
Okay, cool.
Anyway, it looks like we've got a couple of different things.
We've got the efficiency, speed-up, and time,
just for the math part of it.
And then an efficiency, speed-up, and time for the whole thing.
Because think about this.
What does this matrix multiplication thing do?
It has to read in the matrix from a file.
It has to read in the vector from a file.
Then it has to multiply the matrix times the vector.
Then it has to write that vector to a file.
So there's file IO and there's math stuff going on.
Now, the part we're parallelizing is what?
The whole thing?
No.
And in the book, it's only parallelizing
that outer loop of the doubly nested for loop.
That means we're not parallelizing the IO at all.
So, that's like saying,
if you take how long it runs on one processor,
the T1,
even like the sequential version of the program,
it's like, read the matrix,
read the vector,
multiply the matrices,
write the vector.
So this is like, read matrix,
read the vector,
multiply matrix vector,
and this is write the vector back out to the file.
Those all take time.
The two biggest things is,
reading the matrix and multiplying the matrix.
Because this thing is,
the memory in this is order-inspired
and the compute in this is order-in-square.
So, let's think about just this part.
That's the part we can parallelize.
And these are the parts that we're not parallelizing.
Let's say that this is 80% of the execution of the program.
So we would have 20% of the execution of the program
we can't do anything about.
80% that we can do about.
So now this is back to animals again, right?
Now, if I just looked at the entire damn program,
it's an extent error with this thing.
But the total speedup is a function of like,
I'm still paying for this.
Well now, that doesn't really tell us how well we parallelize just the math part
because we're measuring the whole thing.
No, no, no, this thing says, no, no, don't do that.
Just look at the time it took to do this
and then compare that and look at the efficiency speedup as time for that.
Because that doesn't tell us how well the parallelization worked, right?
Because you're not parallelizing the whole thing.
And then you've got how well did it work with respect to the whole thing.
Because the end user, they don't really care about it or where the problem is at, right?
They just see it from a total time.
So that's what's going on right here.
That's why there are six plots here.
There's time, speedup, and efficiency for the whole thing.
Time, speedup, and efficiency for just the matrix multiplication.
Does that make sense?
So like, for example, if we look at the speedup for the whole thing,
this doesn't look very good.
Like, once you get to six, I mean, hell, at six, we're only two times faster.
And then it shoots down.
That's the whole program.
But now, what about the part we just parallelized?
Well, that's that part.
Of the part that was doing the math on 12 processes,
we were doing almost 10 times as fast.
But now that's just on the matrix vector.
What about if we were in a program where the matrix and the vector were already in RAM
because it was the output of a previous program that's still in RAM?
It was the output of a query to a database that's sitting there in RAM.
Then there'd be no overhead of working with that data because it's already in RAM.
Would you ever have one program that all it did is one matrix vector multiply?
Probably not.
That's probably going to be inside of another loop.
It does hundreds or thousands of matrix vector multiplies
where the output of one thing is the input to the next thing or something like that.
If that's the case, you're only paying for that reading the very first time.
You're only paying for that writing the very last time.
But the rest of the time, you're getting this kind of thing going on, hand waving, ideally.
Does that make sense?
That's why we want to compare both.
That's why this thing is doing both.
I'm trying to explain to you why it's doing what it's doing right now.
That's so we can measure both of those things.
So it's cool.
The part we work on worked pretty damn well.
But the cost of the fact that the reading and writing took so long,
actually the speedup would really get in.
Isn't that great?
Because we're not speedup or stuff.
But we will talk about it later.
How could we speed up the reading and writing through a couple of different things?
Actually, now would be a good time to talk about one of those things.
It's not complicated.
It's not programmatic.
It's not something.
Where are these files being read and written to and from on this thing?
When you run this thing, like when Mike ran that command in his directory,
where the hell did it actually write?
What physical device was it being stored to?
Now on my computer, when I read and write,
where is the disk that it's writing to?
Where?
It's in here.
Isn't it?
Where is the RAM where that data was at?
In here.
Where is it on expense?
You think the disk that you're writing to is in the node you're on?
Nope.
Let's go see.
We can prove that.
Because you know how in here I talk about benchmarks,
speeding analysis.
What would I even expect?
You know, what would I expect it to be?
So let's go back over here to our portal.
We're going to log in.
And I'm going to do a print working directory.
So I'm currently at home wdumps.
Sweet.
Where is that?
Is that inside this computer?
Well, there's a way we can tell.
How do you mean you have done enough stuff with Linux
so that you know that we're on a Linux server
and we can issue a command that would tell us where that is?
Well, let's take this, df-h.
All right?
And let's do this.
If I'm on Linux, what command can I use to figure out
where its storage devices are, like locally or somewhere else?
Let's keep that working.
We're going back over here.
Now, let's make this a little bit smaller,
because we got the things coming out of there.
OK, cool.
All right, here we go.
User wjones, home directory.
Where is that mapped back to?
That's mapped back to a folder called pool2
that's at this IP address.
That could be my home.
That could be the IP address of this machine, possibly.
Look at this.
Pool1 is .1.
Pool2 is .2.
Three, you know.
What in the hell is going on?
Well, these are network-mounted drives.
That's like when you're on your laptop and over here at Finder
and it says, hey, your OneDrive thing is over here.
But that OneDrive stuff, that's not on your computer.
Now, yeah, you're going to be synchronized and pulled down,
but that's some cloud storage place.
Imagine how much you think about this.
This server doesn't have to have any disks in it.
You could just be sitting there.
You know what, if you didn't have disks, how'd they boot it up?
They could boot it up across the network.
It doesn't need to boot off the device inside of it.
It could boot across the network.
That's actually simpler.
You don't ever have to install the machine you're on.
You just have to boot directly from some place off the network.
I mean, you've been able to do that since the early 90s.
That's old school.
Yeah, they got cooler stuff for it now.
A little more better, a little faster, whatever, buddy.
That makes it really easy because that way when you boot,
you don't have to change that one image over there for all the machines.
You don't have to reinstall anything because they're all going to be used to tell everybody,
reboot, and then they reboot, and they're all the right thing.
So I mean, this is basic Linux-like system administration stuff.
Now, we don't know how they did it.
That's what we're trying to figure out.
But I would intend to do that this directory is not on the computer
that I am logged into right now.
It is across the network, hopefully not far away, hops-wise, but it's over there.
So do you expect to be able to read and write to that IP address
as fast as you can read and write to a solid-state disk inside that computer?
Because it's not cloud.
It's network-attached storage.
But I would imply that it's actually across the internet, like outside the domain of this place.
Hell, it might be, but I doubt it.
It's probably inside the same building wherever this thing is.
I'm guessing.
All right, let's see what SatChat2T said.
Another thing we could type is these volumes that are attached.
You know, like in Windows, like C colon, D colon, the drive letter colon, and all that kind of mess.
On Linux, those are called mounted things.
They have mount points.
There's no drive letter.
So there's literally like a folder that is the folder that's attached to the device that it's mounted to.
And how can you get a list of all the things that are mounted?
You can type a word, mounted.
Man, there's a bunch of stuff mounted.
Well, let's see.
Now, I want to look for just the thing that's associated with me.
So I'm going to type to grep, which means filter, for wmjones.
Cool.
So it says that wmjones is mounted to a volume that's being served on a network-attached storage device
without an IP address.
And the type of this file system is network file system.
It's an NFS that's been around since before I was in college.
It is the de facto way to do this.
It's free, easy.
Is it fast enough?
No, not necessarily.
But it allows you to attach a storage device across a network that will allow you to read and write from it,
as if you're reading and writing from your actual computer.
Your computer doesn't know any difference.
Like, when I do F read and F write, it has no idea that I'm actually writing to something
that's somewhere else.
Does that make sense?
So that tells us how we could do this.
Now, let's go see what it says here.
Okay.
You could listen to block devices, and you could see whether they're mounted to devices
that are on the computer.
Because if they're actually on the computer, they'll have the slash, the device file.
Like, that's also where your video card would be, and other things would be a slash dev,
or device, that you call mount points.
Apparently, there's all these other source stuff.
But I typically use this one.
Because that shows you the things that are mounted.
And if they weren't mounted, then we'd be looking at some of the kind of things,
looking at the, you could say, like, LSPC, I show you everything that's attached to the PCI bus
of this computer, and then grab from storage devices.
You can also look at the things that are attached via USB, for example.
You can list the LSPC connect device.
Now, some of these things you might not want to type, because if you try to do something
that changes the state of something, that would be like a violation.
That would be like you need super user access to do that.
But if you're just looking at some of this basic stuff, you could do it.
Yeah, see how they did mount, and they piped it.
And it said, let me look for an NFS, or a lesser file system, or GDFS, or SEP, or something.
I don't know what this one is. I'm not familiar with that one.
I don't know what kind of file system that is.
But that tells you all your devices.
So, if it's on your computer, it'll be slash F.
If it's a mount, it'll have an IP address over there.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Now, is there any way on Expanse that I could run it so it's not in my home directory?
Where could I put it?
Because my home directory, first of all, if you make really big files,
you can't do that in your home directory because you don't have enough quota space.
But what about if you wanted to make that?
Well, you can. Let's go over there and look at how you would do this.
Plus, if it's on NFS, it's going to be slower than an SSD-attached storage device on the node.
So, how do you actually do that?
Okay. Well, here's how you do it, all right?
Actually, you can look at the guide, but I'm just going to show you.
All right. So, they were right here.
History. I want to look at my command, so I don't have to retype it.
And it looks like I was getting a compute node here.
I don't really want to do that. I'll get a debug node because I don't need to use all the cores right now.
Hell, why not? Let's do that.
So, debug partition.
Assuming I can get it in there, I don't want to see.
If not, we'll go to the compute.
This thing right here, this job ID, is going to be important right here.
Okay. So, we're going to want to copy that.
All right. Let me also try to get into a compute node.
There we go.
Looks like I got into a compute node before I got into this one.
So, I'm going to hit control C.
Okay. I'm not going to worry about that one.
So, now, notice how I was on the login node.
I'm now on this node.
And my job ID is this.
And that would be unique for every single person that runs every job, a new job.
So, I'm going to copy that.
Now, let's do this here.
Let's go to slash device.
Is that where it is? Actually, hold on. Hold on.
It's in the scratch file system.
I'm trying to see if I remember.
I'm really going to have to look it up in the device here.
Probably going to have to look it up over here.
I'm going to go back to the user guide because I don't remember.
So, I'm going to do control F, scratch space.
Okay.
Now, the scratch space,
scratch means space that you can write stuff to,
but that you can't be guaranteed that it'll be backed up.
It's scratch. It's like a scratch piece of paper.
You put the error, you use it all you want.
It might go away.
Keeping some in your home directory is going to be backed up.
It's not going to go away. That's the idea.
But now, this thing says that it's a scratch space on the luster file system.
That's probably not where, like, that's just another file system.
In that case now, that's a parallel file system.
That's better than NFS.
NFS is not a parallel file system.
But if we go down here and look underneath there,
there's actually a local scratch disk.
That's an SSD device.
Flash storage. One terabyte SSD.
Okay.
And it says that you can access it by going to
slash scratch slash your user ID
slash the job ID.
You see that?
So, where can I write it to?
I can write my input and output files to that directory.
So, let's go over there and find that.
As I said, it was in slash scratch.
No, I'm not going to log in, though. That ain't going to work.
I'm going to go over here.
I was freaking out. I was like, oh, God, that's not there.
Alright. So, cd slash scratch.
Now, there's a bunch of people's directories in here.
But I'm not going to be able to go into theirs.
I'm going to be able to go into mine.
So, cd wmjones.
And look at that.
There's only one directory in there I can really write to.
And it's that one.
Because that's associated with this job I just started.
And when my job ends,
that directory won't necessarily be there again.
They're probably going to wipe it out, if my guess.
I don't know. Because it's scratch.
Think about it.
If everybody was using this SSD,
every time they logged out,
you know what I mean?
Like, if you've got exclusive access nodes,
shouldn't you be able to write the entire disk if you wanted to?
So, we're going to go over here.
We're in here.
So, we can write a file there.
There's a file right there.
Now, what about in du dash h,
so disk usage for that directory?
I wonder if it will let me ask that question on slash scratch.
Probably not, yeah.
So, not a whole lot has been used right there.
We could probably come over here and make a really big file.
Like, say you just want to make a really big file,
just all of a sudden, just to see what happens.
So, let's come over here and say,
there's a blast of a bunch of files out there.
So, let's copy this.
So, this would give me a one gigabyte file full of zeroes.
Let's try that. Let's see if that works.
Because it's actually writing the data,
and if I timed that,
I could tell how fast it took to write that out.
So, let's try that pretty damn fast.
So, what about, let's do 4096.
So, 1.9 gigabytes a second, this was only 62.
Why would that be?
Well, there's other kind of stuff going on here inside this disk
that I want you to think about, like,
imagine this disk has some kind of local cache.
What is the next 8192?
Now, this is like a sequential write.
It's writing bytes one after another into a file.
Now, those aren't random writes.
Random writes would be slower, normally, a little bit.
So, it looks like we're getting about
670 megabytes a second of write speed to this thing
when we just generated an 8.6 gigabyte file.
Okay, well, like, how about we want to benchmark, like,
what if, let's see, what if I want to benchmark,
sequential read and write speed of an SSD device.
That's my type of spelling, it's horrible.
Sequential read, some gotchas that could be caching.
If you do something too small,
you can get answers that are affected by caching.
Oh, the file FIO, that's a benchmark suite itself
that can be used to look at read and write speed.
So, like, for example, you could benchmark
how fast the actual device is,
and then you could measure how long it took you to read
and write a matrix in front of a file,
work backwards, and see, like, is your program actually
getting the same read and write speed
as the device is supposed to get?
Because, you know, like, when you measure how fast something is
that you've designed in the program,
the ultimate question is, well, what's the fastest it can be?
Well, it can't be any faster than the device.
That gives you some upper bound to say,
the read and write speed say this is only, you know,
one gigabyte a second.
So, you're never going to give anything more than that
with a sequential read and write on one drive.
Now, why don't there are two drives?
And you write both of them at the same time,
and it's parallel.
Now, you need to get a write speed that's faster,
which you use twice a minute.
So, we're going to talk about parallel I-O later.
Right now, we're talking about parallel computation.
The other thing is parallel I-O.
And unfortunately, I-O is the thing that, like,
a lot of people don't think about when they look at parallel systems.
Everybody thinks it's cool to look at the computation.
Keep you accelerated.
Wow, that's awesome.
Yeah, but where did all this data come from?
Well, let's assume you already have it in RAM.
Cool, but the very first time, it ain't in RAM.
It's coming from somewhere.
So, I just want to point out that, like, parallel fossils
are a big thing on these things.
So, you know, I asked in this report, I want benchmarks done.
I want to know what the speeds of these things are.
So, look around and see what you can do.
Is it going to be perfect? Probably not.
But it'll be some kind of thing that you did to try to see.
And then what about if you read and wrote your data file
to and from that thing over there,
the matrix and vector, and you're getting a speed that's faster
than what we got on this thing?
Well, what could be going on?
Well, maybe the matrix is not big enough,
so it's being done by caching.
So, what about if you benchmarked it for a number of bytes
equal to the size of the matrix, then you'd take the caching into effect?
What about if it was something else?
What about if the way F-read and F-write works,
does it wait for the whole thing to actually be written to the disk?
Let me ask you a question.
Let's suppose you said write was one gigabyte file out to F-write.
F-wrote it out.
And F-write returns to the next line in the program.
Does that mean that that file is actually on that device
when that function returns?
It could just be in a copied place in memory that is protected
so it puts it in a buffer.
It's like, hey, you want to write this data to a file?
Cool.
It makes a copy of it right there and it returns to your program
and then a DDMA control, a direct memory access control,
is writing this thing to the file while your computer goes on a desktop.
What about if you did one?
You might say, oh my god, it's like 10 terabytes a second.
It's like, yeah, that's how much it was to copy it from one place in memory
to another place in memory.
It's not how long it took to go from memory to the disk
because you're not actually measuring the thing that you think you're measuring.
So benchmarking is an entire thing,
so if you don't even really know what you're measuring,
you have to, you say, I know what I'm measuring
is the time it went from this line to this line in the program.
Yeah, but what does that actually mean that really took place on the computer?
And it is the thing that took place on the computer,
the thing you're trying to measure.
All these things that all come into play here.
So any questions about this design, what kind of questions do you have about it?
How many of you have started on this assignment?
It's okay, but I changed the code so I can always describe it.
On your laptop you mean?
Yes, on my laptop.
All right, so that's a great question.
I'm glad we're asking that.
All right.
And I'll work to the answer.
So the answer is, I know, don't do that.
Let me explain why, all right?
Notice how in my code here, when he ran it on Expanse,
he went from 1 to 128 because that's what was available.
That's not how many cores it has.
But when he ran it on his own machine, he only went from 0 to 8
because that's the only number of cores he has.
So you could run it oversubscribed up to 128 probably.
But let's suppose that you had some way of doing hyperthreading on those 8
and you had it core locked that the threads were doing whatever
and you weren't using full weight processes and stuff,
you could probably benefit up to some point.
But after about 16, I mean, all the other stuff,
you're just spawning up a bunch of processes.
What are they doing?
They're doing this.
There's 128 processes running, 128 of them.
And only these 8 are running at the same time.
And then those 8 are running and these 8 are running.
And you're spending a bunch of time going around between these things.
That's from 356, right?
Process management, the waiting queue, the running queue, the blocked queue.
Is there any reason to have all these queues?
Yeah, I need the queues.
Is there any reason to fill up with a bunch of processes?
Probably not.
No, it is cool to do it.
Let's see what happens.
What you'll probably see is this complete crap.
Did you try it more than 8?
No.
Well, you probably see that if you oversubscribed it,
it would totally suck after 8 or maybe after 10 or 12.
Somewhere in there it would just, the speed would go like this,
the time would go like that, and the efficiency would go like that.
I mean, that's all we have.
Because you don't have that in any course.
So don't worry about on your own computer
testing out a number of processes that exceeds the number of cores that you have.
That's a good question.
I see that.
I think, I think I've been there a long time,
when the mom and the child sorted a little.
Okay.
Wait.
I gotcha.
But moving forward, like, on your own computer, you only need to go up to,
you can do that.
But the only thing that's really important is from 1 to the number of cores that you have.
And other stuff, you can gather that data, but it doesn't really mean much.
In fact, you should, the only, the most meaningful thing about it is to see that,
that's not a good idea.
And then you're like, cool, that's why you don't do that.
I think somebody else was raising their hand before that.
I thought you were raising your hand, but I got you, you're probably stretching.
Other questions?
Didn't you question about anything?
This assignment or otherwise?
All right.
Well, I hope everybody has a great day.
If you want any of these flyers about open positions,
click now, and we'll talk with you guys later.
Have a great weekend also, all right?
Yeah.
It's not really done.
Okay.
But I wanted to see if you had an idea of what you might want to talk about,
just because I want to go to a discussion in DC and it's from the 8th to the 10th.
So, I think the final?
So, send me an email to remind, I don't know when it is, but like my plan was that
it was going to be whenever the university said it was.
Have you checked to see when that's supposed to be?
I looked a little bit back and I've seen any of you.
So, let me, send me an email and I'll send you back where the university has this grid
and it says, you know, every class, when that exam is.
If when the exam is interferes with your trip, then let's take that one step at a time
and we'll see, but like what that probably would be is, it would be like, okay, well
then you got to take it ahead of time.
Yeah.
That's the kind of thing.
But let's, that's supposed to be the kind of thing that I have to get approval from
the dean's office because technically I'm supposed to give everybody the final exam
at the same time.
So, let's see.
I'm skipping out on the first stage because I do have another exam.
So, like I have an exam on the 8th.
So, I'll only be probably for those last two days of confidence.
But, I mean, I'm happy to work with you about the case.
It's just, let's figure out when it's supposed to be and then see what the deal would have to be.
Then let me, you write up a thing, then I kind of give that to the chair, the dean and say,
hey, my plan is to give this student eggs the, you know, the exam ahead of time because
of the fact that she wants you to do the same and blah, blah, blah.
Make sure it's okay.
One time, like I, yeah, please, yeah.
One time I gave an exam a long time ago and even all the students agreed to it.
Like, they were like, yeah, we'll all take it on this day, which was earlier because they wanted to go.
The university's like, that's not your call to make.
You know, you can't decide that.
Like, that's our chance.
They're like, well, it's probably about if one of those students who said yes, then they
changed their mind once they saw the exam.
And they were like, they didn't give me the entire time to study.
So I just don't want to make sure they don't come and say, well, hey, if you would say you
wound up doing that on the exam, then you say, you made me take it early.
And I'm like, well, hold on.
I didn't make you take it early.
You know, you chose to do it.
Like, well, I'm happy to work through it.
I just need to, it's been a while since that's happened.
So let me, let me just, I don't know what the current policies are.
So we'll figure it out.
All right.
Thank you.
Yeah, absolutely.
Yes, sir.
So I might end up sending you an email some time later.
Okay.
I'm not sure if I'll be here today.
But it's just me.
Yeah.
Okay.
I mean, yeah, whatever.
It would be like a private information.
I don't know.
I don't know if I've seen you pay for it.
So I might just send you an email.
So my thought would be like, what do you want to achieve?
What are the masteries?
What are the things you want to get out of that experience?
And what is your main interest area?
I still don't need to look forward to that.
Because the reason I'm thinking is, like, if your interest is the kind of stuff
that that degree is about, that's cool.
But if it's kind of like, if it's not a great match, you don't, well, there's a
couple of things.
Like, I don't think there's going to be a lot of opportunity for it to be paid
for in the way it is at other universities when you go physically there and you,
you do jobs, like you teach classes or you teach labs or whatever.
And the university pays you.
And on top of that, they waive your tuition.
Now, I mean, I don't believe Coastal does that for this online degree program
because it's online.
How do you teach something not here?
So I don't know about, and there was this discussion about that recently.
So send me an email about it.
And I will ask if there's, because there is supposed to be, you know,
because they endowed that thing with a million dollars.
But they can't sell, they can't use the principal.
They can only use the interest.
But even a 4% interest on a million dollars is $40,000 a year.
So one might argue, well, then you could have enough.
You could have, you could waive the tuition for a student.
And that was like your top student.
And you could do that.
So like, that's kind of stuff being discussed.
I just, I don't know like what the full deal is.
But send me the thing and I'll find out.
But the other thing I'd say is, aside from that, depending on what your interest
areas are, as well as like, you didn't have loads from a school that has like a
more traditional in-person brick and mortar masters during computer science.
Like, you might find that those places would definitely pay for it.
Because in a lot of places, like the graduate students are foreign nationals.
And foreign nationals have to pass like a, the reading and the writing tests
and speaking tests, first of all, be accepted to that school.
But in a lot of places, there'll be a preferential treatment to say,
if you're a native speaker of English, then this university is probably going to
push you in a place where you're interacting with people in the classroom.
And it might do that less frequently with people that don't speak English as well
because they don't want their students to not be able to understand what's going on.