Okay, all right
All right, so what I want to do today is to say all right now that we have that homework assignment that you did
What is something we might want to do with that program?
To look at its performance as a function of the number of processes as well as as a function of the number of divisions
That are done. You know that in other words those two parameters n and p or n and p basically
so
Part of what you'll see that we're doing in here is that we'll write a program
But then we need to analyze it when you look at like how effective it is
Do we get the same answers do we get better performance if we increase the number of processes and so forth and so?
I made a little folder in here
And I'll share this code with you guys later, you know, it's not not a big deal. I'm happy to share it
But so I made you know, I made my version of the modified
Trapezoid thing to follow the deal about our we said about homework. So let's just take take a look at this
So I'm gonna MPI CC it dash wall dash G dash Oh
I
Pile it say to you know, I'm gonna try to run this thing now
Now I'm gonna run without any parameters at first here. I'm not gonna pass it a B and N
And I get a nice use of statement. So if your
Code doesn't work this way already make sure moving forward that it does. Okay
I don't want it to blow out if I don't produce any inputs
What is the typical thing you do for a command line program?
If you don't pass any parameters to it, it either is going to assume something and run it, which I do not want
I want it to give me what's called the usage statement. Is everybody clear on that?
So just check to make sure that any required arguments are in fact there and if they're not
Print a usage statement to the user to let them know hey the way you run this thing is
You run the program along with you have to pass it a B and N
Okay, it doesn't set fault. It doesn't blow out doesn't have some kind of crazy MPI error any of that
How many people wrote their program to already do that?
But raise a hand. All right
So now here we go. I'm going to integrate this is x squared, right? So I'm going to integrate from 0 to 2
And I pre-calculated what the integration from 0 to 2 is of x squared. It should be 2 and 2 thirds
Okay, so looking at this thing and I'm going to say I'm not only going to divide it into like a hundred hundred intervals
Which is not much
And let's see what happens
So I get you know 2 and 2 thirds
This point 6 though should be out here a good bit more than that though, right because like it's supposed to be real close to 2
thirds
Of that fraction and we can see like for example if I increase the number of things
That it started that you know now this this moved over a little bit more down here
So it's getting closer to 2 thirds like maybe I do a bunch of them getting closer to 2 thirds
It's never going to be exactly 2 thirds obviously for number reasons
You know one reason is you can't you know, you can't have exactly that that fraction in there and number two
It's you know, it's never going to be perfectly this discretization not ever going to be really equal to the to the value
Now these other parameters I'm printing out to the screen here. That's a that's B
That's the number of N that I ask it to do and this is the number of processes and this is the total elapsed time
Now I didn't ask you to do this on the homework assignment
But imagine you need to update that for your next version of the assignment like I want this there because
With a couple of things like moving forward. We need to be able to evaluate the performance of this program as we change N and P
And what do we mean? Like we'll do like for example, here we go. Check this out. I'm gonna go ahead
Let's let's say I'll go up to that big. So that's that only put point zero two seconds now that that's freaking fast already
That's not slow, right? I mean, okay. What about if I add another couple of zeros to it that took point two seconds
What if I've had another zero?
Alright 1.7 seconds
It's not great when you're dealing with programs that are already so fast that the amount of time it takes them to run is very slow
Anyway, like very excuse me very fast and ie very short anyway, but this first program we've got
What's the loop structure in there? Is it a triple quadruply nested for loop?
No, it's just a one-dimensional floor loop. So our computer is pretty fast nowadays
It's gonna do a one-dimensional for loop really freaking fast anyway
But if we increase the precision now you think about what we're doing here every time we we do this
We're increasing the fidelity of our model because if you think about it
This is supposed to be equal to the analytical integration from a to b of x squared
So the bit the more divisions you have the smaller the width of each division and the more this Riemann summation turns out to be
like the integral of it, right
So I want you to think about like this it's like in a science program
This would be us be getting better fidelity in our model, you know
Imagine you're talking about a picture of somebody
This is like difference between like a 10 by 10 image and a 20 by 20 or a thousand by thousand image
Like you you're gonna get more less pick less pixelation as you get more
Spatial fidelity. Well here we're doing the same thing
We're getting more spatial about developing fidelity by dividing the interval from a to b into smaller smaller chunks
By having in be larger, right?
now really what I'm doing here is just making in big enough that it takes a little bit of time because if I
What are we doing parallel programming? One thing is to make it faster. Well, you don't need to make something
That's two hundredths of a second faster do you?
But something and even really one point was the 1.7 seconds. That's not great
But now what about if I kick this up by another factor of 10?
Now
It just blew out and that's because the data type is being used for this
Isn't big enough to hold a number that's that large
So, you know, I could try to change my data types to be bigger
I could do that, but I don't want to I don't want to do that right now
So what I don't know like what is like the biggest thing that I could that I could do here now
We could go work backwards and figure out what about if I made this like a two?
So about three point seven seconds that makes sense because it was one point seven seconds before and I just
Doubled the amount of work that it has to do in that for loop, but it went up to three point seven
So I'm feeling pretty good about that now three point seven is big enough that we can actually we can actually parallelize that we can
We could watch it get faster. Like for example, that was with two processes. What about if I only use one process?
Now I don't remember if I have this written in a way that will be okay with one process or not. Let's see
Six point five seconds. Okay, so one here we go now, right? So
So if we're talking about P
All right, so we went from one to two. So the time on P so one took what six point five. What did you take?
Three point four, let's go do let's go do
Four all right one point eight
It's still getting smaller. What about if I now my computer only has 12 cores?
So what about if I do eight?
Double the number of processes again point nine five. Okay, so eight
Point nine five
Now I can't remember my computer the other four cores. I have maybe efficiency cores
They're not as fast as the other cores, but let's see what happens if we go up to 12
These not all the cores on my computer at the same speed and that means it's a heterogeneous system
which means it's a little hard to
to kind of
Think about like how it ought to perform because they're not all the same speed
Like if you're gonna work on something, they're not all the same speed you wouldn't divide the workup evenly
Would you you give the slow processors less work to do?
But we haven't done that here. Right? So let's see. Let's do 12
Point seven. Well now
So if I were to graph that out
so one
two three four
Six seven eight nine ten eleven twelve. All right, so I don't know like I'd get some sort of thing, right?
so up here at this one is a
Six point five and then it's dropping and it's dropping like this right at times doing something like that kind of
Now the speed up
Remember is the time on one divided by the time on P. That's what we said before right?
So if we were to do this, let's calculate the speed up here
So the speed up of
One processor over one processor is just T sub one divided by T sub one
Which is six point five by six point five which is one. So it's one times as fast obviously because it's the it's the baseline, right?
Now what about this one?
This one's going to be a time on one divided by the time on two
So this will be six point five divided by three point four. Can somebody put that in the calculator really quickly?
Just give me a number for that
All right, so one point nine times. All right, let's do this one too. This is six point five divided by one point eight
Three point six
See point six times let's do this one six point five by one point nine five
Eight X and then finally let's do this one six point five divided by
3x so
The fastest we ever made it was nine point three times faster than the baseline
So the parallel version on our computer up to twelve processors
We could max out at about nine point three times faster, at least for the stuff
I checked I didn't try running any more processes than this
I don't even have any more cores than that
So my expectation would be if I keep increasing number of processes at some point in time and start sucking
Like for example, let's try this. I don't
What about if we say 20 now it says I got to over subscribe it right
So let me over subscribe
0.73 that's worse than it was at 12
That's what I mean. If you just increase our increasing number of processes think about it. They're sharing these cores
They're not they're not they're not gonna be like if I did if I went up here and I said, all right
I want to do a 200
It's even slower. So
Eventually, what would happen is we kept this thing up it would do like this
It would just start it would start doing that
So there's no point in going any further than this because it's not getting faster, right?
Okay, let's plot this speed up
All right. So now we've got all this axis P. So same thing. So 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12
And the first one at 1 that's going to be a speed up of 1
That's 1.0
now the ideal speed up
Shit I'm sorry, I was thinking about efficiency. Let's put one down here
Now the ideal speed up would be a straight line
With a slope of 1 here, right because in the ideal case speed up ideal would be equal to number of processes
Like if it was 1 2 3 4 processor before times as fast
It was 8 at the 8 times as fast as 12 at the 12 times as fast
All right, but now let's go and actually look at this thing. So we got 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12
And let's plug in these actual numbers move. We measured this empirically, right?
So let's see. So 1 2
2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
Alright, so 1 it was 1 on
2 it was 2. It was 1.9. So not quite not quite up there at that line, right?
Let's see 4 it was at 3.6
Maybe here
It's a little exaggerated
At 8 it was 6.8. So 8
8.8 maybe here and
12 it was 9.3
3 so this thing is kind of doing like this
You see that
That's pretty normal
Because
The gap that there is between this and this is how much you're not getting of the maximum
finally
The efficiency is equal to the speed up on P
divided by P
So if we were to plot our efficiency
And P 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 got efficiency
Highest efficiency is 1.0 with 1. So the ideal efficiency would be like this
But then this thing starts going down
Very quickly, right? Like what's the efficiency right here? So the speed up on this last one is 9.3
But the ideal speed up should have been equal to P. So it should have been 12
So what is 9.3 divided by 12 Mike?
Approximately
0.8
So 80%
Okay, so not you're not too bad, I mean it's 80%
But you're you know, or you've got 12 cores doing
you know
They're being used and they run a little bit longer than they should have run if it was the ideal case
So so more electricity is being spent now
Obviously it's 12 times as much for that time
The time has only been shortened to one ninth the original time, but the power has been multiplied by 12 times
Right. So that's not where that efficiency is happening. Like it's not getting it's not getting a hundred percent efficiency in this
It's never going to now
That was for this particular
number of in
But now what about if I had chosen a smaller in and
I wanted to get all this data
What about if I wanted to choose a bunch of different ends and I wanted to gather this data and plot it
So as Chad chippy teach and say give me a script that will run my program repeatedly get the answers from it and plot it
Okay
I've considered a completely acceptable thing for the class. We said you just use the stuff
Okay, we got to know what we're looking for here though. And what we're trying to figure out is
What is the behavior of our program as a function of two variables changing P and the end?
Okay, so we want to see like this the surface if you will. Okay, so
Got a Python program here
NPI trap
I
H
The interface for this thing
so
I've got it running so that these are the parameters that you tell it you tell it where you want to start integrating from so the a to
be
You tell it like the smallest in you want to do. So what's the smallest size in I want to do
What's the biggest size in I want to do and how much increment don't want to do like don't want to go from a hundred
Thousand to one million a thousand at a time
For all those different sizes of in like thinking like what about the ends a thousand ten thousand hundred thousand one million like that
Like now this is not a multiplicative increment. It's an active, but you could have it multiplicative
So it's you know doubling or quadrupling every time or whatever
This is the lowest the fewest number of processes. I want to run it on
This is the maximum number of processes. I want to run it on and this is how many processes I
Change it by each time song and I'm going to choose one because I want to try it for everything like one process two
Three four five want to collect all that data and plot it
I want to do this stuff manually run it over and over and over again, right?
so
We're gonna give this a shot here. Now. Let's see
We ran this thing here
all right, so
Let's take a look at this here
So here I'm saying I want us to
Run
the program
Integrate from zero to two. I want to start at n equals this
I want to end that n equals that and I want to go up by this amount every in
And I want to go from one process to 12 because that's number of cores my machine has and I want to go up
By one core every time
Okay. Now. I'm not saying what program to run here
Like I'm but in the background the default is right with MPI CC as a sub process using my using my thing
alright, so I
Have it have a little give us a progress bar because it knows it's going to do 120 experiments, right?
It knows the number of times in loop is going to happen and time P loop is going to happen
That's the product so the 120 experiments
So it's doing 120 here
It's got a bunch of that stuff and I haven't dropped out some PNGs into the file system. That's got the timing on it
All right, so I'm going to open up this folder
So let's look at the timing
So
The end that I chose like so look at this like so the biggest end is the one that took the most amount of time
Which makes sense, right?
so
Our total time now is only a little bit more than a third of a second here
So, you know, but we can see that as we increase the number of processes for that size in we got this end
That's going down here. We got that. Excuse me the time that's going down
Now look at this one
That's with only that number of trapezoids or whatever like that that didn't really help too much here, didn't it?
So that means that the amounts
Betterness that you can get it's kind of limited to how much work you had to do to start out with
This first thing was running less than 0.05 seconds. It was already running fast now even starting in PI
Even running a program in the operating system. It's going to take some overhead
It doesn't matter if that for loop happens like this, right that that other stuff's gonna be some fixed overhead
So you're gonna see that a lot of diminishing returns there. So what about if we look at the speed up for this?
So when the number of trapezoids the amount of work that had to be done is small
You see we don't ever even get I mean we were on two processes and it's not even it's a little bit faster, but not much
Eight and twelve went up a little bit didn't even get that it didn't even get better than 1.5 times as fast
That's really inefficient because you're using eight processors, but you're only getting a 1.5 speed up
You should be getting a eight speed up right ideally
So we can see that like for example for the really big number of them in though. We're getting a little bit better
So for here for in here
This one, you know, we ran on eight processes
We got a little bit more than four times as efficient four times the speed of now. What about it was exactly four?
All right, so that would be four divided by eight. That's only 50% efficient. Now. It's good that it's at least kind of like this line
But it's slow is really low. It's not it's not keeping up with the ideal speed up. Where are the ideal speed of the
Yeah, the ideal speed up line could be here. I should add that to my script here, too
So that running on two should be two times faster running on four should be four times faster. So the ideal speed up
Is up here. Now notice these things aren't keeping up with that. They're good bit lower. Does that kind of make sense?
All right, what about the the efficiency here so
Again which one appears to have the best efficiency the one that has the most work to do you see that
Now let's see
Let's run this again
Wonder if we can make this anymore
Is that I don't know if that's going to overflow the bounds of the thing?
So it's not notice how it slows down right here
You see how that and then it gets faster and it slows down. That's because as the end gets larger
It's taking longer to run my program at the very beginning
It's on the early iterations of that in loop and at the end it's it's taking a little bit longer here
So let's see if we get anything. That's the more we've
We've increased the amount of work that had to be done by a factor of ten
Right. So that means there's more work that has to be done
Which means it should benefit from this parallelism even more than the previous one
I ran because there was more work that could be divided, right? That was the idea
So let's watch this thing happen and see what happens if we come over here and say we look at H top here
You know, we can see that like
You know, it's going remember. It's going one two three four five six seven nine ten eleven twelve one two three four five six seven
Eight nine twelve so you can see it kind of you know
We don't have a sample rate here high enough
But you can see that like the first few cores are always engaged
These other ones only only if it's the fact that they're up to that number of cores that are being they're being handled there
So come back over here. We get this we look back into our
Timing
Now look at that. That's a lot smoother. That's another thing you're going to notice is that
Little small perturbations change the timing a lot like me moving my mouse around me looking at H top
That that causes it to take different amounts of time when it's running because I'm using my computer
But if you if the time of your program starts going even higher those small perturbations and timing of me messing with my computer
Don't influence the answer very much, right? Now, what would you really want to do in real life?
If you were going to measure this for every value of NMP here like for every
Work problem signs in and number of processes P
You might want to do a hundred of those and take the average of it
So that you get kind of the law large numbers so that these little perturbations that if if the time is really small
You have to do that kind of thing because those small perturbations mess mess up your stuff
You know you run at one time it might be faster
You run up the next time a little bit slower
You look at what the average amount of time is this that now this program that I wrote here
it only does one experiment for the data point, but you could say hey now do a hundred experiments for every data point and
Plot the average along with the standard deviations on top of this thing
We could look and see like how standard deviation changes as a function of the NP and the time look at that
What about the speed up now see now this is starting to look a little bit better because look at this
Two two processes two times faster four processes
This one is getting closer to four remember before this was way down here, but for this this really large size down here
It's getting it's going up and then of course for the one that was the smallest
It still has kind of this this issue here
And what about for the efficiency?
now
Even as our processes go up. We're not we're not staying you know at
At a hundred percent here, but we're staying closer to it up there. You know so does that make sense?
Now if you look at the syllabus for this course
Siminac about old load there's a team project. There's also some assignments and
Let's see if we go down all the way to the end here
Remember where it is in here, but one of the things that maps to this course is
Communication skills verbally and and in writing okay, so there's going to be reports in here, and we're not going to do presentations
In front of the class we're going to do one of these things where you record yourself
You know, but they're still going to have to be like you talking your way through logically through everything that's kind of going on
So how many of you have used LaTeX before to write reports?
So that's the that's what we're going to be using in here to write reports
So let's talk about that really quickly because I'm going to make a new assignment
You know that's based on this first one so kind of like the same thing that we've just done here
You know it should be an easy aid for you guys because we did it here. I'm going to give you the code
ask for a couple of things to be changed with it, but then I want to see like a
Presentation about this I want to see a report about this all in the style that we're doing now later
We'll be doing parallel programs that are like you're we're doing it from scratch and they're more complicated
But I don't want you to be hit with the reports and the presentations at the same time as that technical stuff
I want us to get used to doing our reports and used to doing our presentations this way
Along and along for every assignment that we do okay, so
If you if you've got low tech on your own on your own computer system
That's great. If you've got it on your own laptop, and you can do it on there
I mean, that's what I do, but if you don't then I would suggest that you use a
Overleaf
so you should create yourself a
Account overleaf comm and if you use your student email address like with a dot edu
I mean, I think it's free
I mean, it's probably free anyway, but like I think they have some kind of deal where if it's a dot edu addresses
Maybe you can collaborate with more people or something
You know
I don't know like there's a kind of a limit if you don't pay for it to the number of people that can
Collaborate in a single project, but these first few reports and presentations you're doing they're all individual the group thing won't happen
But except for that group assignment at the end, but all the assignments are all individual so individual reports individual presentations
so
Let's go back over here. Let's go to Moodle and
Let's check on something here so 473
import up files
And we had this fourth 73 dot zip. Let me look to see what was in that thing
Hey, at least the internet's working today
Positive about that
It is yeah, it's a good thing
So my feeling is this is it fault can't have everything in it that I'm looking for
It doesn't okay, so right you have you needed to have a CI login right for Coastal
I had asked you to make sure you had that so if you go to CI
If you got you go to code dot Coastal dot edu
And we sign in
Apparently not. Thanks. I'm gonna get my password manager out here. See if I remember what it is here
The code that coastal that you the same as the same password as it is for CI coastal dot edu. All right
Let's see. This is called
CI coastal why is it that I'm not typing it correctly ah
That's one different than what I was typing okay
So not now let me see W Jones
All right, so I logged in
And if you get in there, I think if we look over here because I have a links directory
No, but I'll provide it
So if you go to
Code dot coastal dot edu and you go to W Jones dash get repo
You'll have read access to this stuff. You can you can clone this repo or whatever you bring it down
So in there, what are we gonna see in there?
We're gonna see the classes that teach
210 310 473 207 and then this report this thing called LaTeX here, okay
And if we go into LaTeX
We go to into example
You'll see that there is a zip file in there called that's some general paper for class
Now how many of you have had a class before where we use this thing?
All right, so it's I'm just giving everybody an example where to start from that's that's what this is
So let's go ahead and download the file
Come over here
Open up the zip file. We'll see a bunch of a bunch of stuff in here
Okay, and the stuff that's in here LaTeX documents and style files and examples of how to do some stuff
I just want to bring us bring us over here into Overleaf
So we go back into Overleaf over here
I want to create a new project and I'm going to upload a project from this file
And again, if you already know everything about how to use it, LaTeX and all that that's fine
But it needs to use the style that this is so the IEEE
Style that I'm dealing with here. Now if you can do that your own way or whatever like you don't need to use this
But I'm just kind of showing you kind of what it's supposed to look like. So we're select a zip file
I'm gonna
Select this it's gonna upload it
And then it's gonna unzip it into a thing that we can edit and create our PDF right in here inside the inside of the web page
Theoretically that's not seem to do it is it?
Okay, so we're doing all right over there
There we go. Okay, so it finally loaded it up
Okay. Yes, I've got it. Thank you
So
If you look around in here, you've got some files that you can play with
The way this program this thing has been designed is is that there's this file that's called main dot tech
And in here, you know
You load up all the packages you plan to use that will help you so that does the right kind of this formatting and everything
That's correct. And then eventually down in here. You've got the you've got like the title of it
Go down here a little bit further. It's got the author information and then finally you begin your doc
You know the the document begins you include your abstract you include like the introduction whatever
These are the main things and basically these are just include so they don't have all the tech in this in this one file
Like that that means that I want to include like that's like saying pound include intro tech pound include related tech
And those are these files over here. So intro tech design conclusions abstract and all that sort of stuff
that's what this thing says to do then it says go ahead throw in a bibliography for all the things that we reference and
If you look over here
There's a reference dot bibliography file so you can put your references in there in the right format
So that then when you turn around and you know, like for example, let's this this thing was called exploring trade-off, but um
let's say here we came up here and we change this a little bit like so we're call it on my
NPI example
We go over here and we hit recompile
And you know, you can see the the changes over there
Then when you're done, you know, like you'll do two things when you upload this stuff to your answers
You'll want to have the PDF
That's compiled. It's got your report in it
But I also want the entire project downloaded and zipped up and submitted in the Moodle 2
So that if I want to recompile it I can
You don't you see what I'm saying?
So like I could have a program that would unzip recompile your stuff and look at it myself on my own computer
So, how do you do that?
You can come right over here to this menu
You say I want to download everything and this will download it that whatever state it's in
It's got all your stuff in it. You're ready to download it. You'll click that button
it'll download it and
You can submit both the PDF and the zip file separately from each other so that you know, both of them are there
Does that make sense? And I need these I need these things to
To to be well thought out written. I need you to have a problem with that chat GPT, right?
You use it to help write your paper. Okay, but I
Want to make I want it to look good. I wanted to have all the right pieces and parts in it
So I wanted to be something like this, you know
Let's say it's for this thing we're talking about right now might be like
Introductory evaluation of MPI program performance for trapezoid based integration
You know abstract, you know this paper we're going to lay out the problem, which was a
Numerical version of integration for one-dimensional problem using the trapezoid method that was originally written in C is a sequential program
It was then converted into an MPI program to leverage, you know, inter-processed communications for distributed shared memory machines
We're going to provide the problem description and development of the code the processes to think took place you blah blah blah blah
And we will show that we obtained results that showed that primarily
as
The problem size gets larger
So does the things like speed up and blah blah blah and we have better efficiency yada yada yada
And then you start your introduction here and you're going to be telling me what that you're going to talk about. What is integration?
What is numerical integration? You didn't talk about what trapezoids are you're gonna have pictures and figures of
Trapezoidal integration in here. It's gonna look good. It's gonna have captions that look right in your figures
Your figures are not going to be ridiculously big. So it takes up two columns
You're not gonna be ridiculously small so that you can't see them. It's going to look professional
When like this paper here, this is a professional looking paper
So when you think you said, what do you think looks good?
This looks good
Okay, I got about ten other words
I can provide you to give you an example of saying this is what something good looks like
And I want you to model it after it. They may say what Jesus like but the only thing I did this program was
I mean, I just I just took their code and I modified three things. That's all I did
Okay, that may be all you did but you're gonna write up a complete report as if we were doing this thing from scratch
You're explaining the entire thing. It's a complete report. That makes sense
Then you're gonna have you know
Some pseudocode segments you're gonna have sexy. Are you going to take screenshots of code and stick it in here? No
You're gonna use a LaTeX pseudocode package to type up the pseudocode so that it looks good in this thing
All right, then you're gonna get to experimentation and you're gonna have a table that says, you know
I tried it on all these different combination number of processes number of
different problem sizes blah blah blah
As we can see in figure blah blah we can see the timing of it in figure blah blah
We see the speed up and figure blah blah. We see the
efficiency
The observations we make is that you know for this and that I noticed that this happens else
But I know it over here this other thing happened the best performance we got was right here
But now on the computer when I ran it on my laptop
And I've only got four four cores as you can see in this graph blah blah blah blah blah I get this behavior
But when I ran it on expanse
On expanse I you know, it's got more cores. It's so I was able to get bigger speed ups blah blah blah
Now what is expanse? Oh, by the way, what are the parameters of my own computer?
My own computer has this processor this amount of cash this many cores
Expanse has this type of compute node this type of processor this amount of cores
Here's the memory that everything has got charts that say that if somebody wanted to replicate my experiment
They could buy the hardware that I have they could have the software that I use they could repos replicate 100% my experiment
Because the scientific paper means that you should be able to replicate someone's thing. There's enough detail
That they could replicate the entire thing they could buy a computer
They could install the correct version of Python correct version of MPI
Whatever it is that stuff's in there
They could do all of this and they could run your exact code and you might say well my code is not gonna be in
The paper that's true, but you can say it's in my attachments over here
You know and the code will be in your attachments
It's gonna be the zip file when you upload all your stuff into the thing does everybody get the get the sense of what I'm talking about
Here, that's the kind of paper. I'm talking about
So if you if you ever ask is like if Dan if the question is it okay just to do
But it's probably not the answer is err on the side of too much. All right, we're not trying to cut corners
We're trying to lay the foundation that anybody who looked at this
All right, not knowing anything to begin with more or less other than like, you know
You don't have to explain what integration is, but you might want to have an integral in there
Like let's assume they know what integration is, but they don't know anything about parallel computing
They don't know anything about API. They don't know anything about shared memory distributed memory all this
They want assume that whoever's reading this they want to see cool figures. They want to see cool diagrams
They do not want to read a bunch of words without pictures. They are a visual person, okay
They want to have words that back up those visual things, but they want to be able to add a glance
Understand what the entire scope of this whole thing is looking at pictures. Can you use pictures that were from the internet? Sure
But like don't have them if they're a picture that was originally this big
But a lot of detail and you shrink it down to fit in one of these columns and I can't see anything
No, okay, and what do we mean by see anything? Well, you could see anything if you just zoom in far enough, that's true
but
when you go to a PDF document and you go into that PDF document you say I want to view this thing at a zoom angle of
100% I
Want to look at it. It's an actual size that when you tell acrobat that acrobat knows
How many pixels your screen is it knows how many pixels per square inch that there is?
So it's able to put the PDF up here in approximately the same size. It would be if it was printed
to size
Okay, approximately. So if you can't read it at a standard
100% zoom factor not zoomed in but then you can't read it if you were going to print it out either
So that's gonna be the thing. I don't want to have to be like well, I could see their thing
But only if I you know, I could see their their thing if I if I zoom in like this then I can see the figure
Yeah, I can see all the little detail that no that's not gonna be okay
So you better have figures that are appropriate that have font sizes that are appropriate that are readable at a hundred percent zoom factor
The right level of genericism for whatever it is
This is being tried to describe if you need more detail about one component of that figure
Then put a general block diagram for the worst first one and then have another one that says now
We're just looking at this little block boom have another block over there for that. Do you see what I'm saying?
So this is the caps on class
communication
All right, then
presentation
The presentation I'm going to provide some parameters like I
Need it to be something that you've done in PowerPoint
So that when you record it, you know, you do a recording work like where you're you're talking
Right and you're and you're saying as we can see here and here and here and you're doing stuff and you're uploading that entire thing
And it's gonna be minimum five minutes maximum seven minutes. You have to at least talk five minutes about the thing and you got to have it
flow
Like whatever you just wrote in that paper. I want to have to be covered in a five-minute presentation
All right up to seven minutes. So nothing shorter nothing longer
All right, it needs to look good
It needs to be zoomed in needs to be so that like if we were playing it in here
You were explaining it to somebody like it would be at the same size
Like as if you were walking around talking up here, but you're gonna be recording it at your own computer
Does that does that make sense? And we're gonna have that for every single homework assignment that we have report
Presentation report presentation now some
Reports will be based on modifications of previous reports
So I'm not saying that every assignment is literally going to be a brand new report
But I'm saying like if we took this thing and then we added some more stuff to it
Then we're going to keep what we had and then add the additional sections like let's say we took this thing and we wrote it
With p-threads instead of MPI. Well now there's gonna be an MPI section. There's gonna be a p-thread section
There's gonna be MPI results. There's gonna be a p-thread results
So we'll just keep adding and making it bigger and bigger in more detail. Does that make sense questions?
Yes, sir
No, so I don't need your camera
I don't need a picture of you or double like if you ever recorded something in PowerPoint, like just a voiceover. Yeah
Yeah, that's what I mean. I mean like do the thing where you say I'm gonna record and it voiceovers even every slide
Now that I want that at a minimum
But now if you're like not see now the thing is like I got this other technology I prefer using
You know, so it's going to make this 500 megabyte file
Movie or whatever you download that that that that's okay, too
Alright, but I need to at least have the voiceover in slides
But if you like, for example, when you do that voiceover in PowerPoint, you can't move the cursor around and point at stuff
You can't go to the command line and run stuff
Now do I want you in the middle of a presentation going in command lining and running stuff?
No, because that's not how you present this thing. Probably if you were trying to present to an audience
You might have that at the end. All right, you might be like, all right, cool. Now we finished presentation
Let me just show you let me just demo my thing
So if you want to do some of those things, I think that would be good
But at the bare minimum voiceover PPT, okay
Other questions
You got a question? No questions
Alright
so
And I'll make a note to myself I'll send you the get repo link as well as the
These two files so that you have them you can look at it if you're interested
But literally I just I just gave it my
Program and I just said I want to conduct an experiment like this has these parameters make it for me
And you know and it did it and I
Want all this stuff that's in here to be in Python by the way
I don't want it to be something else and the reason I say that is let's say you did it in C-sharp
I don't have that on my laptop. I want to be able to replicate everything
So you're gonna have your MPI program being in C and you're gonna have your other mess
Whatever that other mess is is in going to be in Python and if I need to load up specific stuff
I need to have a YAML file or some kind of thing or requirements file that tells me exactly
What I got to do in Condit to load the thing up. Does that make sense?
But what are the dependencies in other words?
Because as a part of this, I'm going to be looking at your report. I'm gonna watch your presentation
I'm gonna look briefly at the code and I'm gonna run it
That's what I'm gonna do. I'm gonna run this stuff and we'll see what happens
All right
And I'm probably gonna wind up having a naming convention that I require so that I can run all your programs
Automatically because I'll know what the path is
I'm gonna run it and do a meta analysis of the entire thing to say all right
Did these people do this stuff or not? Did they meet the specifications or not?
And this will be due
Monday night next week
Okay, this is when this is going to be due. So one week from yesterday
But think about it. There's no more technical stuff really here. I mean
Which is a change a couple of things about these programs, but you've got that
The rest of it is getting familiar with all that other stuff and writing a report and doing that
All right classes
Slides
Briefly here, let's see
So we talked about the reduction sums
about broadcasting
And already do so that everybody
Everybody hasn't
An answer now this slide is kind of interesting. I wouldn't say it's very interesting
But it's a little bit interesting when they do in the all reduce here
they're saying this is equivalent to an all reduce because of the fact that
Everybody's got their personal sums. I'll do in a reduction down to the head node
So node zero, but after node zero has gotten that answer. I'm going to turn around and then broadcast that to everybody else
So like a reduce followed by a V cast is this is essentially an all reduce
however
The way all reduces actually written underneath the hood is it this takes like basically if you think about this time out of time
Being time T and this being roughly time T. This takes two T amount of time
The way the reductions actually done for an all reduce is so that it takes less than two T amount of time
It's because this is kind of the worst amount of time it can take right like at the same time that you're reducing this
Down here you could actually gear in other time steps. You could have that guy
Submitting, you know sending his to other people so that they all wind up having all of the combinations at the end rather than only
That would avoid having to do a broadcast even with the tree based algorithm bear at the very end
You know, so that would that would be a something that could be done like like this
You know, so when it's all said done
So like in this first time step the if you look at this even odd pair
So like even odd even odd, these are the ranks here. So they send it to each other
Send it to each other. They do their partial reduction sums here on theirs
But then in the next time frame instead of sending to this neighbor, that's one away. He sends the thing to the one that is
Three away
Alright, and you do it so that you keep sending it further and further away and the farther you send it you get every combination
So everybody actually adds up these numbers in different orders
But they all wind up having the same sum at the end
Now the difference is in this and this is that like in this one everyone's involved
But after this only these four are involved after this only these two are involved after that only ones involved
Whereas over here all eight are involved every time step
But but see if you think about the time steps essentially in this one these other processes are the ones that are not here
So like this guy
That guy that guy and that guy they're not doing anything in this time step
They might as well be doing something because they're waiting around doing nothing else, right?
So what this says is instead of having those guys sit idly by let them do a little bit of work and
Communication during those time periods so that this takes you know, one two three time steps here instead of one two, three
Four or five six
That's that's the idea
But we don't have to
Luckily, we don't have to write this from scratch to do this. We're using we're able to use the NPI
All reduce command because I can tell you that writing an algorithm that does this just using from MPI sends and receives is
Interesting to say the least to try to write that piece of code
We used to use that as an assignment that we would do in here and it's super confusing and it's it's nuts
And when you finally see the answer, it's very trivial looking
But you're like, how would I have ever come up with that myself?
And you're like you do wouldn't have and I wouldn't have either and I don't you know
I don't see there's a lot of objective to running it
The idea is that someone figured it out
Somebody can do it faster and that's why they encapsulated inside of an API that does that for you essentially. All right
The tree grace broadcast
So as we saw like they used to broadcast to get the information out to the other users
So after they got the stuff from the users, which you guys got from the command line, right?
They used to broadcast to get it back out. Let me ask you a question in you guys's code
Did you broadcast out a B and N to everybody?
Tell me why not
So I got let's say I got three processes zero one and two
And when you start this thing you did an MPI run blah blah blah blah dot slash
And then you said I want to integrate from zero to two and I want this to be a hundred thousand
Why didn't after so who is the guy who who got this? What did all of them get this?
Did process zero get it who got it? They all got it. They all got it
So they all got it from the very get-go. They didn't need to be sent the information. Didn't they?
And where was the thing they got it from? That was the you know, the AR
GV array
All right, so they got and by the way, what is the argc for this scenario right here?
So argc is how many arguments and how many arguments are there here?
Four the program name and then these three, right?
Okay, excellent
Now eventually they get over here and they start talking about
Other types of algorithms that we could parallelize like matrix vector multiplication
So that's the first one we're going to talk about here
now what was the problem with this is not saying it's problems not really the right word the
The stupid little integration example only had one that nested forward. So it was order in it doesn't take a long time
Anyway, that's how we had to make in gigantic to even take any amount of time
Well, now what about matrix vector multiplication? What order complexity is that he might know?
Did they discuss matrix multiplication in 220?
No
Well, let's just do it really quickly. Let's suppose. This is our matrix a and we're going to multiply it by
Vector x and we're going to get some sort of equation or some sort of answer y
So let's say our matrix was 1 2 3 4
multiplied by
5 6 and we're trying to get some sort of output answer here. Now remember matrix dimensions have to be compatible
So if this thing is
m by n this has to be n by 1 and this thing over here is going to be
m by 1 because the inner dimensions have to match here and
The outer matrix over here is going to have the number of rows of the first guy
It's going to have the number of columns of the second guy. That's the way matrix multiplication works, right?
So like that answer right there
So that answer right there. I was put a little dot
What are those things equal to well that thought is this row multiplied by that column, right?
So it's the inner product here. So it's this times this plus this times this
Alright, so that's 1 times 5 plus 2 times 6 and what about this element?
That's this times this plus this times this correct
All right, so that's 3 times 5 plus 4 times 6
But when it's all said and done, this is a single number and this is a single number
So this is a 2 by 2. This is a 2 by 1 and this is equal to a 2 by
So 2 rows 2 columns 2 rows 1 column 2 rows 1 column. This is compatible
And that's the output answers dimensionality, which is is that are we good with that?
Now imagine the end is really big or m is really big. Let's imagine they're both really big and for the moment
Let's assume you have an inner the same thing. Let's just assume
In is equal to n. So let's just say that this is n by n by n by 1 and this is in by
What kind of loop structure is it going to take to do this to compute this element? What have you got to do?
You got to take every column in this and multiply it with every row at this one right here, right?
So that's going to hop and how how much is that going to take?
Well, if this is in life and this is in long then there's going to be in steps to get that
So that's going to be order in times
But how many of these do you have to do you have to do order in?
To compute this how many of these are there? They're also in and those so they'll be in of these
This is going to be able to order in square
Okay, and if m and n aren't the same value then that just turns out to be order m times n
All right, but it's but normally like for example
What would be a weird case a weird case would be this is 1 by n that's n by 1
Well, I mean you see got a vector times vector, you know
You got a matrix times a vector or you have a matrix times a matrix too
You know so like depending on what it is we're dealing with here
We're assuming that we're talking about roughly square looking things because that's how it normally works out
You don't normally have a crap ton of rows and only one column or vice versa
So that means that like the the previous problem that we did if we look at the amount of time it took
For a different problem size in our previous one grew linearly because it was order in but this problem grows quite quadratically, right?
Like it's it's it's growing quadratically because the fact that it it's more complicated is doing more math stuff
There's a doubly nested for loop instead of a singly nested for loop
So as such it's an interesting problem to try to parallelize because it's more complex
Any questions about that?
Okay, so
Let's look at a piece of pseudocode for that
That's the same thing we just said which was
you take
The ith row of this and multiply it by and find the inner product with that vector and that gives you the ith element of this
But let me ask you this question
I'm gonna do it with different colors here. Okay
What data is required to calculate that element?
You need this and you need that
To make that don't you
Now when you're doing that couldn't you be calculating this at the same time?
Because what does that require?
That one requires this data
and this data
To get this data
So literally you could be taking every row of this and multiplying it by this vector at the same time
Because none of these things depend on each other. Do you see that?
Like every element of this can be computed
Independently, so
If we were thinking about trying to divide this problem up
Into pieces you remember that before what you think about just remind you what did we do before we had a thing where what?
We divided was
We had some function f of x
We wanted to integrate from here to here
so we broke this up into pieces and that was like taking the single for loop and
Breaking the single for loop up into pieces right have each person do its own piece
But what you could do over here is this is the simplest example is we say, okay
We're gonna divide it up like this right here
Process zero will be taking this row and multiplying by this column to get this answer at the same time
that
Process one is multiplying this row by this column
To get this answer that can be happening at the same time. Okay?
So now typically then you're gonna have a doubling s at for loop to do this. You're gonna have like four
Every row in this and then four every cop, you know every
Column in that I'm gonna have to do some arithmetic
So the loop that you could divide up could be the outer loop or it could be the inner loop
You could break up this inner loop into pieces. You can break up this outer loop of the pieces now
You're gonna see later by the time you do this course while this is the case
But for the time being the rule of thumb is if you're gonna divide up a loop the loop
You want to divide up is the outer loop about the inner loop, okay?
Let's just leave it like that. So when we go and look at this the pseudocode for this thing
We look at this
We're gonna want to divide up that loop
so instead of
Remember this would be in rows by in columns in general
I'm gonna have each process. So process zero will do this half of the M rows
This process will do this half of the M rows
So you're gonna have one of them go from zero to about half of M
And the other one to go from half of them up to the end of the loop. Does that make sense?
Now each one of those though. So like up here this half is going to be
traversing down those columns of a
and
multiplying it by that
column of
Of X and adding it up
So one element times the other element plus this times this plus this times this adding it up to and sticking the answer
Right back in here and having it take that product back times that plus that time that stick it here
While the other guy is doing this times this plus this time this is even to that. Do you see that?
Now there's a couple of reasons why this works out, okay one is
Only one process is writing to this location at any one time. Think about this
Process zero is writing in to like so if there's only you know, this thing it would only go from zero zero to one because
You know, there would only be two rows
Process zero would be working on index zero here and process one would be indexing on one
So only two people are saying plus equal to a place
But those places they're doing the plus equal to are not the same place. So there's no race condition
Okay, because only because think about this now when you talk about race condition
Is it okay for two things to be reading the same data at the same time?
Sure, because that doesn't change the state of the data, right?
I have a race of like, you know, will could be reading a value out of this memory location the same time
I'm reading and it doesn't matter if he reads it first or if I read it first does it change what we read?
No, but if we're both writing to it
Now that's that's different. So writing to a thing is a problem
So anytime an equal sign and the sign mistake that's happening somewhere
That's where your problem could be but in this case the assignment is having two different places
This is being read like when you say this times this plus this times this that's reading this data
The only thing is getting written is this
And process 0 is doing that while process 1 is doing this and they don't overlap
So therefore there's no, you know, read modify write race condition
Okay
So here's the pseudo code for it
You know sure enough right this is order
m times n and if m happened to be n like it's a square matrix, this would be n squared, right?
So it's doing n squared multiplication
In square additions, right? So it's doing some guys doing some more stuff
Whereas the previous thing that we were doing I mean it did some stuff
It did a multiplication too because it was that it was x squared was our function. So it had to do a square
It had to do an addition
So it did some stuff, too
Hey now thing is in C
We all know that C stores arrays in row major order in memory and that even though it might be considered a multi-dimensional array
It's actually just a linear thing of numbers one after another in row major form
So we go ahead and convert this down in here. So we're gonna have now what they did in this implementation is kind of
There's not the way we're gonna wind up doing it eventually here, but they said because of this reason
They're like because this is the idea a two-dimensional array
But we're just going to use a one-dimensional array a to actually store this stuff
They've come along in here and said, okay
I'm gonna have a routine called matrix vector multiply and it's going to take a 1d array a 1d array and a 1d array
This is really so this is going to be just a vector. This is a vector, but this is actually, you know a matrix
It's a two-dimensional matrix. This looks like this but because it's not you know with rows
Columns, but because of the fact that it's saying actually it only has one index here
We're going to treat it like it's a one-dimensional array is what they're saying to do
And you've probably seen this before that when you try to index into a multi-dimensional array
you can treat it like a single dimensional array by taking the I and
Multiplying it by the width of the matrix and adding the row offset into it to calculate the two to one
You know two-dimensional to one dimensional dimensional ray in this scene, right? Like you probably you've seen that before right? How many have seen that?
I haven't seen that. Okay, let's do a quick example here
You've got a matrix a
Say it's like this. Let's say it has two rows. It has three columns
Now this is index 0 0 0 1 0 2
1 0
1 1
1 2
So this is a of 0 0 a of 0 1 a of 0 2 a of 0 like that that and that right
That's how we do it. So the I
I
Selects which row and the J selects which column. Okay
But what they're saying is that's not actually how it's stored in memory and see in memory
Is being stored like this?
This would be a a is a pointer to this location. So this would be a
0 0 this would be a 0 1 this would be a
0 2 a 1 0 a 1 1 a 1 2
Okay. Now, let's just suppose the numbers were like this
The numbers would be a
Now if someone said hey guys
In is equal to 2 for the number of roses thing has and in is equal to 3 is the number of columns it has
And I really want to access a
Ij
How do I actually get a Ij though if I can't have a double index if I can only have a single index?
How do I do that? That's what we're talking about
So what we're saying is you want to do this, but notice they don't they don't do that in their program here
They don't say a of Ij. They do just a of this crap here
So where did that formula come from that formula came from right here?
If you take a and you say of all right, and you say which row you're on which is I
times the width of that row in plus J
That gives you the right location. Now. Let's just prove it by example
What about if the element you wanted to access is this element right here, so you want to access a of one?
One, but you can't you have to do it using a single dimensional array indexing so that would really be this is I
This is J, and what is in three?
So come over here, so we say it is one times three plus one do you see that
So then we get that's equal to four
So if we come over here, and we think about a is only being a single-dimensional thing that this would be x a big zero
One two three four five here like this
Damn it. I'm like what the hell is going on. That's five isn't it? God almighty. I was like this ain't working out like something's wrong here
Okay, so
Shit, that's wrong, too
Okay, hold on here
Let's see now. I know damn well that the index thing is this zero one two
Three four five so I know the index that we're trying to get to is five
Because that's the element that we're trying to do down here
Yeah, I said one one
That's the problem. I'm like you something's wrong. It's only get to two here two coming down over here
So let's go back one times three plus two
That right some three plus two is five
Thanks, who's a Anthony?
Yeah, yeah when I looked at this I wrote down one one over here
It's seven one two that's the index I want to get to so that that's it's just mapping
The two-dimensional array index to a one-dimensional array index given that you know
That every time you jump down to another row
Like this row has three things in it this row has three things in it if it had more rows
That would be another three things another three things so every time you increase the row index
You're jumping down by three more so jump down by three more by three more by three more
And it's just jumping down through memory to grab the items does that make sense?
There's a reason why the person did this
And the truth of the matter is is that
There's nothing wrong with this I mean
Because in in reality in the computer that is the way it is
now that doesn't mean we couldn't have used a high-level construct that would have made it so that we actually would say a of
ij instead of a of
this thing
So we got two minutes left
So that's the sequential version
Coming over here and saying let me turn it into an MPI version. So we're going to have like
My chunk of a my chunk of x my chunk of y how many local rows?
I'm going to be doing the total number of columns because everybody's going to do that and then the local in over here
And you got some local variables and if we come over here
They have done a bunch of crazy stuff in here to get this answer
So they did an all-gather which is a collective communication that we haven't done
Okay, we skipped over that in these slides just right now
so
What I want us to do for homework is
This is not to turn in but this is just to look at I want you to look at
The part in the book that says what an all-gather is
so you'll notice they talk about a scatter and a gather and right now figure out what is an all gather and
How does that all gather actually grab these elements and get the data to the right place?
Assuming we're going to divide our matrices and vectors up like the way they're talking about it in this code
Just just on pencil paper
Just try to figure it out to start to make you look at it see with your eyes
You convinced that if you do it all gather that is in fact going to wind up with the right answer
In it in the wise in the Y in the Y vector
Okay, and you can go run it too. Like you can you go run if you look down at the command line here
There it is right there
There's the matrix vector multiplication
So you go look at it. It's right there. You can run it. You can see what happens
Try that out. See you back here. So be on the lookout for the new assignment for next Monday
Take a look at the Python program that I sent today
It turns generating automatically these graphs because you're going to want something like that for your record, right?
And then let me know if you have questions
Make sure you get an Overleaf account also
If you don't have one get one and see if you can follow the steps we had today and maybe change the author to your
Name just to prove that it that it worked, you know, so you guys have a great one