How's everybody doing today?
So we're looking at matrix vector multiplication last time and we were talking about trying
to look at it and see and understand how it works.
And so I made a, that up to chat to the team this morning, a set of programs to illustrate
a point in this directory called matrix.
And I've also put a copy of these programs that I created in Moodle for you to use.
And not necessarily to play with while we're in class because I want you to pay attention
to what's going on.
But I didn't want you to know all of this stuff I'm going to show you is in here, right,
for the files.
There it is right there.
So these are the files that we're talking about.
And so, you know, we're going to say that we want to do matrix vector multiplication.
We're going to use the stuff that the author provided for us.
How does it create, how does the author create the matrices?
Have you looked at it?
It asks the user to enter the sizes and in some cases actually ask it to enter all the
elements of the matrices and vectors so that it can then multiply it.
So I was like, look, in real life, where is the data typically coming from?
Is it coming from the user entering values into the matrix and keyboard?
It might be in something, but it's probably not, right?
It's not a scientific application.
Where is the data going to come from?
Database, a file, like data's going to come in, out of the file, stuff's going to happen,
it's going to get processed, and then the answers are going to be written out to a file.
So that's kind of the workflow.
So I wanted to create a workflow that had that sort of thing going on here.
So I've got a C program that makes a matrix, a C program that will print a matrix out,
a C program that will multiply the matrix and the vector together, and something that
will test that multiplication, time it, and all that sort of stuff that we did last time.
And then an MPI version of the thing that it does it, and then a thing that tests it out,
tests out the MPI code to look at and speed up some efficiencies and all that sort of stuff, okay?
But if you look at these things, and then when you get a chance to look at them,
they're like, they're far more complicated than the stuff that we did the other day.
And so I want to talk about each step.
Let's just talk about some of the stuff going on in these things, okay?
I'm going to go over the rough idea, but it's going to be on you to sit down and say, okay,
cool, I have to code.
Let me start digging through this to understand what it's got.
It's got some comments in there.
You use tools like chat gpt-cloud, whatever it is you want to use to investigate what this code does.
What's good about them?
What's bad about them?
Whatever it is, you know, when you look at it and use the code, you're like,
I have no idea what the hell that thing actually does.
Then ask the thing, what does this code do?
Okay?
Is that clear on that?
That's the idea.
I want you to use all that stuff.
I need you to use all that stuff so that you can understand,
in the end, everything is going on in these five or six programs.
This is going to be like the thing we're going to focus on now.
It's going to be like our test environment, you know, all right?
In other words, I'm not even asking for something to be built here.
This stuff's already built.
I just need us to work through to understand it, not to run it.
Know what all pieces and parts are.
That's what we're trying to do.
Before we even get any of that, let's just run this stuff and watch what happens.
All right?
So how many of you are familiar with make files?
All right.
So we're making use of a make file in here to do this compilation and stuff here.
So I probably don't want to use CC.
I probably want to use GCC as my compiler.
Using MPICC as my C compiler.
We're using the C99 standard for the C.
Now, the W all are the warnings we've been talking about, but this W extra,
those are additional warnings that are being enabled beyond the ones that are included in
all that help you, like, find things, at least from a static analysis, that the compiler can find
that could be problematic with respect to things like types not matching,
values not being initialized possibly depending on the order of operations doing execution,
like, stuff like that, things that might be an indication going, hey,
like, I'm, there could be a cornered case here that my code's not considering.
All right?
Use the optimization flag.
So, like, in C, you can do things like, you know, like,
capital O, the number two.
And that says, turn on level two of compiler optimizations.
Okay?
And you can read for GCC what each level of compiler optimizations do.
But what exactly are compiler optimizations?
They're things that hopefully will make the execute will run faster.
Now, I don't have any of them turned on here.
Because sometimes when you turn on some optimizations, there can be issues with later
trying to debug the code.
But we would want, in a production environment, we would definitely want things to be optimized.
And you will notice there's a big improvement to code execution when optimizations are turned on
when they're off.
And you may say, well, this is a parallel class.
Obviously, I want to turn on.
Yeah.
But, like, not right now.
Not we're in development and testing and stuff.
And later, we want to run all these tests again, make sure they ran with optimizations
turned on, right?
Because there are times when you turn on optimization and all of a sudden something
that you assumed was going to work.
It's like, well, when the compiler does optimization, it assumes you didn't make this mistake.
It didn't.
It didn't assume something.
And it compiled out.
And now the error's really happening, right?
Is that going to make sense?
These are the compile flags.
So when you're doing, when you're compiling the code, so it's going to use,
it's using this variable.
So it's saying when you compile it with these, the C standard, these warning flags,
and with these optimization flags, those are my compiling flags.
And you've got, like, the linking flags in the libraries that you want to use.
That's nothing here.
Extra stuff that you might need.
You know, these are the things that would need to be compiled up.
I've got, like, these sequential things.
So I need to compile this program, this program, and this program,
because I've got those three things.
So the things that make a matrix, print a matrix, and do matrix multiplication
the regular, normal way outside of MPI.
And then the sources that are related to MPI.
The reason this is in two different sections is because you need to use two different compilers
to be able to compile that code.
One is GCC.
The other one is MPICC.
So you've got to probably have that broken down in directories.
You've got to have your targets.
Eventually, you've got all your things saying, look, you know,
this is how I'm going to build Mate Matrix.
So I'm going to, you know, use my C compiler with the C compiler flags.
And I'm going to have an output file that's got the same name as this thing here.
And I've got to make my, if there are any of these flags, go ahead and pass them in.
That shows how to build all these things.
And the same thing for the MPI version of it.
So I'm going to use the MPI C compiler to do that with whatever MPI flags there might be.
There's additional ones.
Dash O to the output file name.
That is just the output file name with the same dash C ripped out of it.
Any kind of flags.
And then you've got a clean, of course.
Like, you know, normally you're doing make clean, make all this, that.
That's what all these other sections are.
So let's try this out.
So do make, and I didn't save that thing.
I don't want to use GCC.
I want to use GCC.
All right.
So make clean.
So when it can pop, that's interesting.
It didn't use, it didn't use, I need to go figure out what's going on with that in a second.
But let's, for the moment here, let's just go with it and try to run some stuff.
So if we're going to do like make matrix here, the parameters for it are,
you tell the number of rows you want the matrix to have, number of columns you want it to have.
And now I'm going to have it initialize all the variables in the matrix to like random values.
So those random values are uniformly distributed between a lower bound and an upper bound.
So you might say like between minus 10 to 10.
That means all my float point values will be in that range in there,
just so that we've got data that it's not always the same.
And dash O is whatever the output file.
Where do I want you to put this data that I just created?
So let's give it a shot here.
So let's say I want to have two rows.
I want to have three columns.
I want my lower bound, say, to be zero.
And I want my upper bound to be one.
So the numbers are going to be somewhere between zero and one.
And let's see.
And we have my output thing.
I'm going to call it a dot binary.
Now the extension doesn't matter.
That's just a thing for us to remember that this is a binary file.
Because that's something else.
These are not being written out as text files.
It's written out as like hard binary files.
So that's cool.
I did that.
We looked at the directory.
We've got this binary file.
Now let's look through some sanity chain.
Is the size of this file, the size it should be,
given that I made it the size I made it.
OK.
So it's got two rows and three columns.
This is what we got to think about.
So we got to think about every little detail.
This is so easy for this stuff to just go sideways.
We need to make sure that the, I wrote it to the file.
I guess it's there.
It's like, is it really there?
So this is a two by three matrix.
That means it should have six elements.
And I will tell you that I'm using double precision voting
point values to represent my numbers.
So this is the biggest thing.
But why am I doing that?
I'm doing that because a lot of scientific code uses double precision.
But also, I'll make these programs the slowest they could possibly be.
Because multiplying floating point numbers is longer in the computer
than multiplying the integers, for example.
So, and I need something to take a long time.
Because otherwise, if I don't take a long time, why would I want to parallelize it?
That's the idea.
So that means that there's six elements in the file.
Multiply it by now.
Doubles use eight bytes per number.
So we have like eight bytes per element.
All right.
Six times eight is 48 bytes.
Now, how many bytes are in this file?
This is eight bytes.
That is not 48 bytes.
What do you think is going on here?
Let's assume that I haven't made a mistake in changing.
He hasn't made a mistake.
Well, how could that be?
What's the deal?
Okay, what kind of headers might you have in here?
Okay, so like the number of rows and columns.
Now, here's the deal.
Let's suppose my matrix that it had written out as a text file.
Literally, I got the blah blah dot text.
It's got ASCII text in it.
And my thing look like this.
One, two, three, four, five, six.
That's literally what's in it.
Like one, two, three, character, turn four, five, six.
There it is.
But I need header information to tell me the number of rows and columns in a text file.
I could figure it out, couldn't I?
I mean, you might be smart for me to have it, but do I need it?
No, because I could be like,
how many tabs are there in here?
Okay, that's the number of columns.
How many rows are in here?
That's the number of rows done.
I know the damn dimensionality of the file.
But in a binary file, you have no idea.
If you've just got six elements in there, that could be this matrix.
It could be this matrix.
Those are all different matrices.
Because there's just one binary number in there.
There's no carriage return.
You don't know where the end of the rows are.
So you have to have some header information when you've got a binary file.
That's for damn sure, unless you're just assuming something, right?
So when you talk about the number of rows or number of columns that something has,
what data type comes to mind?
Do I need a floating point number for that?
No, because rows and columns are whole numbers.
So I might as well use the integers.
All right, so if I use the integer,
how many ends would I need?
Two of them.
One for the rows, one for the columns.
Okay, multiplied by, there's four bytes per integer.
Because on this computer,
like when you just say integer four bytes, that doesn't jack.
Because on your phone versus on your watch versus on the refrigerator processor versus
inside this thing, that's not guaranteed.
So integer is a data type that is like ill, ill specified.
Now, in real life, somewhere under the hood, it's not actually using it.
It's using some type of event that actually says how big the energy is for this computer type,
right?
That's that platform incompatibility issue that we have.
Let's see, because not every architecture is the same, right?
All right, so a so embedded processor that's in some sort of device
might not need very good integers.
So, so anyway, what do we got here?
Is this eight bytes?
Now, what is an eight plus?
This is what?
86.
And there it is right there.
That's what's going on.
Now, what about if I wanted to look in this file?
I can't just open it in VI can't open it in a text editor because it's not text.
Like what if I did that?
I just want to like make sure everything looks okay.
All right, here we go.
I'm going to open it in AI binary.
Okay, garbage, because the binary stuff, it's not text.
It's trying to interpret everything in the file as if it's an eight bit ASCII text,
and it's not.
So how do you look at a binary file?
We use some sort of binary editor, binary viewer.
So on most Linux machines, there's a word called hex dump.
It'll dump the file out and hex it as on format.
You can see what the individual bytes are in the box in hex.
Okay, so do a dot then
You might go, oh my God, what is all of this stuff?
God, what's this stuff?
There's all kinds of stuff here.
Well, the default parameters to hex dump.
And by the way, on Mac versus Linux, the default parameters to hex dump might not be the same.
Okay, so you got it like, it might print out different because they assume some other kind of thing.
And remember, this is an Apple silicon.
chip versus x86.
So the indianness is not the same on those two things.
Do you know what indianness is?
It's the byte order inside the computer memory.
Indian.
The indianness.
x86.
So Intel, AMD, all this historical stuff that is based on technology that came out before I was born.
It assumes little indian format.
But the arm and things like this stuff is sometimes big indian.
So these, when you ever look at the bytes in the order they appear in the file,
they won't be in the same order because the indianness.
All right.
So when we actually look at this thing, we, it's hard to know like what the hell is actually being
printed out here.
But let's, let's kind of look at it.
We said the integers were four bytes, right?
Now, this stuff over here, these are like addresses.
This is like the address of the file.
So this is like starting at the beginning of the file.
And then this one over here is like saying, okay,
a certain distance over the file, certain distance over the file.
We're not going to worry about it.
Remember how in 310, excuse me, 210, we would look at the hex viewers,
see what was in it and everything and all that.
We had addresses that were over the file.
So that's what this stuff is.
The data itself is this stuff right here.
That's that stuff right there.
And it starts with the top left and comes across here.
Now we made this and it's two by three.
Do you see two and three in there anywhere?
Yeah, right there.
There's two and three.
Now, these two and a threes were supposedly four bytes each.
Now, four bytes.
How many bits are there per hex character?
Only bits per hex character.
These are all hex characters.
How many bits is that?
Four, four, four, four.
So this is 16 bits, four, four, four, four, another 16 bits.
How many bits is it from here to here?
32 bits.
That's how big the integer is that represents the number of rows.
Then the next 32 bits.
That's the number of columns.
And you might say, why the hell is the two in the front?
And how on the other side?
Remember that Indian and stuff I was telling you about?
We don't even know what order it's turning it out in.
Like, which one is this is the least significant hex character?
It must be this one.
It must be like, if I had written out that 32 bits,
it must be that the order of the bytes are like this.
And it must be, I mean, I don't know, but it must be something like this.
If that is that number two, okay, and it's got eight of those things,
if it's really the number two, that's not the two,
this should be zero, zero, zero, zero, zero, zero, zero.
Why the hell is it not printed that way over there?
But it must be printing these four first and these four.
You see that?
So if we were to put these index positions,
zero, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, this is probably like this.
Zero, one, two, three.
The swoon shift.
Zero, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven.
So it must be doing something like that when it's printed out.
Part of that could be about the order of this thing printed.
The other part could be about Indian and stuff.
In general, can you kind of see it?
There's a two there, and there's a three over there.
If you wanted to really get down to it, you could go Wikipedia up.
Did he get in?
Why is it written this way?
He explained to me this exact thing.
All right.
Then, what is all this stuff?
Those are those six floating point numbers that range between zero and one.
Now, we can go through and prove that each one of those numbers
is actually the correct bit pattern for a particular 64-bit floating point number
if we were doing CSCI-3-10, which is the class where we normally talk about all that,
but we're not going to do that.
Okay.
So let's try to print it out.
All right.
So I've got a print matrix here, and it takes one input to follow our print.
Cool.
So print matrix, one input, eight-hot binary, and there it is.
There's the two-by-three.
So it had to read in that header information to know the right dimensionality
and then it printed it out, in other words, between zero and one.
We good on what these two programs do.
Okay.
Then, let's see what else we got in here.
We got do a matrix vector multiplication.
Let's see what it takes as input parameters.
It takes the first matrix A, multiplies it by matrix B, and puts the answer in matrix C.
And it reminds you, now, by the way, now, this isn't matrix-matrix multiplication.
It's matrix vector.
So you can choose any kind of dimension you want for the first matrix,
but the second matrix has to be n by 1.
Like, it has to be a column vector.
And the answer, as a result, will be a column vector.
Because remember, a vector is just a matrix.
It either has one or one column.
Whether it's a column vector or a row vector, right?
So our file format works for any matrix of any size,
but this multiplication routine only works for multiplying a matrix by a vector.
Or not even multiply a vector by a vector, too.
But the second thing, B, has to be just a vector.
That corresponds with the stuff that the author was doing in his code, right?
So let's, I just want to see it at work here.
So to have something, I got to have another matrix vector to multiply, right?
So I got to do, like, a make matrix.
And if that one's 2 by 3, this one's going to have to be 3 by 1 in order to make it
so that it'll be compatible for matrix multiplication, right?
So then you're on that.
Now, I don't know.
Maybe I want to print matrix, dash I, B.
Oh, shit.
I overrode it.
And that's a kind of good copy and paste error.
So 2 by 3, we'll call it A.
And then 3 by 1, we'll call it B.
We've got A and B here.
So let's see.
Print matrix, dash I, B.
So there's my column vector.
Cool.
Multiply that.
Let's see.
So A dot, dot, B dot, bin, and C dot, bin.
Okay.
Got some timing information in here.
We got some timing information that says, like, how long it took to read the data,
how long it took to compute the data, how long it took to write the data,
and finally what the size of the matrix issues I was dealing with
in the last time in seconds for all of this sort of stuff.
So that my Python program later can grab that and plot stuff.
If it's to grab it to look at what the, you know, the timing is, right?
I'll print that out.
So then also, let's see, if we print that out.
So print, let's see.
C dot that.
And we got this.
Two by one.
I mean, we probably should go and actually do this by hand
and make sure that they have to test the right answers.
You know, we got, like, trusting it.
I mean, I assume it's right.
But we don't know.
We should probably go test it.
Okay.
And so then we've got Python program.
And here's the thing.
I'm just showing you how to use it.
Don't remember looking at how it works.
All right.
I just wanted to be, you know, before you even talk about, like,
what it, how it works, and you can see what it does.
Okay.
So that was a test matrix multiplication, matrix vector multiplication.
And here's what it does.
It says, I'm going to run this.
And I'm going to start at a matrix size of n,
go into the final one by the increment, right?
So I want to go from matrices that originally started.
I assume those matrices are square, right?
So I'm only changing.
So I'm assuming I'm going to take an n by n multiplied by n by one matrix.
And I'm just going to say, what happens is I keep making my matrix bigger and bigger and bigger.
Figure out what's going on and figure out how long it takes.
How much time is spent doing IO, how much time is spent doing computation.
You get some sort of idea, right?
Like, that's normally what would happen, right?
You would, you would have a program you're running and you'd be like,
looking at the amount of time it took.
You'd be like, oh my God, this is getting really slow because of the big O of n squared.
So I need to parallelize it.
But when you parallelize something, you got to know,
well, how much room for improvement do you even have?
You got to have a baseline.
How fast was it when you didn't even write it in parallel?
So we're, this is just to measure that, right?
Right.
And so let's see what happens.
So you see, this is what we got in our directory right now.
So I'm going to Python this thing up.
And I'm going to start at matrices of a size 1,000, go to 10,000,
in units of a thousand.
Now I've got to do in the following.
You know how I said the other day that when everything's worked really fast,
you need to do lots and lots of evaluations and trials so that you get a good statistical average.
So one of the things that I have in here is that says, hey,
I want you, I want you to run every test that I do a number of times so that
every test runs for exactly two seconds, at least,
or up to five iterations, depending on whichever one's longer.
That way, we don't see these small perturbations on my standard deviation.
Remember, I told you last time, if you measure something that takes a little time,
then small changes make a big difference in the answer.
So I need to run it thousands of times, baby.
Well, I didn't do that in here.
I don't want to sit around for thousands of times.
But I said, run it enough times that I get a good answer,
in terms of the number of iterations that it takes to make it so that it kind of converges.
Now, I don't actually look for it to converge,
but we're going to plot out the standard deviation of it,
but we can see that it's pretty good, okay?
So like this thing said, you know,
if you start looking at the total number of experiments that had to be run,
it just kept it, it took different amounts of time.
The other thing is, this is kind of neat, too.
You know how I know the day we did the thing where we said,
if it was going to percentage, I was done?
Don't you guys hate it like when you're running something on the computer
and it says, percentage of it done,
and it's moving along, and then it just stops, or does it get slower?
And that percentage doesn't mean percentage of time.
It means percentage of maybe iterations, right, or something like that.
So I have this code also saying, hey,
keep a track of all the timing of all the previous experiments I did,
and fit that to a second-degree polynomial, all right,
using least squares regression,
and predict how long the next iteration is going to take,
and the sum of all the next iteration,
so that it keeps track with that,
assuming that it's predicting that n squared kind of term.
So I just threw it around and said, hey, I just want to see,
like, you know, don't tell me the percentage,
tell me the estimated time it's going to take to finish.
So it says, well, since I know that this thing's going to grow in a square,
then I can take a few timings,
fit that to a quadratic expression,
calculate low-efficiency,
and predict how long the next iteration will take.
Do you see what I'm saying?
And then you could sum that up for all the iterations
and say, that's an estimate approximately how long it's going to take.
Now, I play with it a bit.
It's like, well, the estimate's not actually real good.
It's kind of rough when you first start
because it didn't have a lot of data to go with it.
By the time you get to the end, it's like, hey, it's actually pretty accurate.
It's kind of like your GPS.
It says how long it's going to take you to get to your destination,
and in 10 seconds before you get to the destination,
it always says one minute, and it's totally correct at the end.
It's the beginning of it.
When you first start, it's not necessarily good.
So let's open this thing up and look inside this results directory.
This is what I've got.
You've got the raw data over in here.
So I've got all the trials, the summary of everything.
So let's take a look, for example, the overall amount of time
versus the problem size.
So it says, look, now we can kind of see that,
as my size gets bigger, the more time it takes.
And look at that.
It looks kind of like a parabola, doesn't it?
Now, how many of you in 2010, when you took 2010,
ran a program over and over and over again
to statistically figure out what its actual time order,
its empirical order complexity,
and see that that matches the reality
of the being a big O of N squared.
So did you do that?
Did you do that?
Well, I would argue that it isn't real until you run it.
It's just pencil and paper saying, I think this is the case.
So I would encourage you, any time you ever have an idea
of theoretically that this thing should take this long,
theoretically don't matter.
What matters is what it actually measures out to be.
Now, if you measure something out that's way different
than what you expected theoretically,
that might be like, oh my god,
I'm not actually doing the thing I did.
Like, what if I did this and my time went up
and it went down and I'm just getting a bigger matrix,
the less time it took.
Is that even believable?
No, because we know down low that the bigger the matrix is,
the more work it has to be doing.
So it kind of gives you some ideas.
The theory gives you an idea of what to expect.
But the reality is where it meets the road,
so to speak, on measuring something.
The reason this looks so smooth is that this is the average
of a bunch of times at different sizes, right?
So this wasn't run just one time at the size of 1,000.
It was run hundreds of times.
And we're looking at the average.
The reason why it's important is,
look at these damn numbers in seconds.
I mean, that's less than a tenth of a second way down here.
This is still in this range.
Like, if we weren't doing some averaging,
this thing would be like, I don't know, like this.
It would just be jacked up.
And it doesn't really matter how long it took to write at one time,
the same average how long it's going to take.
So that's why we're averaging that thing up.
So at least with the sanity perspective,
the amount of time it took to run this seems realistic,
because that looks kind of like some sort of n squared
with some coefficient in front of it, right?
You guys agreed?
Nobody's like saying anything like, you're doing any questions?
Does that make sense?
Like, when I say, does this make sense?
And you're like, I know.
But no, I have no idea what you're talking about.
I need to know that.
I mean, is it good?
Yes, sir.
Well, let's make sure we're talking about the same n squared here.
Do you mean like, what made me change square matrices?
What made me choose square matrices?
Well, I don't do that.
I just run it and increase the parameter
and see what it looks like.
So like, for example, if the problem size is n,
then I increase n, re-measure, get an answer.
And I look at that and I say, well, I know theoretically
that it's a doubly nested for loop that's n squared.
So I know it should have looked like a parabola, and it does.
So I feel good about it.
Is that what you mean?
Yeah, I was confused as to if that causes bias.
You mean like, because I expect the confirmation bias?
Yeah, it could.
But the main reason I'm doing that is that like,
if this thing isn't doing that,
it means I might need to think about it a little bit more.
If it's going down, it means I probably did my test wrong.
So a lot of what I do is I look at saying,
does what we do even make sense?
You know, like, for example, let's suppose that someone,
you know, you're drinking some water
and they stick a thermometer in it.
And it says, this water is at minus 10 degrees Celsius.
Does that seem realistic?
Standard temperature and pressure,
that regular H2O would be minus 10 degrees Celsius in liquid form.
Now, could there be some weird thing going on?
Okay, maybe there's a bunch of salt in it.
And it's colder than we really think.
Maybe my instrument is bad.
Maybe that ain't water.
Do you see what I'm saying?
Like, it's the same thing here.
You need to think about everything that you do
with this critical thing of,
does this even make sense?
Is this even plausible?
And I was like, you know,
how much does this car weigh?
And it's like, it weighs 10 ounces.
Is that even, does that seem realistic?
I mean, maybe it fits a little toy car,
but it's like, is it even within the realm of what I would expect?
What about if it had this shape,
but that axis over there, where it's hundreds of seconds?
Even for a small matrix,
would I, maybe I wouldn't have any idea, you know?
Maybe I would come over and run an applet on the internet
and make a hundred, a thousand by thousand matrix
and be like, oh my God, it's depending on the internet.
Less than one tenth of a second to run,
but my damn program is taking a thousand seconds to run.
Something's wrong.
You see what I'm saying?
That idea of like, what could even be right?
That's what I'm talking about.
That's what I'm trying to do.
I'm going to run these experiments.
And so just because things match up
don't mean that they're okay.
But if they are way off,
that means that they're probably not okay.
Or whatever I was expecting wasn't reasonable for me to expect
because something's happening in real life.
That I'm measuring that I didn't think about.
That's what it's about.
Now you use this like a lot of this is like a debugging things.
This is even doing like what I think.
I mean, you know what I mean?
Like after it runs and after it prints
and after it does whatever it does,
how do I know it actually did anything?
Well, you know, I need to look at the files it's creating.
I want to make sure all files don't ever get, you know,
they're being bigger and greater.
Shake their file sizes and make sure the file size
is matched to a particular amount.
You know, all this stuff to make sure that it's right.
Does that make sense?
Because otherwise, you're just running stuff
and closing your eyes and being like,
yeah, I guess it works because it didn't blow up.
We're way flat stuff not blowing up.
Blowing up is like icon, you know, 135 here.
Not blowing up is good enough.
Not blowing it out don't mean jack.
It doesn't mean anything
because you don't know anything about what it's doing.
Like now you're with the author's thing.
Okay, you knew what was doing,
but you typed in the numbers by hand
and it gave you the answer out.
But then you could the author's code
have been used to do this performance analysis.
Oh, okay.
So that's where we're coming from with this.
So let's look at some of our other stuff.
The compute time.
Now, this is the overall time.
That's the overall time it took to run my program,
including the time it took to read the stuff out of the file
to compute the product and to write this stuff.
And so does that mean that that time
is just the time it took to do the math?
No, it's the entire time it took to do the whole problem.
So what about if I just look at the compute time?
Okay, well it has the same shape.
What about if I look at it combined here?
And look at this here now.
This is the total time.
So that's another graph we already looked at.
But that total time is broken into these pieces.
We had to read the file in.
We had to then multiply the stuff together,
and then we had to write the answer out
and add it all this plus this plus this is this.
Okay.
Now, it might not look like it at first
because I was like, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
That plus that is bigger than that.
That's a point one.
This is like three points up, and this is four points up.
Okay, we'll put one plus that, and it adds up.
Okay, that's what's going on here.
So the multiply thing is certainly increasing
quadratically, but so is the read time.
Well, that makes sense because the matrix is bigger
and bigger and bigger.
It got read out of the file.
I'll tell you why we did this in a second.
The other thing is I plotted out a plus or minus
one standard deviation around the mean for the total time.
Look at this out here.
Once I got to a pretty big size thing, look at that.
You can't even, like, that means most of my numbers
are right there at the mean.
But down here, like, for here, when I did this
experimentation, there was a lot of fluctuation in here.
This one standard deviation, then you'd probably have,
like, two standard deviations.
There's fluctuations there.
That's the reason why we're doing this averaging
because otherwise, this shit would have been crazy
and that average wouldn't have even necessarily been
anything other than just, like, well, the middle
of a cloud of points.
It doesn't really mean anything.
But if you keep running it over and over and over again,
your standard deviation, this measurement will go down
as a function of basically run over the square root
of the number of trials that you do.
So if you want a specific amount, you just keep running
it enough to make that go away.
Or if you can't make it go away, that means there's
some sort of behavior under your computer
that's causing it to run at different amounts
that happen every time.
It's not this statistical aberration.
It's like a real thing that's causing it not to run.
Like, why don't you run at your size 4,000
and you ran it 100 times.
In 50 of them, you ran 0.1 seconds.
In 50 of them, it ran in 10 seconds.
Now I'm having a huge standard deviation.
And even it wouldn't matter how many times I ran it.
It was always 50 one-way, 50-way.
It would be a gigantic variance.
And you'd be like, well, now something's going on.
It's weird going on.
You know, it would tell you something.
So having this stuff so you can look at it
and give you some sort of confidence,
you'd be like, maybe I should have run these a little bit
more.
Maybe instead of choosing two seconds, I should have
shown some to say, run trials up the baby
for four or five seconds and do it.
I bet if I did that, this would come down.
I bet if I ran this again, this might not even
be in the same place as it was before
because there's different stuff going on on my computer.
All right.
Does this make sense?
Okay, so even at 10,000, it's still not taking very long
to run here.
The actual part we're going to parallelize,
the part that's a matrix-like figure of that doughiness
where we're going to parallelize that,
that's really only this part.
So nothing that we're going to do is going to help
this part right now, for right now.
Because this part, you have to read it or write it
no matter what.
So let's think about this term to animals all, all right?
Let's think about this.
I've gotten a special program.
I haven't run it in parallel yet.
I haven't paralyzed it.
I haven't run it in parallel.
I have no idea what to expect.
What's the best we can expect?
Well, let's try to figure that out.
Because like he mentioned,
I need to think about what I should expect to see
and then measure it to see if we get that.
Now, let's use some actual numbers here, okay?
I almost really, really look at this.
I don't want to just guess off looking at this plot here.
I want to look at it in the data file itself.
All right, so the total mean,
so the total amount of time that is spent
is 4.4 seconds, okay?
Excuse me, 0.44 seconds, right?
So 0.44 seconds.
But now of that, the mean time it took to do reading
was 0.1 seconds.
So this thing was 0.1 seconds doing some readings
to data out of the file.
Writing data to the file took,
I mean, damn, that's really small, isn't it?
I can't, I mean, that's orders of magnitude less than this.
Do I need to even really worry about that time it took to write it?
Now, what about the time it took to compute it?
Well, it's just going to be this minus this,
which is basically 0.34.
This is the multiplication, okay?
And I'm getting ready to parallelize this thing, all right?
So if I were to perfectly parallelize it,
like I literally took this
and I divided this work exactly in half
and made it so that one processor was doing this amount of work
at the same time that this guy was doing that amount of work.
But remember, the reading still has to happen.
And again, the writing had to happen too,
but it was so damn thin it would be like this.
You can't even see that in there.
This will still take 0.1 time.
How long will this take?
Well, this will take 0.34 over 2.
Now, what is 0.34 over 2 equal to?
17?
0.17?
This will take 0.17 amount of time.
Yeah, I perfectly parallelized it, okay?
Okay, cool.
So the overall time here then,
the time to run it on two processors
would be 0.1 plus 0.17, which is equal to 0.27, correct?
Do you agree?
All right, yes or no, do you agree?
You see what we're doing?
We're trying to predict how long it would take to run on two processors.
Assuming that, we have now profiled the original job
that we have figured out.
That original job spends 0.34 seconds of time
doing the part that we can work on.
We can only work on that WS and for loop.
And in a best case scenario, we make it twice as fast.
This one particular part, do you agree with that?
That's like saying, you know, that we divide the work of evenly, right?
But it still has to be ran out of a file.
So that's now equal to 0.27.
Okay, so now what's the speed up on two?
Well, that's the time on one divided by the time on two.
So the time on one would be 0.44 and the time on two would be what?
0.27?
Do you agree with that?
That's somebody to tell me what would the speed up to be then?
What should that be?
Somebody tell me.
How much?
1.6.
Let's just say approximately.
Okay, so the efficiency on two would be the speed up on two divided by two,
which is 1.6 divided by two, which is what?
0.8?
That's 80% efficient?
Does that make sense?
Huh?
Okay, well, let's see if we parallelize and we get that.
I mean, that's one data point.
I can do the same thing when we say, okay, now we're going to divide it into four pieces.
Okay, so that's going to be this.
That's happening at the same time as that.
It's happening at the same time as that.
Now, that would be 0.34 divided by four would be the approximate size of this.
And you see that no matter what I do, even if I keep making this narrow and narrow,
that thing right there is still going to be a problem.
I'm never going to be able to make this thing any faster than a certain amount here, right?
Like, in fact, what is the maximum speed up I could get?
The speed up max.
Well, even if all of this computation were to go away,
I did it instantaneously fast.
It was so freaking fast it didn't even last any time.
This would still take 0.1 seconds.
So the speed up max would be equal to 0.44 divided by 0.1, which is 4.4 times faster.
Do you see that?
Did you believe that?
That ain't great.
That's like saying, if I had a thousand processors, I couldn't make it but four times as fast.
Okay, why does that happen?
Because animals all says that.
How much faster you can make it depends on the part that you can improve.
If you can't improve this, then the best you can do is make this go away,
and then your best improvement factor is that over the remaining part.
Does that make sense?
So let's go try to run it in parallel and see if we can see what we get.
I want us to see where we're going with all this,
and conceptually, before we start worrying about looking at the code.
That is not normally the way that I do this class.
I normally write a good looking at the code,
and so you don't even know what we're looking at.
Why we're doing what we're doing, if we don't do this first,
that's why I'm so different this time.
Now, this couldn't be worse to do it the other way.
But, basically, previous experience season is class, it can't be that much worse.
Because, you know, people should behave this up.
So, if this is anywhere equal to hate or less than hate,
then I'll feel like I did something good, I guess.
Okay? All right.
So, let's get back down here and run the other one.
So, I'm going to do MPI run dash MT2, okay?
And I'm going to run this as the MPI matrix vector to multiply,
and I want to see what the parameters are.
So, the parameters are I need to tell the number of processes,
and you run a program, and I need to give it that matrix A, B, and C.
Now, I'm going to choose a different seed this time,
so I've got my previous seed that was the answer when I ran it serially.
I'm going to save it as a different file name when I run it parallel, because a lot.
Why would I do that?
And make sure they give me the same answer.
See, like, if I write a parallel program,
but I don't get the same answer as I did with the special program,
what yours is to make how fast it is.
I could make that infinitely fast.
I could just slip a coin for every value of the file,
and I would be able to do it infinitely fast,
but it would just be totally wrong, you know what I mean?
Like, if you want something to be fast, you can just say,
well, let's just assume all the answers are zero,
and we're done real quickly.
It's just, and it's only about 50% wrong,
because every other bit is correct on average.
If you assume, you know, uniform random entropy in the file, right,
you'd be 50% correct by most bits.
All right, so let's try this out.
So, we do A.bin, B.bin, and C.bin.parallel.
So, I'm going to save it like I would give a parallel answer and come out there.
Okay, so I got some information.
You know, it didn't take very long at all,
but the damn thing's as small as two by three, all right?
Now, let's do an LS here.
So, there's the C.parallel, it's 24 bytes,
and there's the C.bin, which was the sequential version,
and it's 24 bytes.
So, at least the file sizes match the size,
because if that wasn't the case, I don't even need to look at it.
I know something's wrong if those don't match.
Now, what is the command line utility in Linux
that I can use to compare two files to each other to determine if they're different?
Who knows?
It's the program called diff for different.
So, I'm going to compare file C to file C.parallel,
and if it doesn't say anything, that means they are identical.
That means that every, literally every byte in one file is exactly identical to the other file.
Now, if you wrote this program on a text file,
it will actually tell you what text is different,
but if you run it on a binary file, it will be just like,
these are different, I'm not going to tell you what they're different,
because there's all kinds of shit ton of things that are different,
because if one thing is off, everything's going to be off, right?
But I can just tell you they're different.
So, it'll normally come up here and say, it's different or not.
Like, for example, if I diff A.binary with B.binary,
it's like, look, they're different, for sure.
If you wanted to know exactly where they're different,
you'd have run some other kind of program or hex editor or something like that,
you could look at the files.
Does that make sense?
Okay.
So, I feel pretty good that when I ran it in parallel,
I at least got the same answer I did before, right?
Okay.
So, let's try something here.
Now, I want to see if I could have run this, but only on one processor.
Like, is the code written in a way that will actually work
if I only ask for it to be run sequentially?
Let's run the diff again.
So, it seemed to produce that.
Now, maybe that's because it didn't actually write my file out,
and that was the same file I had before.
Let's remove it.
Let's have it regenerated.
Let's diff it.
Now, I don't know for certain, it just got reproduced because I deleted it.
So, I feel pretty good that my program runs for one process.
Because, see, sometimes you can write parallel programs that will work
for other numbers of the processes, but won't work for one.
Like, remember that Hello World program that we had?
Or the one that said, one guy was going to send it to another guy?
Well, if you only ask it to run with no guys, there's nobody to send it to.
There's nobody to receive, you know what I mean?
It has to be written in a way that it will work for one process also.
The reason why that's important to me is the following.
I'm going to use the time it takes to run on one process to be T1.
Right?
So, I'm running the NPI version of this program,
but with one process to get the sequential time.
And then I'm going to compare it to everybody else.
Yes, sir.
So, did it again?
Oh, did it?
Jim, did the same thing again.
Well, it did have been different.
I was like, all right, yes.
Let's call it for today.
Yeah, thank you.
Like, yeah.
All right.
So, I did the same thing.
I wrote a Python program using chat GPT to say, hey, I want to test this thing out.
A bunch of different process number of processes and a bunch of different
problem sizes, just like we did the other day.
So, I'm going to sweep from small problem size to fixed problem size.
And for each one of those problem sizes, I'm going to test it on one core,
two cores, three cores, four cores, up to 12 cores, because that's what my computer does.
Okay?
And then I'm going to have it generate our plots.
I'm going to have it generate the seed up, the efficiencies, all these plots.
We can look at it and see what we get.
And then we can see if when it's equal to two, if we even get anywhere near what this was.
Now, that might not be a fair comparison,
because this is actually a different program than the sequential program, right?
But let's see.
Okay.
Let's see.
So, Python.
And then this is a test NMPI, matrix, whatever.
Now, let's see what the interface for this is.
It says, I need to tell it the smallest starting size, the largest problem size I want to do,
and how much I want to increment that variable in and that loop by.
So that when it says, like, you know, N plus equals,
N plus equals whatever this increment is, right?
For that double, that outer, that's the for loop.
And then on the inner nested for loop, it's looping over the size of the number of processes.
So I can have it starting at, say, one, going to 12 in increments of one.
If I wanted one for every combination.
And I do.
That's what I want.
So, I want to go from 1,000 to 10,000 in increments of 1,000.
And I want to go from 1 core to 12 cores, 1 core at a time.
So, it's making it bigger and bigger matrices.
You see it slowing down now because the matrices are getting bigger.
And you shouldn't be getting this feeling.
Look at the numbers are coming up.
The support of this thing ain't going.
This thing's not going to seem to be going very well.
All right.
Now, the last time we ran this thing, the data we were looking at, we were looking at sequentially,
we were looking at problem sizes that were size 10,000.
So, let's compare apples to apples.
Let's only look at things that were size 10,000 with this new thing.
So, we're going to go here to my MPR results folder.
I'm going to go ahead and look at the overall time that it took to run it
versus the number of processes I had.
Well, 10,000.
Total amount of time it took is I kept increasing the number of processes that it,
it started off above here.
That's a little bit more than what it was before.
I was like 24 something, and then I was like 5.5 something, whatever.
But with that, I was like, did it better?
It got here, and it's like, shit.
It just started going back up again.
That's not great.
It's like, well, it would be better if it was like this.
These, these, these problem sizes are right here.
They didn't see any kind of bit of it hard to do today.
Okay.
Well, this is a time on one, and this is the time on two.
It's time one divided by time two, the speed up that we're talking about here, right?
So let's just say that that was 0.5.
That was 0.4.
It was 0.5 divided by 0.4.
1.2?
What did we say it was before?
1.6?
Well, that's closer because that's actually bigger than 0.5.
That's actually less than 0.4.
So it'll be, it'll be bigger than 1.2.
Let's just see exactly.
Let's go look at our speed up graphs.
Overall speed up.
So on two processes right in here, the overall speed up.
So that's not quite 1.6.
Now, this thing here, this program, it didn't do a bunch of trials for each one.
It only had one time.
You get what I'm saying?
I didn't do all of that statistical averaging in this one.
I only did, you know, doubly, that's probably not a triply nested one,
where it also did a trial for everyone.
But the idea is, as you can see here, that,
like, as we went up to six processes, even for this size n is equal to this,
I only got about 1.5 times, or 1.75 times after.
So, like, my problem really didn't get very much faster.
And I threw a bunch of quarters at it, didn't I?
Okay, well, now, why is that?
Well, part of that reason is,
is that no matter what I do to this thing over here,
I can't make this thing faster.
Yeah, but you told me that we might be able to get it to 4.4.
Well, now, this one here, this size,
5000, it did a little bit better now.
Damn, not just you out there because I didn't average it out.
I don't, I don't know.
We shouldn't modify the script to see.
But the point of it is, is that,
if the part you're doing isn't very big,
then you're never going to be able to make it speed up very much.
As a result,
let's run it one more time, see if we did something different.
Just want to run it again.
See if we get those different graphs.
Didn't have a chance to go ahead and ask you to do the, you know,
do 10 trials for a run.
Plus, I didn't want to in class take, like,
three or four minutes to run the thing.
I didn't want it to have to be like that.
The other thing I need to go back and do is make it so that,
because I think one of the things it's doing is,
it's creating individual files every time it does this.
And it's adding and removing and adding and removing files from a hard drive.
I don't know if you know, but, like,
when you've got a solid state drive,
you don't want it to be reading and writing and reading.
Reading's fine.
But writing over and over again is not particularly great, right?
Eventually these things run out.
So, if I were to do this for a lot,
I wouldn't want to do it on the other people's machines.
So, I'm not messing up my own hard drive.
I'm going to have to do, like, millions of times.
But I don't want to do billions of transactions against my file system
on this solid state drive.
So, we got our speed up here now.
That's 11.48 and 11.49.
So, that is, in fact, the new file.
So, I feel good about that.
So, yeah, I mean, I'm only getting  I mean,
now, this is not the same as it was before.
Bigger problem size is the one that achieved the maximum speed up in Big God.
But it's nowhere near 4.4, something less than what I expected.
What could be going on?
There's the fact that we're having to send this data around.
See, on the sequential program, I didn't have to send anything anywhere, right?
But this one's got to send it.
Somebody's like, how did the other computer  how did the other processes
get the data out of the file?
Well, the way this is written is that rank zero reads it up out of the file,
and then he scatters it to all the people using a collective communication
to scatter those rows out.
That takes time.
That's communication overhead.
And there was no communication overhead in the first program.
There is now.
That's why  that's why when we looked at that max speed up we expected to get,
we're never going to get even closer to that number
because of the fact that there's other overheads that are not in the sequential program.
And we probably want to instrument this program to go figure out,
well, how much time is it actually spending communicating?
How much time is it actually spending reading?
Right.
That can actually be difficult to obtain
because we're using print statements and timing measurements in our program to calculate those.
But think about it.
That's timing measurements on every processor.
They don't even have a shared clock space for that.
They're not synchronized with each other.
That's why you would use a tool to profile this thing out.
You know, you would actually have a thing that you would run.
You'd do some kind of profiling tool that Intel made or some NPI people made
that would actually do these fine-grained measurements
of your program while it's running so you could see all this sort of stuff.
And it would visualize it and be like, all right, cool.
This is my time to spend on CPU.
This is when the transaction's happening.
It would even have like a little diagram of like,
this process is sending stuff here.
You know, you could scroll around and see.
Problem is, a lot of those tools are not free, by the way.
Like, a lot of those tools are based on a particular implementation of NPI
because like, how you would measure all that would depend on which NPI version you're using,
right?
So like, a lot of these things are not free to come.
I'm going to try to see if I can find this free one.
We can profile it and have this really cool thing.
But how many people have ever profiled your code before?
And what profiler did you use?
And it goes and it tells you like, how much time it spends with this and this
and this gives you some sort of thing.
Probably with cords or something here and tile over here or other kinds of things.
That's the same thing here.
Except for it's probably not nearly as nice as the one that NVIDIA makes
because they've got a crap ton of money to put into it.
But you've profiled the code to try to see where is the problem?
Because we're not getting very much speed up here.
But at least knowing that we weren't going to get more than 4.4 anyway is the saying of,
I've almost got to two.
So I'm almost about half as wide as the maximum I could get.
You know, like someone says, most of you that were making your life 200 dollars
over the year, you're making 200 and 100 dollars.
And you'd be like, well, I'm halfway there.
You know, like, what about if you got into three here?
You'd be like, well, that's pretty freaking close to the best we could have gotten.
You see what I'm saying?
You need to know what the best you could have gotten is
so that you can know whether or not you need to keep working.
But now, what about if we look at those same things,
but we look at it just with respect to the time it spent doing the multiplication.
So like, it read a file out.
It shared the files with the people.
They did the multiplication.
And then they wrote the answer back to a file.
If we took out all of that except for just the part we're parallelizing.
So in other words, if we only measure the part we're parallelizing,
how much, how much did we, how, how do we do here?
Because these numbers we just saw are skewed by that communication and by that I-O.
But like, say, well, all right.
But what about just the math part?
Did we do a good job of just the math part?
You're like, all right.
Well, then that's what this is here.
So just the computation time.
Those curves look a hell of a lot better.
They started out, now remember that first one was like a 0.5.
But only, but the 0.35 of that was computation.
And look at that.
We damn sure they've done a lot better.
So all of these are nice.
They look nice, you know.
And so likewise, there's a speed up on that.
Look at that.
On just the computation, this is holding pretty linear.
And then we get right here and shit kind of starts going crazy.
But, you know, again, some of it would help here as if we did thousands of runs.
All right.
And the other thing is, what you typically want to look at is the problem sizes.
Like this one's the biggest problem.
Look at that.
The biggest problem kind of went here.
But it's pretty good.
These ones where this stuff here is happening, there's so many smaller problems.
Well, yeah, the smaller problems don't take any time, anyway.
Smaller problems, less than a tenth of a second.
You don't need to be paralyzing that stuff.
All right.
What about if we made the problem bigger?
You said we don't need to worry about that?
Well, good.
Let's go over here and say, what sort of sizes do we need to worry about?
Okay.
Well, let's do this.
Let's start at 10,000.
Okay.
Let's go to 40,000.
And let's do that 10,000 at a time.
Okay.
And I say that because when you get up to about 40,000, how big are these arrays?
It's 40,000 times 40,000 times 8 bytes per whatever.
What is that equal to?
Times 40,000 times 8 bytes per element of the array.
So let's see.
So how much is that right there?
12 gigabytes.
Is that what that is?
Like that.
So I'm going to be making a 12 gigabyte file on my computer.
Maybe I don't want to do, maybe I don't want to go away on that big.
How about if I just go to, maybe I do the 5,000 at a time,
but I go to a little less than this.
Maybe like I go to, or actually, you know what?
Let's go to 20,000.
We'll do the 1,000 at a time.
And we'll let that be running while that's going on.
The other problem you have to do is that when you start taking some of these numbers,
like when we get to some of this stuff and you take the number 40,000 multiplied by this, by that,
and you're using a function that's got the number of bytes in it, like a malloc.
That's what you pass to malloc, right?
The number of bytes and some of these other things when you're saving the guy,
it's like the number of elements.
Well, if that's actually larger, that will fit in an energy data type.
You can get some problems there where you might have to go to like a long, long end
or some kind of thing like that to get around these issues.
Now, I guess we can wait for this because by the time I start moving the mouse all around
and doing stuff, that's going to perturbate the answer.
So we're here in just a little bit each top.
Okay, so we got 96 gigs of RAM.
Why about a head more than that?
And you can see the processes being listed over here, right?
Like when you MPI run that, it's running a bunch of copies of the program.
So I bet if I were to bring up a disk IO monitor over here,
it would show like a gigantic stuff going on here.
All right, we're almost done here.
You have to use these utilities like this that run your program with a bunch of parameters
and look at what's happening.
When you first start, you're just going to like run it in the command line and just check,
make sure it doesn't go out.
But eventually, you've got to wrap it in something and gather data and visualize it,
look at it and see what's happening.
In other words, you don't have any sets of like what's going on, you know.
First thing is make sure it doesn't crash.
Second thing is make sure it gets the right answer.
Then like, okay, cool.
Now let's evaluate its performance.
All right, let's see what that did for us.
Oh, it's wrong.
So let's look at the overall speed up.
Okay.
I can get the speed up a little bit more there.
So like the bigger you make your stuff, the better because
this thing here isn't growing at the same rate that this is.
The thing gets bigger and you start having less of a problem over here.
And eventually, like the strategy we use to do the kernelization actually can start
to have an effect on this thing.
Like we will show later that there are clever things that you can do to overlap communication
and computation so that while some people are communicating, other people are computating,
I guess, computing.
You know what I'm saying?
This is the program I'm not doing any of that.
It's like one guy is reading.
Everybody's communicating.
Everybody starts processing.
And with the matrix, one matrix vector multiplication, like that's what I was going to do.
But it was the last time a science application would only have to do one matrix multiplication.
That's not how it works.
It does tens of thousands of them over and over again.
Okay, cool.
Now, so they're feeding in on each other.
They don't need to be written out of the file system.
It's staying resident of memory.
I think they might want a time simulation of weather.
Okay, the next time step.
Next time step.
Nice time step.
You're not reading and writing necessarily every iteration.
You might originally to make a visualization of weather happen.
But what you're really trying to do is look at what happens tomorrow,
and I need to have time to step tomorrow.
I don't need to necessarily read and write out every one of them.
So you can minimize the amount of this stuff that's being done
so that you really see a big gain over there.
And we can see that.
That's getting higher over there.
And if we had this as matrix multiplication,
so in Q, we would see this just shoot through the roof
because this thing would be big old.
Like, think about the big O of the amount of work that has to be done here.
It's a matrix that's in squared.
You have to read in and the work is also in square.
So the kind of the same rate on matrix matrix multiplication,
the matrices are still square.
So the memory order complexity of the of the thing,
the tower, let's just say the loop or whatever.
That's in squared, but this is in huge.
So for large values of N, this far outweighs that.
And this is the part where you're actually getting the work done.
So you do a better job on things that actually are intensive to compute.
So in some sense, this isn't really that intensive.
All right.
And we didn't even parallelize the I.O.
We only parallelize the compute part.
Okay.
What about the speed up?
Oh, that was, we did have that.
So yeah, so efficiency.
Still taking a damn hit, though.
I mean, it's bad.
I mean, it's not looking good, but it's going to look like that.
I mean, the only way to get that is for the speed up to be ideal and have it be up here.
You know, so it's like, well, you know, if each one of your,
say each one of these processors was like actually a computer and you had to buy two of them.
So you said, okay, why don't you kind of have 10,000 server.
And when I run it on two of those, so in other words, I spent $20,000.
The cost per bit of that that I'm getting is not actually $20,000 worth.
I'm getting less than that because it's only 80, 70% efficient.
So price to performance is not worth it, but it is faster.
It's just, it's not worth it.
It's not, every dollar you spend is not giving you the same increase.
At some point someone would say, well, it's not about money.
I have to have the answer now.
Well, then call up the money that it takes to get the answer out.
That's what you want.
Even if it's highly inefficient, right?
So that's kind of the, that's kind of the idea.
So I'm going to get the thing on there about the homework assignment for last time.
You know, like we talked about how there was thinking working on, right?
The report and presentation and all that stuff.
But this is also up there.
And when we come back next time, we're going to keep, we're going to pick up with this.
And we're going to look through every one of these files to understand
what is going on in these files.
And I'm asking you to look over not the parallel ones, okay?
I want you just to look over the make matrix, print matrix,
and the regular matrix that I can multiply and really look at it
and try to say, what is this doing?
Copy and paste it into an LLM and ask it, please explain to me
step by step what every damn line of this program means.
Because when you look at this stuff, there's going to be a lot of stuff in here.
There is a crap ton of error checking in this thing.
There's a crap ton of things that are like,
if I'm on this kind of computer, then I do this.
If I'm on that kind of computer, I'm going to do that.
There's probably stuff you've never seen before in C.
So I need you to go in there and really say, hey, have the thing break it down to you
to tell you this is what's going on in this file.
Like, couldn't I have just done this?
Couldn't I have just done that?
Well, ask it.
Could you really have done that?
Why is the code written the way it is instead of some way
that you might think would have been better?
Like, for example, when I read this thing out of the file and print it out,
I don't need to actually save the matrix and memory to do that.
I just read it one integer out of the time.
I don't want to put it one integer out of the time.
Read, print, read, print, read, print, read, print.
I can just do that.
That's not what it did.
I said, read the whole damn thing in the memory.
And then in the loop structure, loop over it and print it to the screen.
That's because it required me to now have space to hold that two-dimensional array.
And even though I didn't need to do that for a print,
I damn sure need to do that for the matrix vector multiplication.
So I'm trying to have all the programs written.
So they all allocate the memory the same way, whether they had to or not.
So there's a consistency across all the programs.
That's what's happening here.
Hope you guys have a great weekend.
And I'll see you later.
If you've got questions, just let them know.
I remember career fairs next Wednesday.
I'm hearing that through the College of Science,
that they said that there are more employers
that are related to the College of Science than there's ever been
in terms of Coastal's career fair.
All right.
Now, I don't know what that means.
There's five now, and they used to only be four.
Like, I don't know if that's what that means.
But they said it was a lot.
And I would say that when I went to the employer's website
to try to view how many employees there was,
it was like 20 entries per page.
And there were at least six pages.
I had to just keep clicking and clicking and clicking.
So there's a lot of employers, but some of them are, you know,
like a coffee shop and things like that too.
So, you know, anyway, have a good one.
It's in the gym, man.
Last year when I was there, you couldn't even move around in the gym.
There were so many employers and so many students.
Like, it was so packed.
I was having like an anxiety attack from just, I mean,
it was just like this with people.
The first two or three hours.
Then the last hour, you know, the employers were still there,
but the students had mostly gone.
So if you get there and it's overwhelmed.
But then by that point, a lot of the free stuff,
they've handed out like the shirts and the chat skis
and whatever else, like that's gone by that point.
So anyway, have a good one.
Yes, sir.
I have a question like this slide on me
to make for you with like your presentation.
Did you just want me to focus on like the marketing 100 data?
What about the MI2 super file data?
Yeah, I was going to ask you if you want me to look into that
and have like similar plots for that.
Yeah.
And like whatever you can do to get something to talk about.
And I have it so that like, if it looks good,
so it's got the raw images in there, I can play with it.
I can like modify it.
And maybe you like down it like either,
because remember, I'm not going to use the slides as is.
I want to take it.
I want to do something to it.
But like, I just need enough information.
I can tell what's going on, which would be great
if you could draw some diagram.
You know how we were talking about that power thing in the internet?
Let's suppose you had figured that out.
Well, then draw something that explains all that.
Say this is a screenshot of the header that's in the file.
This is that sub array over here.
That's what each one of these things mean.
Not like that.
Like something so that when you if I ask a question,
we're not sitting there in words trying to describe
to her what the hell is going on.
Like there is a picture.
Because like, I think that's one of the main reasons
that we are not communicating well in that in those meetings
is because there aren't anything to look at.
People are just talking.
And people are saying, there's got rows and rows of data
and arrays and things like that.
He's like, I don't know what we're talking about.
And then I think maybe we do.
And then that's not actually what we're doing.
She thinks something different.
And everybody's like, yeah, this is cool.
And then it's like, actually, we're not even saying the same thing.
And it's like, I think anything that would help
can say that would be useful.
Thank you.
Yeah, just like, whatever the best thing you can do, just do that.
OK.
Like, as if the contract didn't, you know what I mean?
Not that it does, as far as I know.
But no pressure.
No pressure.
All right, have a good one.
Thanks for working on that.
Yeah, of course.
Yes, sir.
Yeah, I was just asking if this thought came up
while I was doing some experiments yesterday
with the knowledge that I saw.
And I was wondering, you guys, when you were trying
to reproduce the results of the code of the person that you had,
were the results inconsistent?
Like, as in, were you guys able to get the code running,
and then the results were like?
So we got the code running, but the results were not.
They weren't as good as what you said they were.
OK, interesting.
And so Nathan's over there right now, and that guy is there,
although he sounds sick with fluids.
So he has not been a thing.
And Nathan was going to ask him, like, what are you guys going to get out of the place?
I'll let other people know.
Can you tell me what it is we need to modify about your files
so that we can make it be like it was whenever we ran those experiments?
Because he is clearly left in some kind of weird state.
Like, it wasn't even testing the stuff that was in a slide.
It was just testing some other thing.
He was like, well, what if I could see?
Clearly, it made a bunch of changes.
But there was not a copy of code that was like,
this is the exact code that produced these classes.
It was in some other state.
But we're getting very close to the point where we're going to communicate openly with them.
Part of the issue is that, you know,
he's at another nuclear weapons laboratory that's outside of the United States.
Even though we're allies, there's lots of things along with him talking to him.
Even just saying, hey, what's up?
Like, if it's like, you're having a good code, we're talking about French-style school,
the minute you start talking about code, it's like,
okay, well, this is work-related.
So, there's a whole protocol of work.
But the hope was that they would see face-to-face inside their compound there.
The guy would be like, yeah, yeah, this is what you need to do.
Are you getting results that are also crazy?
Are you trying to use this code?
No, I have no idea what that code is.
Or at least related to what I was doing.
There are, like, some times I run an experiment,
and, like, the results are, like, wow.
Are over 85 percent.
And then I rerun.