And the way you can tell
is that if either one of
these is a one, but not
either nor both, then it's overflow.
So you just take this wire,
run it here, run it here,
run this into an exclusive or
gate, and that is the overflow circuit.
So like that's, you
know, it'll come out later
in the class, you
know, that sort of thing.
It's pretty cool.
Cool.
I need to grab some water
here, so I'll be right back.
Is the vending machine
up here actually working yet?
Is it still broken?
There's one down.
I don't want to go downstairs.
I don't think the second floor one is.
Let's just get some water I guess.
Okay.
Of course.
No, I'm just kidding.
No, I'm just, I'm just auditing.
Okay.
Yes.
They're not going to believe me when I try
to tell them that
there's something wrong with this.
I'm going to record it.
Is it allowed by other people
in it trying to use it?
Nope.
Hit on or off any of these buttons.
Nothing's doing anything.
Okay.
I think it's not proof
that there's something wrong with it.
At least that works
and that's not working.
Okay.
All right.
Looks like class has started,
so let's go ahead and...
So this is the syllabus.
Kind of pass it around a bit or whatever.
Pass it around.
There's probably a lot more
than we actually need, but...
So if you're in Moodle
and you go to our class,
the syllabus is there both for the people
that are taking it
for honors credit as well
as there's just a regular credit.
And if you look at it, it's really...
There's only one
small difference between the
two with the way the grades are calculated
and the project part of the class.
Anybody take it for honors?
Okay.
So we can talk separately about it.
Lydia Morgan?
Yes, sir.
I wrote you an email.
Are you good?
Yeah.
I think I got it.
I'm offering you an opportunity
to interview for a position.
Oh, that's...
That's okay, dude.
Let's see.
So let's take a look here.
So this is our cap song course, right?
It requires all these things.
210 networking, software engineering,
operating systems, count, chart one,
and implicitly all the
programming classes and everything else.
So it's kind of like
the end of the line, right?
I mean, people are
here graduating this semester.
What about next semester?
What about some semester beyond that?
So anyway, yeah.
So we're near the end, right?
So let's take a look.
There's only one required textbook
for the class, this first one.
It's called the introduction
to the parallel programming.
It's really kind of a simple
book if you look at it.
A lot of universities use it for
sophomores that are
learning about parallel computing.
So it's not high level.
It's not super intense, but it also won't
be the only place we do stuff from.
But I think it's cool because you find the
following when you try
to find any other parallel
computing text.
It's either written like some sort
of graduate textbook
that's impossible to understand,
or it's only about one small aspect
of parallel computing, like
only about shared memory,
only about MPI, only
about vector, only about GPUs.
And it's like, no, we need to kind
of have an older
view of those things, right?
So this is the closest that you can kind
of come to that
combined with this book here,
which is out of print.
You can't get it anymore.
But you can definitely find
the PDF for it online.
It was written a long time ago, 2003.
And the ideas about how parallelism works
is the same now as it was then,
and there's different
accelerators and stuff
now, but the issues, race conditions,
concurrency, throughput, all of these
things are all the same concept.
This book was great.
Michael J. Clinton, who's
a Stanford professor, whatever,
your science has done all of a sudden
inside of his life.
I was like, I'm
going to be a photographer.
So I guess they couldn't publish it.
But anyway, he wrote a really
good book, and I like it.
And we're going to have slides for this,
as well as other
materials will be in Moodle.
There's student resources that
are available online for it.
In this thing here, there'll be slides and
some stuff that I'll
provide for it as well,
and can point you to
places where it can be acquired.
And I'm only saying that
because our bookstore can't offer it.
So my thought is I've tried the official
route to offer it,
and they can't offer it.
So now it's the
official route saying you can
get it in various
ways at these various places.
All right.
Now, this one, this is just, hey, if you
find yourself, you'd love
in this class, and you're
like, I just love this material.
This book, which is a lot of, you
know, it's not more recent than this book.
Yeah, it is.
Probably more recent.
I don't know about the second edition.
I don't think the
second edition really improved
it enough to make
it totally like, say, that
it was new.
But this one is really sophisticated, but
it's long, so 100 and some pages.
It's a really cool
book, and it was written
by a person that
is both a parallel computing
expert and also a physicist.
And so as you're going to find out in
here, a lot of parallel
computing is done for high
performance reasons that come into play
when you're talking
about science, modeling, and
prediction, and these kind of things.
And so it's a cool book.
Let's see.
It's a standard rating scale in here.
The pluses are where
the pluses are normally at.
Let's take a look at this.
It's midterm, 30%.
That's a lot.
That's going to be individual.
No computer, no nothing.
It's going to be a
pencil and paper sitting right here.
Everything's OA.
It's whatever comes out of your head.
And it's 30% of your grade.
It's 75 minutes.
So it's serious.
Now assignments of projects.
Pretty much that
includes everything that's
not one of these other three things.
Like, for example, say we
have a quiz one day.
I don't say quizzes on here.
But I say assignments of projects.
We'll just call it an in-class project.
It's due in five minutes.
And it'll be broken down and moved away.
The actual assignments of that 30%,
70% is in this category.
15% is in this.
That's all going to be combined
into a single number that is then
30% of your final grade.
That'll be how that works.
Team project.
And by the way, I'm going to encourage,
in the class that's being recorded,
I'm going to get those things
available for you
through Moodle or whatever.
You know, these projects and assignments,
I'm going to encourage you to make
use of whatever
technology is currently available.
Okay?
I think it's like sitting
your head in the ground.
If we pretend like that after graduation,
you're not going to
use every resource available.
You can try to do whatever your
employer is trying to get you to do.
So the caveat is the following.
That test, that's 30%.
This final exam is 30%.
That's 60% of your grade.
And that's going to be
75 minutes of pencil and paper
and 120 minutes of pencil and paper
of all the same concepts that are required
in order to understand
how to do those assignments
that you're going to be using
chat, GPT, and call, and so forth.
So what I'm trying to say
is when you use those materials,
what I'm saying here,
when you use those things,
you better understand what
the **** is going on
because you will not be
able to pass this class
just based on those assignments
that get turned into 30%.
It doesn't matter if that's 100.
You're not going to pass the class.
So we've all used the material.
I use it every day.
And I use it multiple times
if they try to solve stuff
that I need solved.
But if there's something I'm
going to be accountable for,
I use it to try to learn the thing.
Can you explain this to me?
Can you show me what the piece is?
Or why is this the way it is?
Because those things do a
pretty good job with that stuff.
And better yet, you can test it out
and see how it works on your own computer.
You can test it out.
You can evaluate it.
You can do performance analysis on it.
You can do all these sort of things
to make sure it's
actually achieving the goal
that the program is
supposed to achieve, right?
Does that make sense?
So I'm going to hold you accountable
that whatever amount of stuff
you're doing outside of class
would be tools that you learned from it.
Otherwise, you're not going to do well.
And I'm not going to have
any sympathy for that at all.
I'm just not.
If you've got access
to the most powerful tools
that the world has ever known,
you should benefit from them in a way
that actually is more
than just regurgitating a thing
into an assignment that you turn around
and copy and paste it
into the assignment thing, right?
I mean, I think that's the kind of deal.
So I'm not saying this to be like,
I encourage you to use it.
I want you to use it.
I want you to.
Because I don't want
you to be stuck forever
on some kind of particular thing.
But I want you to learn from
the thing that got you on stuff.
All right.
There won't be any
kind of curving in here.
There won't be any kind
of extra credit in here.
The tendency is required, but
I'm not going to take it.
If you happen to not be here,
you don't have a
valid excuse that's recognized
under the attendance policy of
Coastal that it has to zero.
Homework turned to delay.
It doesn't matter what
the reason is to zero.
So that's the deal.
Please use email communication as the way
to communicate with me.
Or use Microsoft Teams to
ping me with the question
or something in there.
Maybe do both.
Sometimes notifications are
silenced on the phone
or on the thing.
I might not see the thing in Teams.
But my email, I'm
constantly looking at the email.
Or if you say, hey, I
sent you a thing in Teams,
can you go look at it
because you've used it to upload things
and do it screenshots or whatever.
If you think that it's
probably more convenient than email,
then use that.
Academic integrity.
Academic integrity is only
going to be included
on the things that you're doing in here.
Pencil, paper, clothes,
books, clothes, notes.
The stuff that you're
doing outside of class,
I'm not going to be trying to figure out
if things match or whatever.
That's an impossible task.
It's a stupid fool's errand to
try to figure out any of that.
I think we're past that.
My opinion on the university
has realized that yet or not.
But I had realized it a
long time ago, about late 2022.
So I'm only concerned about
what you can produce in class
on paper for the vast majority of it.
But am I going to
grade you out of class things?
Yeah, I'm definitely going to grade them.
But I'm just saying that they're
likely to be very good grades,
wouldn't you say?
Interesting.
I don't know if
that's not always the case.
Anyway, all right, cool.
Any questions about any of this stuff?
Let's get started.
So parallel computing.
Let's take a look at it.
Actually, in the syllabus itself,
there's some graphs in that thing, right?
There's these little things.
Let's take a look at that.
It's kind of an interesting little thing
to look at on the
first day, this thing right here.
See, you know, as a function,
a number of processes and parallelism.
How many people took three 10 with me?
Anybody?
That's a good thing.
So we don't have this
weird scenario that we're doing something
that some people have
done and some people haven't.
So that's good.
Did you work again in
the summer in Savannah River?
How did that go?
Awesome.
That's cool.
I was just thinking
of that because we're trying
to work with them on
having a better student pipeline,
having it be more like the
kind of thing that, you know,
they would come here and
visit like during the recruiting days
and all this sort of stuff,
as well as like some stuff
on some DOE research
things that have come up.
All right, cool.
So let's just talk about this idea.
I'm going to try to motivate
it with like a simple problem.
What about if you
were on a computer, right?
You're on some sort of
computer and let's say this is
random memory right here.
It's pretty big.
Let's say you got 256
gigs of RAM and, you know,
most of it is full
of some data that you're processing.
And for the sake of some simplicity,
let's just assume that
it's a one-dimensional array
that just has a bunch of
numbers that you need to add up.
That's all you got to do, okay?
So we're saying, you know,
about 220 gigs of data
that needs to be added.
So it's just in a big array.
That's what the real problem is.
But for the point of simplicity,
let's just draw a little tiny
around on the board to look at it.
What about a random array?
It's a one-dimensional thing.
It has some numbers like
let's just make some small numbers
of one to two.
But let's just do it
three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
nine, ten.
Let's just add those numbers.
Now, you know that
it wouldn't necessarily be stored.
It would just be an arbitrary data.
We just need to calculate
the sum of that data.
Now, what sort of structure
could we do in our...
I'm not talking about C
or Python or this or this.
I'm just saying just the basic idea.
What would you do to add a...
But I'm not saying usability
and function called sum, okay?
I'm just saying, like,
how would you do this?
What would you simply do?
What would you do?
You have an array A sub I.
There's an array A.
It's defined with all this stuff in it.
You want to...
So that's what I'm calling him here.
What function that adds these
index into one area of one?
Okay, and how would you do that?
Like, what sort of control structure
would you use to do that?
Four of them.
Okay, cool, yeah.
So you might do something
like, all right, so four.
I equals zero, I less than ten
or nine or whatever it is here.
You know, I plus plus.
Maybe you say, like, sum equals zero,
and then you come in here and you say,
sum plus equals A sub I.
Something like that.
Is that what you were thinking?
Something like that?
Oh, yeah.
Hey, Chris, was that
what you were also thinking?
Something like that?
Yeah.
I understand it.
It could be a dual or a while ago.
I don't care about that.
It's just a loop.
It's a loop.
And it is literally traversing
the array one at a time
to add the numbers up.
Like, that's how you and I would
have to do it by hand, right?
You got to have any fancier
way to do that by hand
than to literally go number
by number and to do it.
But suppose that you and your friend
could only add two numbers at a time.
I don't see any other
way to do this, do you?
Now, you might say, oh, I'm
going to write a list of numbers.
There's a computer that's going
to do the list of numbers.
So let's just say that
adding two things at a time.
Now, we know that there are
things the computer is doing on that.
But I'm saying that we haven't
discussed any of that stuff before.
But whenever you use one
of these functions in Python,
you probably don't talk about what
is actually happening under the hood
to make it happen.
That's what we're trying to
talk about in this class
and build our ways up
to understanding what the issue is
with actually running some
of this sort of stuff.
So let me ask you a
question from Dr. Reichert's 220 class
or when she's not going
to teach us it now, right?
Mr. Hickland also teaches it, right?
So whoever taught it, let's just say 220.
What is the time order
complexity of that strategy, Chris?
Big O of N.
OK, so as N gets larger, then
so does the amount of time it takes
to do this thing, right?
Cool. I mean, this is time,
and this is N, and, you know,
time is proportional to
this, so it grows linearly.
OK, cool. That makes sense.
So if you got a jack-ton of numbers,
it's going to take a long time, right?
OK, cool. So, all right.
So let's, you know, I'm
just making something up here, OK?
What about if it took the computer
one second every time it added a number?
How many seconds would it take to
add this thing up, more or less?
Ten. I mean, yeah, we will.
The first one didn't have to have, so
I actually wanted to do a nine addition,
so I don't care about
that, because N is big.
If plus or minus one, it doesn't matter.
It's just a billion things you're adding.
Does it matter if
it's $999, $999, $999, $999?
That doesn't matter.
So it wasn't a trick
question like, is it nine?
Is it 10?
What if?
That's not what it was.
It was like, it was just 10.
It was 10, OK?
All right.
But your computer doesn't
have just one processor,
and it has a bunch of them.
Your phone does, too.
There's more than one core in there.
I mean, you know, right?
I mean, I'm assuming nobody
in here is not a device
that doesn't have at least four
or eight cores in it, right?
I mean, it might have
a lot more than that,
but it got at least.
Well, of course, that means that each one
of those cores could be doing this work.
I mean, why is it that I would give one?
That's like saying, all right, cool, guys.
I'm working at a restaurant.
There's a bunch of servers that
could be carrying food out the tables,
but only one person's going to be
carrying anything to the
table any one time.
There might be a bunch of ****
plates that need to go out there,
but one person's going to be doing it.
That's stupid, right?
Wouldn't you want to use all
the servers to try to do it?
Because then that's going to
decrease the amount of time
it takes to get all
the plates out to the table.
That's the same thing in your computer.
You wouldn't want to do
a for loop like this.
This is ridiculous.
Because nothing in this for loop is
telling the computer how to do this,
except for one core is
going to do that one thing.
That's all it's going to do.
It doesn't matter whether
you write this in
Python or Java or C or whatever else.
Those might be slightly
different times or whatever,
but on average for
really large values of N,
it's not going to make any difference.
They're going to take a long time
at that computer there that, you know,
one, two, three,
four thousand dollar laptop
or five, ten,
fifteen thousand dollar server
with 128 cores in it.
You know what somebody
handed it on anything?
Nothing.
One core will be doing something, and
the other one won't be doing anything.
And that's not good because
a thirty thousand dollar computer
should be sitting there being used
more than one percent utilization, right?
But you might say, well, now hey now,
I know that I could go put this thing
in a search structure with NumPy
and I could say some on it,
and it does it better
than I thought it would.
Yeah, you could.
How does it do that?
I don't know what it's called.
That's cool, and that's cool.
I mean, there's always a little
way out of stretch like that.
There are things I play with.
I don't know how they work.
I don't even know how they work.
The man in this
class is parallel computing.
So we need to know how that works.
That's the purpose of this thing now.
Does that mean you're going to
reinvent wheel every time you do so?
No.
I would look like you need to be
able to understand the
technology that you're wielding.
And that's what we're going
to try to understand in here.
So what about if we had two cores?
So there's two cores.
They're both attached to the system of us,
which is then attached to the main memory,
which then has this
10-element array in it.
What could I do?
Like, if I was going to try to
divide this work up, what could I do?
Okay.
So we divide it up.
We have this core add those numbers up.
Cool.
Now, when that happens, let's
just say I get two numbers.
I'm not going to worry about
what these actually add up to.
That's cool.
So we did that.
It won't have to happen after that.
All right.
Who's going to do that?
Because it's like two cores.
Which one do you want to pick to do that?
First one?
Perfect.
All right.
So cool.
So let me draw a con
diagram of core one and core two.
Core two starts at zero.
So let's just say core zero and core one.
So over time, right, core
zero is adding up his map,
and core one is adding up his map.
And then core one stops.
And I'm going to exaggerate this.
Core zero is going to
then add the two partial sums.
And we have an answer.
Now, there is some amount of
time here that's taking the core.
Zero is doing stuff that
core one is not doing.
Now, if you get enough of that happening,
you're back to the same problem.
A bunch of things sitting
idle that are not cool.
But in general, yeah, that seems
like a reasonable thing to do.
All right.
How do you do that with a toilet?
This hard coded example, what might we do?
I don't know.
Can you tell me?
I mean, how would you
actually know how to do it?
And have you ever done
anything like that with threads
or processes or whatever in your programs
where you actually divide
the work of the non-cores?
So that's what we'd have to do here.
So we'd have to have it
so that we'd need to have it.
So the code itself, this
code was running over here.
While it's the same code
as the one this is,
it's been parameterizing.
It's starting and stopping in
different places in the for loop.
So core zero needs to go
from zero to less than five, right?
And the other one's going to need
to go from five to less than nine.
They need to make sure they don't overlap.
Well, what about if it was an
even number of things to add up?
Somebody would have to
be a person out, right?
Did we add more of it?
So then you might say, yeah, okay.
I mean, that's just arithmetic.
I'm going to divide it up, and
I'll round up or down or whatever.
It takes four functions, and
I'll do something up here.
Yeah, that's true.
That's cool.
What about if there's p
processors that are all doing it?
What about if p exceeds n?
What's the right number
of processors to use?
There should be a sweet spot.
One is not good using all of them,
and that isn't going to be good either
because there's a bunch of other phenomena
that we're going to see this inside.
So there's a lot, too, trying to do this.
So we're going to talk about mainly
three ways of doing this in here.
Like threads, processes, which
these things can take place
inside of what's
called your shared memory.
Now, one computer with a bunch of cores,
but this core can
see this entire memory, right?
I mean, like, literally, like, you
know, over in the server room,
there's the rack, there's
a 2U blade in here,
and inside of there,
there's, you know, another board,
and on that motherboard, you
know, maybe there's, you know,
two processors plugged in here.
There's much RAM over there.
Now, this RAM is
physically connected to this stuff.
Like, all the little cores
over here can see this RAM.
All these little cores can see that RAM,
and they can't see
it equally well, though, necessarily.
Sometimes there's issues where it's not
all the stuff is equally fast.
But then this other computer over here,
what about if you owned this entire rack?
That's your company's rack right there.
And you wanted to add
all of these numbers together.
Well, we started out here assuming that
this thing was in memory over here.
How did they get in memory of the input?
And that would only be
in one of the people's memories.
It'd be like over here.
How would you get it
over there in those memories?
And how would they communicate
back and forth in here?
Because these things are most likely
connected to some kind of switch
with network connections that
are going over here, right?
And there might even be something
fancier than that nowadays, you know,
like where, you know, Nvidia has come
out with some kind of thing where,
even though these things
are in separate racks,
this network makes it
possible from this computer
to see all of the RAM
of that computer at the same time
through this high-speed,
extremely expensive network, okay?
Like there's all that kind of stuff.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to start off this class
just playing with shared memory.
We got one computer with lots of
cores that can all see the same RAM.
And by the time we get to the
end of it, class, we're going to be like,
no, we got lots of computers
that can't see each other's RAM.
How do we do this?
Okay, so let's talk about kind of getting
started on it a little bit, all right?
Let's go in here.
Let's try to take a
look at, let's see, 473.
And I copied that folder over
and I copied it over again.
We got materials, we got slides.
Now, chapter one of our
book, I mean, you know,
I prefer to do stuff on pencil
and paper on the board, you know,
like looking through a
huge number of slides.
There are going to be some things
in here that slides have a good,
cool drawing already or animations
or whatever the case may be.
So let's see what the, this
is the chain code text, right?
We want to choose for sophomores
at USC and Clemson, for example,
to learn how to do parallel computing.
So it's not too bad, you know, so
why would we want to do, you know,
what's the whole purpose?
We need things done faster.
Now, have you ever, like, a real
program, maybe not when
you're doing a job,
but like one that you did here at Coastal,
what is the longest you've ever had to
wait for one of your programs to run?
And I don't mean one where
it has to interact with people
because it's just sitting
there waiting for user input.
I'm talking about an actual
program that's going to go do
a bunch of data
processing and get finished.
How long have you had to wait?
12 hours.
Eight hours.
That's a long time.
Now, 12 seconds, that's
not too bad depending
on what it is you're trying to do.
That's certainly not good if
you need it to be human-interactive.
You know, one second's too long to wait.
It'll be like a third of
a second and it starts getting,
you start getting agitated after
that, you have to wait, right?
We're not talking about where
we're trying to provide real time
back and forth with individual users
because it needs to be responsive
to you in the mouse or around
or touching some device
or whatever, you know.
That is certainly a concern.
And that's why I'm
like, for example, in 356,
they talk about how do
you, you know, maintain response
to the mobile processing sharing machine
and how do they do it?
They round robin with all the processes,
so everybody gets a
little chunk of the processor
and that way there's this
illusion that there's
concurrency going on.
We're going to do that same thing too,
but they do it to make
the machine kind of usable, right?
Because when you run
something on the computer,
you can't have it just freeze
up doing one thing while it's waiting
for something else because
your computer's running hundreds
or maybe thousands of processes, right,
each of which need a little bit of stuff.
That's not what we're
talking about right now.
We're talking about, hey, this
whole computer I've got is dedicated
to doing the one thing
that I need to get done.
All right, and
human-interloop's not a problem.
It's a problem that the
complexity of whatever I'm running
takes 10 hours, takes 12 hours.
10, 12 hours, like, is not bad.
Some of the people that I work with,
we're talking about if the
computer started running it today,
it might take three months
for it to run uninterrupted.
Okay, so three months
is a long time, right?
I mean, that's, you know,
and that's in parallel, you know.
So we need the performance of our stuff
that we're trying to do to increase these.
Well, yeah, but the
computers themselves have been increasing.
So, like, if it was
able to do it last year
and stuff's even faster this
year, why is it that way?
Wouldn't we get kind
of an increase in performance
just because we got newer
graph this year than before?
You would, to some extent.
But you're not getting
it because what everybody expects
the computer to do is more this
year than it was last year, right?
So every time you
fix some kind of problem,
users want something better,
cooler, faster, more complicated,
more realistic, more fine-grained.
So the size of the
data went from kilobytes to megabytes
to gigabytes to terabytes to
people that I work with,
it's just petabytes of data.
Okay, well, that would have been
inconceivable even ten years ago, right?
So they were happy
with whatever they had then.
All they needed to do is
just get from gigabytes to terabytes
and it was going to be okay.
And then terabytes came along,
but actually it's not okay.
We need something else.
So, you know, it's just a human condition.
We want this sort of stuff.
Like, for example, right now with
this hurricane that's going on out there,
you saw the little
spaghetti models that are showing
like what the weather
people think are running.
What kind of computer do
you think those things run on
when they try to predict
the future path of the hurricane?
They're running on big
supercomputer kind of things.
Now, let's suppose you could
get a very accurate idea
of where Hurricane
Aaron would be tomorrow.
It'd be perfect, but it took
six months to get that answer.
Is that useful?
Oh, because everybody's already
dead and it moved on.
It doesn't matter.
So what can you get in the time you go?
That means you cannot run
the calculations you want to run
because it takes too long.
You've got to run fewer calculations.
That means the models aren't as precise.
That means that there's
a lot more uncertainty.
Oh, instead of using like a, you know,
say a one kilometer
resolution of the Earth's surface,
think about that.
I mean, square kilometers there
are of the Earth's surface.
I'm trying to model all
that with all this physics.
I can't do that.
I've got to use 10 kilometer things.
I've got to use 50 kilometer things.
It makes the computing go a lot faster,
but it also makes the
models predictivity be a lot less
predictive, right?
I mean, that's part of the issue.
So, you know, that's
some of the issue here.
So we try to
like write these parallel systems
so that we can make things happen faster.
The other little aspect of it is sometimes
it's not even about how fast it is.
Let's suppose that if
you actually have enough RAM
on one computer, you could
do it on one computer.
But the amount of RAM
it needs is 800 terabytes.
There aren't any machines
today that one can have
that has 800 terabytes on one computer.
There might be one day,
but that's not the case.
So you have to actually split it up
just because the data is too big.
Maybe also commensurately, the
computation is a long time
because there is a lot
of data, but maybe it's not.
Maybe really the bottleneck is
you just have to have
a lot of computers so
that you've got enough RAM.
Each one, let's say, has 256 gig RAM,
but I've got to have 10,000
of them to get the total
amount of RAM that I
need to actually run the problem.
So that's also a concern.
And then sometimes it's,
oh, you need the speed
and the space, so to speak.
And blah, blah, blah, you
know, for a long time,
you know, everything was
increasing like 50% per year.
You know, it was called Moore's Law.
You know, when I was growing
up, that was certainly the case.
If your computer was
1 megahertz this year,
then next year it was
going to be 2 megahertz,
and then it was going to be 4 megahertz.
And it was just going up like that.
I mean, in the same exact
program as 2 RAM last year,
that took five minutes,
it takes one minute now.
So you go, oh, that's sweet.
I didn't do anything.
I didn't reprogram anything.
There's no new algorithms or anything.
It's just that the
**** processor got faster.
It just was faster.
But then somewhere like around,
as it says, 2002 here,
I would argue probably more like 2004,
they could not make
individual processors any faster.
But there's a lot of reasons for that.
Let's talk about some of those reasons.
One of the reasons is
that the amount of power
that a computer uses is
proportional to the voltage squared
multiplied by the clock frequency.
So like here in my lifetime,
when I had my first computer,
the processor was running at 12 volts,
and then it was 5 volts,
and then it was 1 volt.
And then now today some of these
things are running at like 0.7 volts.
Because this is quadratic
with respect to voltage,
that was fantastic, and
that really helped a lot
because the power went down.
But my entire life, my
very first computer I got
was 4.7 megahertz.
And then the last
computer I bought in here
that only had one core
in it was 2.4 gigahertz.
Now how many gigahertz are we at today?
What's a gigahertz of your computer?
It might not even be 2.4 gigahertz.
I would be very, very
surprised if you have access
to your computer that's
more than 4 gigahertz.
Well now, we're talking
about in my lifetime,
between when I was in middle
school and whenever I was in college,
it went up by a factor of 500.
But we're saying that between now
and back when I was in college
and I'm 48 years old, it's hardly moving.
That means that this performance
increase that you used to get
by having the multiplicative factor
of having the clock frequency go up.
Because every time the
clock frequency went up,
the amount of time it took
to run your program went down,
well the clock
frequency didn't keep increasing.
What happened?
What happened is
there's physical limitations
on what you can do.
Because this thing gets too hot.
During that same period of time,
processors may have went
in from like this side
I'm not talking about the
package now that it's sitting in.
Because that thing that's in there,
there's all kinds of mess in there.
That's not really the whole
thing about actually the processor.
It's very tiny in there.
So don't you imagine
something that's like the size
of a little postage,
little tiny postage stamp
that is running at 1,000 watts.
That is a super amount of
heat in a very small area.
You know, like if you've
got to play to hot food
and you want to cool it
down, if you spread it out,
it has more surface area on
it and you blow across it,
it cools down faster and you've
lived in a big pile, right?
That's just thermodynamics.
But when you've got a
little tiny thing that over time,
everybody's been trying to
make these things smaller,
taller, smaller.
That means you're using
the same power maybe
because this number was going down
and that number was going up.
And this has stopped going up
and this has also stopped going down.
So that power
has remained relatively constant
inside of these individual cores.
And each one of us is
tiny and there's produced so a sheet,
it'll burn up.
Like if you think about it
from a thermodynamics point of view
or maybe even like just water,
if you've got a cup of water
and you start pouring water into it,
eventually it'll pour over
to the side, all right?
Water's got to pour out of
it at a rate in general
greater than or equal to the
rate the water's going into it.
Otherwise, the water will overflow.
And the same thing
is true for a processor.
The heat that's being generated in it
has to be dissipated out of it
and removed from inside the thing
at a rate that's
faster than it's heating up.
Otherwise, the processor will
burn up and die, okay?
How do you get heat out
of something really tiny like that?
You can't spread it out like
a bowl of soup that's hot.
Well, you do all kinds of fancy things
and try to like bring
the heat pipes out of this
and you start doing water cooling
and you start doing all this other stuff.
But at some point, you just can't
have so much power in one place, right?
The other issue was is that
since they couldn't make this any faster,
they said, cool, you know what?
Then inside this little thing here,
I'm going to blow this
up and make it bigger now,
cool, I'm going to have
80 cores in it, all right?
So I'm going to be like, all right,
you know, I have maybe 16 cores in it.
So I won't have any one core
that's actually any better than
the **** more or less.
That's not totally true.
There have been
really other cool advances.
But from kind
of a qualitative perspective,
this thing really is not a lot
much better than anything that I had
when I was in college.
It's just a lot more of them, okay?
A lot more of them.
And then that's just one
processor, but on the other board,
you can have typically two
or four of those on here
and then you can have thousands
of those in a data center.
So the scale of it is gigantic, right?
So that's why you
ceased getting
single processor performance,
and now the multi-processor,
if its performance was greater,
simply because they were more
of a pack-in to that space.
But the programming, you
and I all learned,
like when we were
in our first programming classes,
was like the way programs
work is you do this,
and then you do this,
and you do it sequentially.
And that's how we were all taught, right?
I mean, we were all like, yeah,
you got to do it in order.
You know, you got to have, I
mean, that's the way code is written out,
for God's sakes.
It's like a line of code, a line of code,
a line of code, a line of code.
Well, wait a minute now.
Does that line even depend on this line?
If it doesn't, why do you
have to do that after this one?
Couldn't you do it at
the same time as this one?
Yeah, but now what about if
this statement depends on this statement?
You can't do those at
the same time, can you?
So there's a few issues here,
but if you've got
a lot of independent calculations
that could be performed at
the same time, think about it.
If I had 10, if I had five cores here,
I could have one of
them add these two numbers,
one of them add these two numbers,
one add these two, one add these two,
and then of those
five, two could add this,
or one could add that, one could add this,
we've got this thing left over.
These two things, say, add together
here on the next time step,
and then that gets added there,
and then we get something
that looks like a binary tree
of adding the stuff up.
And we know now that the big O
of this thing is log in of this thing.
It's not in.
So now we've taken this thing, well, that
is not the right way to say it.
The height of the tree
is the order of that.
The total number of time
steps still really depends on
the number of processors,
because here's the thing.
If you've got a problem that's big O of N,
that's the algorithm. That's just
the nature of what it is.
Now, you might be able
to do it faster by saying,
I will get it done, and
I'll divide the problem by P processors,
and now it'll be faster,
because it's being divided by P.
P is not a function of
N, so therefore that's like a coefficient.
That's just like saying, it's
one P, big O of N.
You're not going to change
the tower complexity of the algorithm,
but that factor, you know,
like that you learned about 220,
how they'll say,
well, sometimes that matters.
That factor's really tiny.
For the size problem you're worried about,
they can be a lot faster.
I don't know what
you're thinking about it.
They should have it in that class.
They always do stuff like this.
They say, okay, cool, man.
All right.
One of them's quadratic, so they
go and do like, all right.
And one of them's linear, you
know, and then another one is like,
I don't know, some
sort of logarithmic thing,
and it comes out here, and it
goes out here, and it goes here.
So like, when we get
out past this point here,
it's like, that's the best,
and that's the next best,
and that's the worst.
Cool.
Well, what about right over here?
That's the best right there.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But in my class it says, that's true,
but that's only for N like in here.
N just keeps going to infinity.
N's not going to infinity.
Have you ever seen a computer
that has some infinite amount of memory?
No.
It's going to be whatever it is.
Now, that might be a big number.
It might be a true.
The question is, for N
equals a trillion, which one's better?
It's one thing to say that if the
limit is in goes
to infinity, this is better,
and that's cool from
a mathematical, theoretical perspective,
but it's the truth on the ground,
which one of these things is better?
And also, what you
find on parallel computing is,
is that algorithms that
are really crappy sequentially
are also trivial to parallelize.
Okay?
And these ones that are
really, really sophisticated
can't be paralyzed.
So for a given size
system, it might actually be better
to do it the crappy way in parallel.
Do you get what I'm saying?
You get hit with that,
because sometimes you'll see something,
you're going, I know this is
not the fastest
theoretical sequential algorithm.
That's right.
We're not doing this sequentially.
We're doing it in parallel, and
that's why we're not doing that algorithm,
because while a pencil paper is
the best, in practice it is not.
In that little book I told
you about that physics student, Brody,
his book's all about that.
It's like, cool theory says this,
practice says this and other things.
And it just hits it over
and over again in that book.
It's really kind of cool.
But either way, aside from all that,
we've been taught the wrong
way to think about problems
all along in computing
since the very beginning,
that you've got to do this,
and we've got to do this,
because that is not the case.
You need to figure out what
can be done at the same time.
All of these numbers can be
added together at the same time
and independent of each other.
But then they have to be
reduced down to a single number.
But now what about if this
thing literally was trillions of numbers?
Well, cool.
Each one of them was order one, you
know, let's say those
one, two, three, four processes.
One-fourth of a trillion,
one-fourth of a trillion,
one-fourth of a trillion, cool.
But at that point, it's just
take this subtotal and this subtotal
and add it together and take those two
subtotal and add it
together, and you're done.
So still, quote, big O
of one-fourth of a trillion.
But then they've got some tree-like
structure to add this stuff together.
Now, I want you to think about something.
This assumes that I can
get this array in this memory.
Let's say we've got that.
It assumes that we can divide the loop
up to make it so that each core,
which reversed, is part of the array.
That's not too bad.
The odds are right here.
Here's how you can do it.
If the queen of people is like,
here's a little civic code you can use.
It's just going to work.
You can play through
the arithmetic and say, yeah,
because it thinks of all the corner cases.
It's like, well, you and I could
do a good job just sitting down and,
all right, we just
don't divide it by this.
Oh, but I've got to shift it over.
Oh, it's a plus one.
What if I was odd?
Yeah, okay.
But this little line will help us divide,
figure out the indices for the
core loop to make it work.
But then we've got to have
a second thing that adds these up.
Wait a minute.
Now, who's adding what?
Because there's only two,
like in this case,
who adds these two together?
So is this processor going to sit idle,
and this guy is the one
that adds his subtotal to this one?
Well, this person sits idle.
This one works.
It has this subtotal.
Which one is sitting idle the other times?
So you have to have some
way to program out of it
to make it so that you
don't have some sort of deadline.
It's not like I'm trying
to grab something from you,
but you never release it
because you're expecting to communicate
with somebody else.
So all that stuff in
356, it comes back up,
raise a condition,
deadlock avoidance and detection,
all of this sort of stuff that's in there,
which is why it's
one of the three references.
So yeah, so things kind of
got better out of here over time.
You know, hardware people were like,
this is the deal, you know,
the programmers are going to
have to go write code.
And then what happened over time?
Well, people developed
libraries so that programmers
should use those libraries so that
they didn't have to think about
the nuances of
actually paralyzing individual things,
which they should do.
I'm not arguing they should.
I wouldn't want to write my
actual real parallel code from scratch
if there's already an exam.
This is a standard.
Everybody's already figured it out.
This works.
But we should know, what
are the limitations of that thing?
How is it likely that it works?
That's what we're trying to do.
We're going to do some stuff on our own,
and then we'll use somebody else's
code to move the next thing.
We've got to do it our own,
but then use somebody else's
to get the perfect ideal performance
for the next thing.
That kind of makes sense.
All right.
So I always have the same way
I forget what time it is in here.
So let me just switch
the class over at 12.05, right?
12.05.
Climate modeling.
So yeah, that's a
classic example everybody can understand,
you know, because we all understand that.
Well, they're probably talking
about a climate model
in terms of, like, climate change here.
But there's that.
There's also literally trying to
predict the weather for tomorrow.
That's important.
Protein folding in terms of what
I do in, like, pharmaceutical research,
you know?
You know, back in the
day, right, what would people do?
I think this medicine will do something.
I don't know.
I grounded up in it
with a mortar and pestle,
and I gave it to people, and they died.
Okay.
Well, that's not good.
We use animals when they died.
So animals cause a certain
amount of breed and all this,
plus all the ethical issues out of
it and all this sort of stuff.
So what will we be better off doing?
Well, what about if we can
actually model the
chemicals in the computer?
We can model your biology in the computer.
Then part of that
scientific method of, like,
always having to
do some physical experiment.
You don't need to do that.
You can do the experiment, at least
some of it, on the computer, right?
You can say, hey, of
these thousand different drug molecules,
we think that these ten
are the most likely to succeed
because of the results we
got out of the computer program.
And then we go into, say, animal trials,
and then into human trials
and all this sort of stuff.
That's kind of the idea.
It's like a lot of the
stuff can be simulated in the computer,
whether that be drugs,
or whether it's weather,
or whether it's this or whether it's that.
There's all this sort of stuff.
So, yes, drug discovery, you know,
a lot of people are trying to work
very, very hard to
try to get fusion working.
You know, in a way that
it actually produces a lot more energy
that comes out that went in.
I mean, when I was a child, I'm 48
now, when I was
a kid in elementary school,
they were like, fusion, it's
only about five, ten years away.
It's always my entire life that it
has only been five or ten years away.
So I guess it's been
a bit longer than that.
Just a little bit.
I feel like they might
be getting closer with some stuff,
but that's still way off.
So this is a big problem right here.
Do you know why this is more
of a problem now than it's ever been?
Climate change.
So climate change is a problem?
Yeah?
The computer demands it's
like AI and algorithms.
That's right.
If you look at the percentage
of the total amount of energy
that the United States consumed,
it used to be a
few years ago that computers represented
like less than one-tenth of one percent.
Now it might represent two percent.
That's a gigantic increase.
Does that mean the United States is
using less energy to cool their houses?
No.
It just means that
we're using more energy altogether
and that fraction of it
from computing is going up.
These AI models, these computers here
that do these things right here,
like a computer that was bought
about two or three years ago
at the place that I did some arguments on,
bought a supercomputer that
had the highest thing,
the most expensive thing that
Nvidia had at the time.
And one rack, just
one rack, uses 500,000 watts.
500,000.
Now I want you to think
of it, and by the way,
you don't build a $200
million computer to not use it.
You better download the using it,
which means you're paying that
bill all the time, right?
You wouldn't buy a
Lamborghini and never drive it.
I mean, you might be scared to damage it,
but you're going to use it, right,
because the people that
spent the money are
going to expect you to use the thing.
Otherwise, why did you buy it, right?
So 500,000 is something that's
not the size of a refrigerator
or a little bit
taller than a regular refrigerator,
but let's say one and a
half times the size of a refrigerator.
Do you have any concept of
how much 500,000 watts really is?
Do you have any idea
how much watts it would be
if you turned on every
single thing in your house,
the heating and the air conditioning,
let's say you turn it on at the same time,
every element in the
stove, the dryer is on.
Let's say nothing's using
gas. It's all there is.
How would you figure that piece out?
Now let's assume you
don't have an electric car.
Let's just assume that you're saying
that it's just your standard stuff.
What do you figure?
If I put a kilowatt little
above, but it's not far off,
it's my off by order of magnitude,
you certainly don't use
50 kilowatts at home.
I guarantee you that
unless you're sharing your transformer
outside with other
people in the community,
the biggest transformer they would put
outside of your house is 25 kilowatts.
And that's rated at that maximum
assuming you're not running
25 kilowatts all the time.
If you were at 25 kilowatts all
the time, the thing
would start getting hot.
It's probably assuming you're
about 80% of that.
So if you look
at these whole home generators,
how much would you
need from your whole home?
Well the whole home means
you can turn everything on.
It's probably 15KW.
15,000 watts versus 500,000 watts.
How many homes is that?
Let's just say it was 10 kilowatts.
50 divided by 500 divided
by 10, that's 50 homes.
But it's probably more like 100 homes
because we're talking about you
maxing out, which never happens.
You're normally at like maybe
1 to 5 to 6 kilowatts.
Hopefully not between the hours of
3 and 6 here at least anymore.
But the thing is, I don't think
you quite understand how much that is.
So the ex-facility where
he built the ex-facility,
I think it's in Texas or somewhere,
they have these tractor trailers with
generators on the back of it
because the power company can't
provide the electricity to the company.
That's the thing specced
out at 500 megawatts.
So 500 million watts for a computer
that can serve better ads to
you and can do some AI stuff.
I mean it's really cold
stuff, it's a huge power thing.
You know how many watts
equivalent your brain basically is?
I don't know, I
think it's around 12 watts.
So from a performance perspective, we've
got a long way to go.
Stuff might be real fast.
It uses us as 12 watts to do
a lot more than the computer to do.
There's a lot more connection in your
head than there are in the computer,
but that's the way it is.
And of course that then trickles
down to the climate change problem
of like how the **** are we
providing all this
energy to these computers?
When I was growing up, nobody
cared how much did the computer use
because it was not a big deal.
The computer used less than a
single light bulb at that time.
The computer might have
been 50 watts, 100 watts.
They weren't any, fluorescent lights
were just a new thing.
Everybody had an incandescent light bulb
that was two to three hundred watts
spread all over the kitchen.
That's a lot more than your computer.
Never worry about it.
Don't turn the computer
on, you don't need to.
So anyway, data analysis, looking
at what your company's doing,
trying to understand what's going on,
trends, how to maximize the profit,
minimize extensives, all
this kind of stuff.
So yeah, this is that
thing we were talking about.
You know, these
smaller transistors they built,
meant that you could raise the clock rate
and that you could put more of
them in the same amount of space.
So you could pack more in.
But then faster process
meant there was more power.
And an increased power
meant there was more heat.
More heat meant that if you
can't take the heat out of it,
they become unreliable.
Like if you overclock your machine
and you can't keep the heat out,
then it won't work right.
It'll even burn up or it'll
crash because it'll eventually lock up
and something happens.
So they went into
using these various cores.
So we need to be
able to leverage these cores.
We need to figure out how
to write parallel programs to do it.
But we've always been
taught to do everything sequentially,
one step at a time.
We've got to unlearn that way of thinking.
You need to be starting to think
about how, what about the real problem,
the big picture in the problem, actually
has to be done one after another
and what can actually be
done at the same time.
And then how do I
write a program to capture that?
So, you know, this is the highest saying,
yep, you've got to
tighten the nested for loop.
There's something you've got to
do, like compute the next value.
Maybe you don't even have that.
You're literally just doing like some bus
equals the thing out of an array.
Imagine this was the problem
I was just giving you,
but this was just out of the array.
So there's a single loop like this,
but, you know, we could do the
thing that we were talking about in here,
which is, and let's see.
We can say, hey, all right.
If I'm core number, you know, I,
then I need to figure out what
my first element of the array is,
what my last element of the array is,
so that like, for example, if there
were two, let's say you use three cores,
you know, and this was index zero to two,
and this went from three to seven,
and then this one
went from eight to eleven,
and maybe decided to
divide it up that way,
so that means that
core zero is doing this,
core one is doing this,
core two is doing this.
That means that the for
loop has to be parameterized
so that the ith core will start on
the correct place inside
of this loop, right?
Does that make sense?
You kind of get that, right?
How do you calculate your
first and your last elements?
It's just some sort of arithmetic, right,
but essentially it's doing
that division for you, right?
So they kind of go through the same
kind of example that I just gave you,
so I'm not going to
worry about talking about that.
You know how we said after
the things were
finished calculating their subtotals,
somebody was going to have to add up?
That's what it is.
It says, cool, you did
all that stuff we just said.
Now, let's suppose that you had
the three cores we just mentioned,
and this core got
his subtotal down to two,
this one got it down to three,
this one got it down to four.
Now, let's say that this is
core zero, core one, core two.
They say, cool, who's going to
be responsible for
adding these subtotals up?
In this setting, they're using
the word the master core.
I think that's kind of
an old type of language,
but let's just say that it's
like the head core, all right?
So the head core here is like, cool.
If I know where these
other cores put their subtotals,
I could just go look
at memory and be like,
plus equals three, plus equals
four, and I've got the answer.
You know what I mean?
Like I said, that's cool.
So it's like, hey, everyone
else, if I'm the main guy,
if I'm this guy up here,
then I do my own work,
and if the other
people are doing their work,
and when they get
finished doing their work,
they send their information
back to this guy.
You know, so it's like
they're both all doing work,
and then this one sends
his information back to that guy,
and the way this code's written,
they both try to send their information
back to this guy at the same time.
Now, let's suppose that we were
using some kind
of interprocess communication
like that you learned about in 356.
There would be something there that
would keep and hold the buffers,
and something would deal with all this,
but, you know, you can
kind of essentially see that
this first core would be
engaged for some period of time
a little bit beyond when the
other people were engaged, all right?
They were doing their work, so a
lot of them were doing work here,
and then at the end,
sending one item, sending one item,
waiting for those things to be received,
add up the other two
subtotals to get an answer.
Does that make sense?
You don't really need to send
anything to anybody in a computer
that's in a single computer
that has to share memory,
because you didn't see it in RAM.
Now, as we learned about it in 356,
we have a virtual
memory manager that makes it
so it seems like everybody's
got their own RAM, right?
But there's things called shared memory.
You can make it so your
processes can share the same memory space.
In fact, what is the
simplest way to have multiple processes
I'm using that because it's
not a process I'm thinking about
all be able to see the
same RAM at the same time.
What did you learn about in
356 that on a single computer
lets all of those things
see the same memory space?
It was a thread, right?
But if you have a single
process with multiple threads in it,
those threads can all be
executing things at the same time,
and they can all see the entire
memory of all of the other threads.
Now, individual processes could
not see each other's RAM,
which is why you guys probably
did things like sockets and pipes
and other things to send
stuff from one process to another
because they couldn't
see each other's RAM.
And that is certainly what we're going
to do when we're in this situation,
because if this guy
can't see this guy's RAM,
the only way to do it
is to send and receive messages
or pay an astronomical amount
to have a fancy network
that makes that not necessary,
but still, at scale, eventually,
maybe everything in this rack
can see each other's memory,
but these two racks
next to each other can't.
There's always going to be a scale problem
that not every processor
can see every other processor.
And you know why that
is? You can think about it.
If there's a billion cores,
they can't all be sending
or receiving billions
of things simultaneously,
trying to get things from
everybody's memory at the same time
because that's going
to slow everything down.
There has to be some kind of coordination.
There's going to be some
bottleneck that will happen, right?
So where is that bottleneck?
It depends. It changes over time.
It's like the little things that
pop up at the amusement park.
You try to hit this thing down,
some other thing comes
up over here, right?
And that's the way bottlenecks are.
You never get rid of
the bottleneck, by the way.
You just fix this bottleneck and
then something else
becomes the new bottleneck
because the bottleneck
is the weakest place.
There's always going to be
a place that's not quite right.
It's not quite balanced, right? So
that's what you're trying to do.
So they're just kind of saying, hey,
even if you get
the partial answers computed,
somebody's going to have to
get the answers back together.
And if it was something stupid
like adding numbers up, guess what?
Most of the time it's
not something stupid like that.
But they're using that
as a motivating factor
here just to kind of talk to you.
You're going to have to
orchestrate after the main problem's over
how do people actually decide
who's doing the last little pieces?
I mean, that's a concern.
So they've got to go
through a global sum thing here
and imagine that like we've been
doing, we've got like, say, eight decors
and they've all computed their
partial sums here, all right?
And we know that the global sum
is the sum of all the partial sums.
And they're kind of saying, how
do we go about doing that?
We want that when we're all done,
you know, we want the, in this case,
maybe the head of the core
is identified as the core zero,
we want them to
have the final answer here.
Now, you might want everybody to
know what the final answer is.
That's also a possibility.
Say, whatever the next
step in the program,
everyone needs to know what
the previous total sum was.
Well, then, after this is computed, maybe
they need to go then send this out
to everybody else.
But you can see that
this would kind of get problematic.
Say there's a thousand threads,
you know, a thousand processes.
I mean, how do you get some issues?
How do you start getting
into how the shared catch becomes?
That becomes a big problem.
And it also becomes a big problem of,
like, a lot of different things, you know.
So, we're just trying to start out, right?
We're just trying to
understand what's going on.
So, say, hey, you know,
don't let one core have
to do all that work at the end, you know.
How we could share that extra
work by doing it like this.
So, they do something like this.
They say, like, what we said
a minute ago, which isn't cool.
Core one sends this stuff to core zero.
And they add that partial
sum at the same time now.
So, this all happens at the same time.
Everybody computes their partial
sum at the same time.
So, I want you to think about it.
This takes some T1 amount of time to do.
And then this little, this one
is sending from here to here.
This one is sending over here.
So, they add it.
He doesn't have to send anywhere
because they already have their own answer
from the previous thing.
So, one value
is being sent simultaneously.
And notice, when you
divide the problem like this,
no one is sending to the
same people at the same time.
You see that?
This, in this case, this is
the sender and he's a receiver.
Sender, receiver.
And they don't overlap.
Now, that thing that
the previous guy were like,
everybody sent that back to the master.
That would cause, if
there were a thousand processes,
the master processes would have to be
like trying to receive all this stuff.
That would be congestion, right?
But right there, a hundred thousand.
So, but anyway, this,
this helps with that problem.
So, then this takes some amount of time.
Let's call it T2.
This takes some amount of time, T3.
And then finally, T4.
So, you know, if there
were n things over here,
the amount of time it
took to do T1, you know,
is probably something on the
order of whatever n is
divided by the number
of processes that there are.
But now, this is constant.
That is constant.
This is constant, but the
depth of this is not constant.
The depth of this thing is
some sort of tree thing, right?
So, that, what's the depth of that?
Now, that's based on the
log of the number of processes
that there are, probably the
ceiling function of it here.
So, the total time it took
is n over p plus this.
See, computation, communication.
Now, you may say, wait a minute.
Now, that's not fair
to call that communication,
because they were sending and adding.
Well, guess what?
What do you think
takes longer in a computer,
to add two numbers or to send something
from one place to another?
Sending is way worse.
Communication is always
worse than computation.
So, yes, it's log p plus one addition.
But the community, that just changes
this coefficient over here.
So, did you kind of see how that is?
It says there's going to be computation,
there's going to be communication,
and they're both going to have costs.
But it's going to
have their own strategies
for how to do that, right?
All right.
So, when you start
getting that whole board latency
becomes a major deal
in that form of computer.
Yeah, I mean, you guys took 270, right?
So, in 270, in networking,
you guys have an equation that says,
what is the time it takes to send a file?
All right.
Well, so it's whatever
its size is in megabytes,
say, divided by the
bandwidth in megabytes per second,
plus whatever the latency
is in the network.
Well, this could be extremely fast,
and this could even be small.
But every time you do a communication,
you have to pay a
fixed penalty for this latency.
It adds up.
Just adds up.
You know, so, yeah,
these networks I'm
talking about over here,
you need to be ultra-high bandwidth,
so you need that number
to be as big as possible.
You need this number to
be as small as possible,
so that when you add them together,
the time is the smallest
possible thing that it could be.
So, latency and bandwidth are
going to come up a lot
over and over again in here.
And the difference
between latency and bandwidth,
something could be 100 megabytes a second,
but what about if there
are 100 gigabytes a second?
But let's say the latency was 10 minutes.
Like this.
Less opposed.
So I was driving a 12 passenger van,
and you guys were going
to go to the beach.
That's a lot better
than somebody riding a motorcycle
over to the beach to get over there.
The bandwidth in the motorcycle
was one, maybe two people.
A 12 passenger van has
got a lot of people.
But how long has it
taken to drive to the beach?
Well, if it's in the middle of the day,
like it's been recently for me,
it takes a long time to get there.
That latency, it doesn't matter how
many people are in the car.
Sure, they all get over there,
but it took a long time
to get there once they sawed it.
So same thing.
Things like Ethernet that
we're all commonly using,
it's a latency.
It's awful.
It's god-awful.
So you don't ever see real computers
connected together with Ethernet.
And obviously not wireless.
Wireless is awful
with respect to throughput.
It's usually fiber-optic.
Well, so fiber-optic refers
to the physical media.
So for example, you can have Ethernet
that runs over fiber-optic cables.
So the media, whether it's fiber-optics,
whether it's copper wires,
that has to do with the physical layer.
But a lot of this also
has to do with the combination
of physical layer and
the protocol layer and stuff.
You know how they...
What do they call that?
The OSI network layer, the seven layer,
blah, blah, blah, blah.
I'm not a big networking person,
but I know that those
kind of things factor in there.
So anyway, what do you
need to do right now,
between now and the next time?
You need to get the book.
Okay, whatever that first book was,
this one right here,
if you got listed there,
you need to find it.
And it was listed as like the book
that we're supposed to
be using for the class.
So I see that it's
with my bookstore or whatever.
It's all in there.
But definitely get that book.
Definitely get the Pachinko text.
Whether it's electronic, physical,
grip-ball from the internet,
whatever it is, get it.
It's not like xi-books, you know,
where you have to have xi-books, right?
Because I want to
have silence in xi-books.
There's not going to
be any assignments in Pachinko
like where it's going
to be integrated into Moodle.
There might be an assignment out of it,
but it doesn't matter whether
you have a picture copy
or electronic copy or this or that.
You get what I'm
saying, where it's like xi-books,
like you wouldn't matter if
you had a paper book,
it'd be irrelevant.
You'd have to have
the electronic version of it.
That's kind of what I'm trying to say.
Get it however you think is the best
versus the cost or whatever.
What's the other thing?
Hopefully, Trump's network will improve
as the day goes on.
And I'll be able to
get the 200-megabyte zip file
that has all of our slides and code
and all that stuff in it.
But I also want you to go ahead,
and if you don't
already have a CI account,
you need to have one of these accounts.
And we're not going to be using the CI...
How many of you are
familiar with the CI project here?
Like ci.coastal.edu?
Cool.
That's most people.
You need to be able to access that thing.
Do you guys not
know, don't have an account,
don't know how to get into it?
Good.
Well, I'm not saying this.
Make sure you can log in, all right?
Because the Git repo that
I use for the class
is at code.coastal.edu,
which uses the same
authentication as the CI project,
which is not
necessarily your coastal stuff
unless you have with a
set of passwords the same way.
So we won't really be using that really
for actual or actual parallel programs,
because we're going to be using our laptop
and do a little bit of it.
And then we're going
to be using a supercomputer
that we have in California.
We have like a billion
processor hours or something on it.
So we're going to start next time
with the programming stuff
from this potential book
that shows how to use the threads
to do this global sum problem.
We're going to actually run it.
We're going to talk about it.
And the thing that
you'll see about this book
that's kind of cool is
the author will do like this.
Hey, here's a draft one of
how you expect to maybe do this.
And you run it.
It may or may not even work.
If it doesn't work, you're like, why?
If it works, then it'll say,
cool, like, how long did it take?
Do you see any problems with this thing?
And then it'll be like,
okay, now here's version two.
It's slightly better.
Here's version three.
Please kind of make sure
that you grab the stuff
so that we're going over it.
You know, you have the stuff.
If you want to be looking
at it while you're in here,
you can actually see the code.
You can run it while we're in here.
There's not going to be
any requirement that you have that.
If your battery doesn't
last on your computer,
it doesn't matter.
We won't have to do that.
But if you wanted to have that
stuff, you could play with it live
and ask questions or something.
And assuming that this
video is recording correctly,
you can expect these to
all be in Moodle, also accessible.
And I'll generally put like a
summary of what we discussed each day
with each video so that you can go
back and remember what was in each video.
I shouldn't have to do that
because I assume it's audio captioning
and then I'll be able to say,
take all those captions
and write a summary.
But I don't know who
else does that or not.
Anyway, take care, have a good
one, and I'll see you next time.
And if there are
any of these extra syllabus,
bring them up here and I'll
throw them in on a book site.
Sorry, I missed your email.
Oh, dude, it's okay.
I thought it was kind
of like a global thing.
Like you sent it to everybody?
No, I only sent it
to like a handful of people.
Like I asked for
recommendations from faculty and staff
and math and computer science and said,
who do you recommend?
Would you do the look at this stuff?
And your name was in there.
So I sent out like an
email to like maybe eight people.
Right.
That's too expensive.
And two people showed up.
I'm not opposed to whatever.
I'm like, there's
no interviews that happen.
There's no job or thing.
But I went and had an information
session where I described
what the job was.
So the job is probably something like 10,
15 hours a week and 90 dollars an hour.
Only one meeting
a week, virtually synchronously,
where we have to know
all the people in the silos.
The press is where you get it done.
We saw a problem that has to do with
looking at how file system
trees are changing over time.
And it was a metric.
And a bunch of like automatically
generated trees to
create patterns and metrics
that you could then train, machine
learning around to do some stuff.
So that's what it was about.
Was it over the summer type of thing?
No, it was lit.
Sorry.
I did the information session Tuesday.
And I'm hoping it will
come the next week or so.
I'm going to hire somebody to
start working on orders for this semester.
Possibly both semesters if things go well.
I'll take a look at it and see.
Yes, please.
Take a look at it and see what you think.
There's an English description in
there about what the job is.
I want to tell you,
I can't see the syllabus.
It might be like
a separate honors Google page.
That's a good one.
Yep, that's exactly what it is.
Send me an email.
Remind me and I'll get
them charged for two sections together.
Oh, okay.
Sounds good.
Sir, how do you do?
Sir, just add some items
to track the level of course.
And it's the first day.
Is that going to be helpful?
I already have links on the level.
Yeah, it is good.
How many minutes on there will be good?
How many quarters do you have?
It's an older one, so it's got a paper.
That's good.
That's good enough for just playing around
and then making sure your code works.
And then we can copy it up to the server
and run it at a
scale there, like 128 threads
or whatever it is, that sort of thing.
Probably still getting
more accuracy at home
because the processor on
my computer at home
is 60.
I remember you were talking about that.
Hopefully it's not that accurate.
Hopefully we get the
same answer either way.
I mean, I have any processors
that probably would be better accuracy.
Well, when I think of accuracy, I
think of like the sum of those numbers,
they'd better be the same size
of the computer I'm running on.
Oh, yeah.
Anyway, have a good one, man.
Chris, what's going on?
Not much.
Definitely interesting to kind of take
a look at the trade-off between like
how you can balance
the decreased effects on performance
negatively of memory transfers and then
the speed-up given
more experimental errors.
I mean, think about it.
Like if you've only got one
RAM memory bank on the computer,
and if there's more cores, that means
they're all trying to read and write
for memory at the same time.
So, yeah, you might.
I mean, there will be
a limit to how many threads.
I mean, how many cores you
can even have on your computer,
not because of making the processors,
but literally because they can't build
a memory infrastructure that
you can interact with.
Because your cores are over here, right?
Yeah.
And your RAM is over here.
You know, just that physical existence
of light stuff is a problem.
Now, that's why we're also building chips
where the entire RAM is something right
on top of this.
Yeah, yeah.
Oh, I see.
Yeah.
So-called hot-down memory.
But guess what?
If you look at that, it's not as
big as the RAM that gets in there.
And also, sometimes it suffers from other
kinds of problems like failures and stuff.
Because think about it.
If your RAM fails, maybe you do.
You just pop one out
and put another one in.
If your CPU fails, that's a lot more
of an expensive thing
than typically RAM is,
right?
Right.
Because it's physically
connected to the board.
Yeah, like this RAM
fan just messes up here.
Well, that whole thing is garbage.
Whereas one of these 16 DIMMs goes bad.
That's not a big deal.
But imagine like, let's suppose
that once every five years,
one DIMM goes bad, man.
You've got a couple of thousand weathers.
100,000 DIMMs spread out
all over the data center.
On average, how many
DIMMs are breaking per day?
Just think about it.
If one has a failure
rate of less than five years,
what does the whole data
center have a failure rate of?
So imagine like how many people you'd
have to have walking around in there,
trying to just replace the DIMMs.
Or you just don't worry about it.
Maybe it's not even
worth trying to replace.
If you're a Google and this thing
right here is some kind of modding thing
because it's like $200 bucks,
at some point you're
like, all right, through it.
I'm just going to throw this
out, plug it up in there.
I mean, I'm serious.
Like, sometimes they run
their data centers hot.
Like, they don't care if stuff fails.
Because they've written their stuff in
a way that it's got immediate failover.
It's like it's...
That's just easy to over this.
Like, whereas that would be a
problem if one of the computers failed
while the node was running a job,
did that job now and totally jacked up.
But if one of Google's servers fails
while one person happens to
be doing a Google search,
it just doesn't page them.
They just hit load,
and then they're not there.
Load distribution thing just moves it
to a certain number of deals.
Or if you try to get your email,
it's not a big deal.
If you have a job that's,
for example, maybe it's not parallelizable
because it's like a physics simulation,
it has to run from something.
If your node creates a
stream, it will run from something.
And it's running from, which is
why they check to get around it.
Yeah, I think we talked
about check one, all right?