I can turn around and write Cindy which is
the okay like she's the first of the pair
like I've been communicating
with her about in
one other case for a student in here about
something that was messed up
so we'll see what she
says all right I'm going
to go try to figure out
all right sounds good man
all right have a good day
yeah
let's go ahead and
spread out here and we're
going to do the quiz here we get the class
those close book close
notes and double earbuds
and star watches and
phones put all that stuff
away all you need a pencil and or pen or
whatever you typically write all
right so this will be 15
minutes there's space to
write your stuff when
you're done um just
put your thing face out
and there you go we'll
start the counter once I
get all these in there's
extra just leave it on
yes to the back
you're going to get started
15 minutes start now you
got about six minutes left
and again if you finish
just turn your paper over
all right about one minute left
make sure you're
finishing up your thoughts
is that you paid your name's on the top of
the paper all right um
good put your pencils down
and uh pass your stuff over here
in front so you'll feel good about this
everybody so how do you feel like at least
uh 50 okay all right
so here's some extra copies
okay
Flynn's taxonomy let's see who feels like
I know this okay all right so
you know we know that we've got we've got
this thing about whether or
not we're doing the same
instructions on different
pieces of data or
different instructions on
the same pieces of
data or or both at the same time
so we have like
single instruction single data
single instruction multiple
data multiple instructions
we have single data and then
like multiple instructions multiple
data and I said
that we probably weren't
going to talk about
Indian and out this
is like your typical program
that you you guys write
all the time like you
and you can see a little y plus z you
know you're doing you know
to do addition for example you
got to have at least
two operands right so add
together so that's as like
single as you can get
versus say like add
two vectors together that'll
be multiple pieces of
data being added together
at the same time okay like this over here
but you know some kind
of thing with quadrants some
kind of thing that's kind
of what I was looking
for two uh two examples
of ILD you know there
are more than two but like what are the
two that we primarily talked
about in here pipelining okay
multiple issue sometimes referred
to as a super scalar
but you know I use the word multiple issue
in here okay well what is cache coherency
and consistency all about
like what's the main
issue there yeah like you got you know a
situation where in your memory
hierarchy you might have say
the cache here the cache here and so like
for example if you got
like the x25 over here
and then this uh your cpu reads it up so
you got like x25 and
this guy reads it like x25
but then all of a sudden x equals x
plus one over here this
becomes six but now like
it's not the same here and the cache is
also not the same here
although that's a different issue
but the main issue is
it's like it's not the
same so like if the
other dude is playing with the
value five that's not
the right one anymore so
trying to keep that
still consistent or have some
policy like hey if it's
a variable that's going to
be shared you can't cache
it up because you know
that's one way to avoid
the problem is just to
ignore it and be like
you can't you just can't
share any things or something
you know that might be
in common um but that
was the stuff that we were
talking about last time was that you got
multiple caches each you
know associated say with like
different cores or whatever and uh there
could be an inconsistency
between the things here
and that was what the slew be uh
a directory based cache
awareness protocol from uh the
chapter two was talking about that
was part of the reading assignment
uh message passing because message passing
primarily used in a shared memory system
or in a distributed
memory system live okay primarily
thoughts can we draw a picture of
shared memory machine this is a computer
it's got a processor
and another processor and
it's got a ram
that's this is shared memory
distributed memory would be
got a computer it's
got a processor and
ram got another computer
it's got a processor and ram and
they're both connected
together via a network
now which one of these is going to need to
pass messages in order to
be able to share stuff
distributed do you need
do you have to send
messages here no because
uh this guy can see
the ram and this guy can see the ram they
don't need to share it
with each other it's already
in a system that's
physically one system it could
be shared does that mean
that you can't put uh
what do you call it that you say come on
in but you can't put
um message passing on here
no you could in fact that's what we did in
any class right we ran
that hello world program we
logged in one node and ran it right you
know that's how i stand
all right this thing's gonna
come out here send
the message to the other
process it's gonna come back
up out of the loop
back interface the network card come back
up here and
they're they're sharing information
but they don't actually
need to share information this
way what was up so they don't they don't
need to share information
because they they could see
it directly but you could
you could put it on
there but in terms
of primarily message passing
is when it has
to traverse the network because
this processor can't normally
see this memory and that
processor can't see this
memory so they have to
share messages or if you're
on a similar computer like
you did in 356 probably
and you had say for
example processes and
you had multiple processes
that don't share
memory those processes communicate
with each other through channels like
pipes or other
kinds of inter-process communication
that's because they
weren't sharing this memory
even though it's on the physical system
questions about that one
all right and finally there's
one at the end all right so we've got a
program that takes 100
seconds to run so let's
write that down you have a program it runs
and it takes 100 seconds so that's in book
notation that's the time it
takes to run on one
is 100 seconds and it says 80 percent of
that time is spent doing
work that could be paralyzed
all right so so you know in this case
you know 80 percent of 100 is 80 seconds
and then so that means we've got
20 percent of 100 is 20 seconds
that's spent doing work
going on that's purely
serial like it can't be done in parallel
and there's no overhead now in the
reading assignment that's stuck
in the book like
they talk about overhead terms you know
i'm saying unless you're
not worried about that
because we didn't really
talk about overhead terms in
here so if we just threw that out we just
talked about well it's that
after your question is how
much time would it take
to run the job with
four processes or
processes or something so
we're asking the question
time on four devices
what do we got all
right so let's let's uh let's
look at this 80 seconds
to the part that can be
parallelized so you're going
to be dividing that
by four because that's
the 80 that we're talking
about right so that 80 seconds hopefully
we're going to perfectly divide it up
among the four processes
and instead of taking 80
seconds it's going to
be four times faster for
that one thing and take
only 20 seconds to do plus
this part of it here
you still got to do it
anyway like it doesn't
matter that you parallelize
the other stuff you
can't parallelize that one
so that's 20 seconds left so we
get 80 divided by four it's what
20 plus 20 it's 40 is that
right ideally now if there was a
overhead would you expect that numbers
to be larger or smaller than 40
exactly it's not going to be as good if
there's overhead like we're
talking about it's not even
will be that good but
like this is the work
that can be parallelized that
means that you can break
it up into four chunks
and instead of doing those
four chunks one at a
time 20 seconds to 20 seconds
20 seconds and 20
seconds they're all being done
at the same time 20
seconds 20 seconds 20 seconds
and 20 seconds so
time starts here 20 seconds
passes all of that work
that took 80 seconds to
done it's happening at
the same time so it's
t-axis and then after that
somebody I don't know who
but somebody's going to
have to do the other
work this 20 seconds and so for a total of
40 seconds of total amount of time because
that's the idea instead
of doing the whole thing
one after another you're
doing a fourth of the
work one guy's doing
fourth of the work fourth
of the work fourth of the work and
then those are all done at the same time
so that would be this thing here now
what is the speed
up obtained by doing that
now the speed up on
p processes is the time it
took on one divided by
the time it took on p
processes in this case
we're talking about what is
the speed up on four
of them well that's the
time on one divided by
the time on four so we
plug that time on four into
here the time on one is
the things we started with so we did a
hundred over 40 and then
you know whatever symbol you
simplified that down I'll
accept that you know but
if you had simplified
this thing down I would
have questions about that
okay then what is
the efficiency of this
so they talked about efficiency
in the book you know you remember the
equation for efficiency in
general exactly the efficiency
on p processors is equal to the speed up
on p processors divided by
p but now the speed
up on p processors is
t one over tp divided by
p that's p over one
so that's the same thing as
t one over tp times the reciprocal of
the denominator which would be one over p
so that should be equal to t one all over
p times tp right all
right now in this particular case
what is the speed up on four it's a
hundred over 40 divided by
or excuse me that's that
and so then the efficiency on four is the
speed up on four so a hundred over 40
all over a number of
processes what would that be
for you know so just so that I could tell
this that whole thing about about that or
you know whatever kind
of manipulation you might have
done or whatever that's
kind of what you've
got does that make
sense well that number b
greater than or less than one when
we get out we get done with it
less than one because
one means a hundred percent
you know is it ever
going to be 100 efficient
no what about this one what is
the minimum theoretical runtime
that could be obtained
if you had an infinite number of processes
what's the amount of time that it takes
well the time on p processes equals to the
time you spent doing
parallelizable work which was 80
seconds divided by you
have infinite p processes
plus the part that
you can't do anything about
20 for the 20 seconds but now we said what
about now if p goes
to infinity of this thing
is as limited as this thing goes
to infinity so this term becomes what
zero so this becomes what is it 20 seconds
so the minimum amount of
time that you could possibly
do this is 20 seconds
that would mean that all
of this got done so
quickly because it was being done
you know little train amount
on it on a boat
on the processes is it
really the only thing that's
left is this to 20 seconds so what is
the maximum speed up that
you could have ever gotten
speed up max right
just imagine the speed up
well this will get a
minimum amount of time so
that's the time on one
divided by the time
on infinity all right well
time of infinity is 20
seconds so this was originally
about 100 divided by 20 which is 5x so
you're never going to make
this thing any faster than
five times faster even
if you have an infinite
number of processes working on
it as you get 5x
so for example if that set
of 100 seconds was 100 years
well the most you'd ever be able to do is
five times better which is
still going to be 20 years
right i mean so like
you didn't have a trillion
cores you know i mean
that's kind of a sad set
of affairs and i kind
of like the same thing
she got going on with
your grades say for example
you know it's like you say there was
only two things with your grades there was
stuff that you did in
class and stuff you did
out of class you know
and you just you know make
amazingly and stuff that
you do out of class
doesn't matter how much you
do on that if you
can't do this and stuff in class there's
a big weight associated
with it and that's what's
happening here this is
a big weight but that's
also a big weight
because you'll never be able
to do anything about that
part so this is very big
at all even if this
was say 99 and 1 percent
how much faster that
can something theoretically be
that was divided up 99 and 1 percent
well let's just let's
just write it down let's
say we had that same problem 99 and 1
all right cool so time on one is still
100 seconds but 99
seconds of that instead doing
something that's parallelizable
one second is
spent doing something
that's not parallelizable
all right so the time on infinite
number of processes would
make this go away
but you still have this
so this would be one
second and the time on one is equal to 100
so the speed up on
an infinite number of processes
would be 100 divided by
one which is 100x it's
only a hundred times faster does that make
sense that's not great
because you would hope right
if you had a
million processors it would be
a million times faster
but that ain't the case
not unless this is practically zero
and unfortunately this is never zero
in fact it's a
lot worse than that normally
plus the community the
overhead they term they talked
about that keeps this from going away that
overhead makes instead of
this thing going away
to zero it'll it'll start going down to
some minimum amount and
then it'll start going up
and when that happens the speed up just
goes to garbage after
that that's that's what happens
any questions about this
all right cool so
i'll get those graded and
we'll be back to you guys by next time
how many people were able to run
a hello world program on the machine
and what challenge is it any did
you experience loading modules
loading modules because by
default are the MPI compilers
in your path when you
first start no okay so
let's go look at a real
problem to try to solve here chapter three
was the MPI chapter go over here slideshow
world we did all this sort of stuff
let's talk about a
couple of things here just
as we as we go we got through this
let me turn this slide off so you can
contrast this a little
bit not quite as bad
as you probably saw there are a lot of
different MPI C compilers that
want to use it there's
some by open MP there are some that are
by Ohio State University
like all in back pitch
there's some by the
original standard called in
pitch there's a bunch
of different flavors of
these things but if they're compliant with
the standard that's the
part that you're you're
send it'll work like the MPI send that
you would expect logically
from any of these implementations
right the no words it'll match the API
now behind that API
how it actually works underneath
right the implementation of it
now that might be way different
if you're going to try
to debug a C program
and you're going to have
it where you know you need
to be able to look at stuff and look at
stack traces of stuff and
actually use like a debugger
on it or use some
tools like valgrind on it or
any of those kind of
things you want to dash g
to be turned on
so the debugging information will
be inside the binary so
that when you run it
it'll come out and
be like this line number
or this line drop
number versus some memory address
because it's like memory
address 0x af cf 4df
you're like what the hell
does that even mean like
i don't know where that was at so you want
one debugging turned on so
it turns on all warnings
that's not really true
there are some warnings
that this doesn't turn
on but in general this
this is a good idea i always have your
warnings on because here's
the thing those warnings are
about things that say
hey at compile time the
compiler's like are you
sure this is really what
you mean is that really what you want to
do because remember C unless
you do all kinds of
stuff that might not be
what you really want to
do so i i try
to never compile anything and see
without the warnings turned
on because otherwise i won't
know what's going on and then the name of
your all your pieces here um so we run
our processes we played
around with this last time
you know you include your
header file at the top
we talked about how the
very first MPI call that
you do in your in your program needs to
be MPI init that
initializes the environment but notice
the two arguments to get passed to MPI
init an integer pointer
which is the argument count
pointer you know how like
when you when you run
a C program from the
command line you can actually
pass parameters to the
C program from the command
line right if you pass
say like three of them
then what we're saying is you need to
pass the address to
that integer into this thing
if for example there's
another piece of stuff that
it's going to do
to manipulate some of these
things what about if that parameter at
the command line
means something that specific
that you wanted the I to do or these
sorts of things and
then finally remember there's an
argument vector in C the
two the two things to
name right the count as
well as the array of
character arrays you know
so in other words an
array of strings that come
in and the reason it's
got three stars here
is because it's the address
of the char star
star that normally comes in
that way the MPI
environment can actually edit
these two things by
reference instead of indicating
a copy of the address it gets the
address of an address
and can manipulate it directly
go override it it
can change things and things
like that and then the
very last MPI call that
you need to do can't
do any MPI after that is
you need to do MPI
finalize now can there be some
stuff in your C program prior to this yes
but it shouldn't involve
you shouldn't involve MPI okay
you know so notice how that's what they do
in your main program
you got the argument account
and the array of argument vector of
argument strings they're passing
the address of it
so in this case this first argument here
is an integer star
so integer pointer because the
original thing was an
integer so if you take
a pointer of it the
address of it because an
n star this one was
originally an n star star
this star plus the fact
that it's an array is
n star star so when
you take the address of
it it becomes a char
star star star which is what
this thing's about i'm just trying to make
sure we're all seeing
that the prototypes match like
the types actually match
the stuff that's going
into and out of
these functions because that's
going to be a thing that's going to hit
us repeatedly with these
MPI calls is that they're
all buffer based which
means they're all array
based and since everything
in C that's an array
is a pointer then you've got pointers
with pointers or possibly
other pointers and all
this kind of stuff going on for right now
the only communicator we
worry about is the impact
common world and remember
the processes like if
you start with 10
processes they'll be numbered
not zero through nine
and they're all members of
this this group if
you will this this communicator
later on if and when we even get
to it we might
do something with other communicators
so how do you
determine how many processes were
started now you might go
like well now wait a
minute i can figure that
out right i can figure
it out because my program
i could i could pass it
the number of uh command
line i could say let
me pass to my C
program the number of processes
i want to start with and i could read it
out of there and i
could convert that ASCII text into
integer using A to I and then i could do
that that's true but you
don't need to do that because
this thing right here is doing that for
you because at the command line you type
MPI run dash MP you know say 10 space
dot slash your program now
if you pass additional parameters
over here you don't need to pass it
the number of processes
that you're launching because
the in this this is actually not even a
binary this is a
script that does some stuff
in the background and it's grabbing this
10 and starting 10 copies of this program
with 10 copies of
what these parameters are
and that has already been passed over here
you don't want to pass
it over there because then if
you do that what about
if you don't have a match
like one of you said 10 does such as nine
that's 10 to say you don't need to do that
so how would you see program actually know
how many processes it
has been started with
you might think hey i
would i would use this to
pass it up and i
put like 10 right here but
you don't need to
do that because after you're
doing MPI init you
can call this function MPI
com size to find out what MP was when it
was started does that make
sense now you it's like
the size of what well the size of the
communicator what communicator MPI com
world now you might say
well now all right now looking at a c c
thing it's got two it's
got two parameters going into it
the communicator and an int star and it's
returning an int well if i'm trying to get
the size of a
communicator why doesn't it just
return that as an
int well because that's not
how return values are
often used in c return
values are often used
in c to indicate what
the error code is so that means if you
want to actually return
something from a c function
that doesn't come out
by a return statement
and none of these
MPI things return things through
the return value that's
the thing you're looking for
like in this case that
won't be the size of
the communicator that's not
what's being returned it's some
kind of error code zero or non zero or
whatever else how do you
do that well you pass
it by reference pass it
by pointer so you pass a
pointer to a variable
that's handmade the calling
function stack and pass
the address of it just
like in 210 right pass
the address of a variable
that's on the stack and
that address can be used
and directly written in
here and overwritten by this
function and you can do that right so like
that's what's happening let's
go look at a little
example here of the
hello world program they have
notice how in this this thing they do an
MPI knit they don't pass
anything for the command line
because apparently there's
nothing kind of an
entry command line
because everything's like hard
coded up here in the program all right and
it's like when your program
starts it doesn't know how
many processes it's working with
so it has to ask
the question what is the
size of the group i'm in
what group am i
in everybody's in the common
world so if you have an integer notice how
integer hasn't even initialized
here this this rank
but it doesn't have to be because it's not
going to be read from before it's written
to you remember you
don't have to initialize variables
that are written to
before they're read from
because if you don't
read from them you don't
need to doesn't matter
even just garbage it
doesn't matter what strategy
is that's not great
programming practice but it
doesn't matter so you pass
the address of my rank to it and so after
you call this if if
if it hadn't started with
say dash np 10 then
the value of my rank and
my concise will be with
respect to those things so the
the concise would be 10
at my rank if i happen
to be number three then
it'll be number three out
of that 10 does that
make sense so anytime you
need to modify something
then you have to pass
the address of the
things you're trying to modify
but that makes sense
that's why that's happening that
way so let's go back
there's that rank so you pass it an
integer variable that represents
that process is right
because if you start
taking in processes that's
where like in this case four of them
that means that there
are four main programs running
and so there'll be my rank here my rank
there my rank there's four copies of my
rank in four different
processes those processes might be
on the same computer they might be on
different computers in distributed
sense and so on every
one when everyone starts
they're going to have
a different rank hopefully
right they're going to
have the rank correspond
to them like if it
was the size of the
communicator was 10 then the
ranks would be zero to nine right
something like that so
that's what's happening there
you just have to remember that when
you're thinking about this
even though your program
might you're looking at
the lines of code and
you look at the code
and you see there's one
you said up here there's just one in each
program that's running but there
are copies of every one
of those programs running
does that make sense
you have to start
thinking about the fact that
it's running in parallel at the same
time so influence taxonomy
instead of this and
you know single instruction
it's like single program
multiple data so let's say that spin d
okay we're only compiling
one program how do
we make those different
programs do things that are
different which is the same exact code how
would they ever execute
anything differently they have
to do it based on what the rank is but you
could literally write a program
like if my rank is this
i'll do this else if
my rank is this i'll do
that else if it's my
rank is this do this now
that that's going to
get cumbersome because if you
don't know how many
ranks you're going to run
you can't have a
if an else statement that's
like 150,000 blocks long
right so you have to
kind of figure out like how am i divide
the work maybe on the
work divide the work equally
maybe there's going to
be one person in charge
one process and that's
maybe that range zero maybe
and everyone else is
doing everything else does that
make sense like you have
to figure out how to
divide the work of and
how would you know that
you would have to know
how what data you're working
how big that data is how many of you are
there and which piece of
work is it that you're doing
based on your rank out of all the ranks
that's what's happening so we
talked about how to send
something to other data
so there's the parameters
to it and remember
when you're talking about
the size of the message that's not the the
total length in bytes
it's the length in items
so for example if
the data type you're dealing
with are flows and each
one of those flows is
say 16 or 32 bits or whatever it is then
the total number of bytes
would be equal to that
number multiplied by the
size of that data type
so you know how to
be umalic something and see
umalic things based on
the total number of bytes
that there are but
over here you're not saying
the total number of
bytes you're saying the number
of elements in this
thing multiplied by the size
of each element that's
actually the total amount of
data that's getting ready
to be sent which means
then of course that
that buffer it better damn
will be at least that
long because if it's not
what are you going to
get what do you think
would happen if say your
array had three elements in it
and that was going to
be called my buffer so
the buffer points to this
thing and I say hey
I'm going to send
three elements and the data
type is int let's
say that this buffer really
was an int array like
it was over here I was
like you know int buffer
four so you pass it buffer
which is a pointer to the thing that
we're dealing with they're
going to send three things
and each one of
size managers typically four
bytes all right so
this whole thing would be
four times four is equal
to 16 bytes uh you're
gonna send three of them
okay cool so it would
use this it would send
those three who would send
the last one you know
what about if you said I
want to send two of them I'll send this so
what about if you accidentally
said five well it's in
five it's not going to
check because remember the length
of an array in c you have to keep track
of there's you can't say like a buffer
size I thought there
were there's a runtime checking
like there might be in
python or c or something
where you can see if
there is it's too short
so if you accidentally
put five here it will
send these first four
and then it will overflow
this array bounds and
go into the next four
bytes of memory and
god knows what's in that
location in fact that might not even be in
your memory space if it's
not you'll get a segmentation
fault however if you're
unlucky it won't blow
up because you might
say well wouldn't that be
unlucky no well that
was good because then you
know there's a problem there's
a but if it just
doesn't blow up there's
still a problem and you
don't notice it so
let's suppose that this was
a number like four five six seven and this
represented a color like
red all right so we
got some f and whatever else in here so it
goes and sends it now
somebody's got to receive it
all right so we're
probably receiving it now
they've also been told
to receive five things
okay they maybe have
their buffer that they're
receiving into it because
it's the same piece of
code remember it's the
same piece of code their
buffer might be the same
length if you if you
may if everybody has a buffer of only four
then the guy who's receiving
will also be four right
and you set five so it'll start following
this start receiving start
copying it in here
and then that last ff right there
is going to get overridden into this array
and this is going to overwrite whatever
the hell is adjacent to that in memory
again if it's not
in your memory space it'll
it'll blow up but what
about if this is actually
over here this is
some other variable like your
user id but that we
just overwrote your user id
with some binary jacked
up version of whatever
color is being represented
over here right so you
have what i'm trying to
say is all the problems
that you have with c
you can still have them all
here except for it's worse because you got
mp copies of it
running and you're constantly sending
things of variable sizes all
around well the only way
you can have variable size
things in c is to
have them dynamically created
with now that can free
and so forth which
means that all that memory
management nightmare you had
before you've got that
now but it's just
to the nth degree because
there's all these processes
running the other problem
is that when something blows up you can't
tell us sincerely which
processes that was which one
just blew up that's
why we probably want to
use lots of print statements
for us to try to
see what's going on throughout
our code if we start
having some issues using that as a bug and
there are some tools also that we can use
i'm just kind of
pointing that out so there's
receive blah blah blah
how much data i'm actually
receiving now like we said you know it's
the amount of data
you're receiving is the product
of the count and the
size of the data type so
remember in c you can
say size of n you know
size of that that gives
you the byte number of
the number of bytes per
that data unit data sizes
that element um this is interesting here
what are the issues the exact behavior
is determined by the implementation
wait a minute that sounds odd
i thought you said that if they they match
the implementation of the api
it'll do the same thing
well kind of what we're
saying is is that it
will eventually do the same
thing but the exact order
that it does things in might depend on how
they've done it underneath
right all they're saying is
that logically they're going
to abide by that api
and some things in the
api will say if this
parameter is invalid its
behavior is undefined other
ones will be like well this parameter is
undefined or ill-formed i'll
throw air you know
but that depends on
which implementation it is
so look at this if i send something
may behave differently with
regards to the buffer size
cutoffs and blocking what
are they even talking
about what about if
you try to send something
that's a gigabyte wait a
minute now is this a
zero copy send or is it not what i mean
what do you guys know like when you send
something say you're going
to send something across the
network do you
actually who's orchestrating the
moving all that data out of this buffer
to the network card
and across the network is
that you no well so if this was a gigabyte
is it being sent
directly from this buffer or
is it copying this
buffer to another buffer and
sending that is it
copying chunks of this a
little bit of time
to the network card memory
and then sending it this has a lot
to do with whether
it is buffered unbuffered blocking
non-blocking all of these things so in
that chatter point
to point communications you'll
notice that there's a big section that
describes the difference
between blocking and non-blocking
synchronous asynchronous buffered
or unbuffered okay and
the reason that that can have some
implications here is imagine
this if this was one
gigabyte say that it
says all right i'm going
to copy this thing from this buffer all
the way to another
buffer and then i'll return
now when you return
that just means that this
buffer is now available to
be to be written into
why would it be okay
to write into it because
you already made a copy
of it or it could be
that i will not return
until such a time as
either it's copied to a
buffer or it's sent across the
network but now if
it's a non-blocking thing
and it's an asynchronous
the call will return immediately
and just because the
call return doesn't mean this
has been sent so
if your code starts jacking
around with this buffer
and changing the contents
of it you're messing
with this buffer before it's
actually been sent so now
your buffer is going to
be some mixture of what
the old data was with
the new data and it's
going to be backed up
so you have to really
look at which type of sending
are you doing and
what does it mean semantically
now it says here
for receive though it always
blocks until a message
is received that matches it
now what does it
mean matching we talked about
this last time matching means
that like hey you know
will is going to send
me a message he's ranked
for he used the tag 99 so when i try to
receive i have to specify
who am i receiving from what
tag am i hashing so i would have like if i
said okay i want to receive
from will tag 99 will has
a sit at yet my process is just going to
lock right there it's just
going to sit there it's
going to block it's not going to move
forward and let's say
five seconds later he sends
then once this matching
things happens my process will
start moving so you
can imagine if you don't
have your syndrome
receives match correctly what
can you have happen
deadlock can occur because
one of the ways that
deadlock happens is if you
are holding a resource and
won't get it up until
something happens that will
never happen right so when
you go to receive a message it's trying to
say all right i'm going
to pull this buffer right
here and i'm not going
to let it go until my
match receives happen but
the other process never
lost the correct matching
send my process is
going to sit there
forever not doing anything
and if both of your processes are wrong
that they'll both freeze
and they'll both just
sit there indefinitely now
one might sit there
and freeze the other
one might go on through
with the other like so
some of your print statements
might come out and
not others right you're like
what the hell is
going on let's go something's
waiting for a thing that will never happen
or that hasn't happened
you have to be really
you're really uh really
careful about it and you
need to understand kind
of what's going on here
so the very first
problem that looks like that
they're doing in here
is this idea of numerical
integration using the trapezoidal
rule in MPI to
describe a problem that
you're going to break up
into pieces in order
to solve it in parallel
and say hey here's a
cool example of doing something
in parallel now the thing
is when i use the
word cool here i'm very
using that very loosely okay
because like i don't
think anybody would actually
write a program like
the one they're getting ready
to show you but it is interesting from the
point of view that it
does divide the problem up
and it does do it in parallel okay now how
many of you know what
the trapezoidal rule is for
integration let's just talk
about that briefly just
just so you guys remember i mean remember
that like there was
a couple of different ways
probably when you were in
the end taught how to
integrate the area under a
curve and you're looking at
the reman sum and as
the limit of the width of
the interval goes to
zero that becomes equal
to the actual integration
blah blah blah blah and
this teacher probably was
like all right let's
just suppose that my
function like looked like
this right that was my s of x and i wanted
to integrate it say from
here from a to let's say
here to b and i'm trying to find the
other area under the
curve it's called numerical integration
my analytical integration
because that would
be something different
we're talking about numerical
calculations with this stuff
all right so you guys
remember like you could
divide this up into some
little little chunks right
it'd be like you
could do here it's
okay i got this rectangle
plus this rectangle plus this rectangle
plus the area of this rectangle
shit this rectangle and
then this rectangle so
and sometimes i'll be losing a little bit
area i should have
gotten and sometimes i'd
be including some area
that i should have gotten
but i get this
kind of approximation that as
this thing gets smaller
the smaller you make these
actually sum it up and say this area plus
this is equal to the area under this curve
and it's cool to be able to try to figure
out what the this trivial
figure of the area of this
is because the area
rectangle is its width times
its height if it's
width some fixed amount let's
just call it you know
delta and then its height
but what is what is
its height well you know
right here in a the
height of this rectangle right
here and this thing here
would be say like a plus
delta the f of that would be here plus two
delta would be this plus
three delta would be there plus
four delta would be there
so we can figure out what
the height is at every
point we know what the width
is because it's always the
same and we can just
add them up and that
would be equal to like the
amount of area that's under the curve you
guys remember this right
well the only difference
between that trapezoidal rule
is they're not making
it be a rectangle the trapezoidal rule is
saying all right let's
say this is our thing
that's the beginning and
ending of my thing here
they're saying let's assume
that this is an
interpolation like that and
so now this is a
trapezoid yeah we got
a trapezoid here basically
right because we've got
like this thing plus a
because our sides are not going to be like
this our sides are always
going to be vertical because
of the fact that that's how we divided up
the x-axis and you can
see where they're going with
this how would you do
is a parallel well we
know that if you wanted
to calculate the area under a
curve say from a to
b then you could really go
from like say a to
here plus from there to there
plus from there to there and add them all
together and that's equal
to it cool so what
are fast two processes
well i'll just divide
the work process zero
and calculate the area under
this part of the curve
process one would calculate the
area on this part of
the curve and at the end
they'll add those two
areas together to get the
final area which is
similar to that global sum
that we were dealing with earlier except
for instead of
adding energies together we're
actually floating we're
adding floating point
numbers here together
global floating point
does that make sense and i don't like well
what about if you had
four processes cool like this
one guy's adding up this
one one guy's adding up
this one one guy's adding
up this one one guy's
adding up that and
it's like quote dividing the
problem up and having
each person do its piece
and it makes sense like
this was a trillion points
and you divided it forward
this will be only a
quarter of a trillion here
a quarter of a trillion
here a quarter of a
trillion here and then we get
enough faster, hopefully four
times faster, because you only
got to do one fourth the amount of work.
And could you be adding this area up while
somebody else is adding
the area up here? Yes,
the cost is sufficient. In
addition, it's associated
with commutative typically,
although with photo point
numbers we know that's
not 100% true because
it's a round off errors.
But except for round off errors, your
catastrophic cancellation and stuff
you probably learned by
other addresses, you can
do that in any order
you want, which means
that those quantities can be
anywhere they want. They can be
doing it at the same time.
All right. In fact,
that's what you're looking for.
What can be done at the same time? So,
that's the only thing
you parallelize, the stuff
that can be done at the same time.
All right. So, they're
going to walk through
how do we do this in parallel using MPI?
Okay. Now, what about if you were going to
do this and you weren't going to use MPI?
I mean, could you do this even without
MPI? We probably have
a for loop here, right?
And the number of things we divide the for
loop is going to be
however many divisions we're going
to make. And the width
of all those rectangles will
be, you know, B minus
A divided by the number
of divisions you have.
And then you just multiply
the height of the circle,
the height of the thing,
and deal with the triangle part at the top
and just sum it up. I mean, you'd have a
singly nested for loop. So, when you see
a singly nested for
loop here, that makes sense
because you don't change
the time or complexity
when you do it
in parallel. You're just changing
the big coefficient out
front. Instead of it being
in order in, it's going to be in order
one peak of in, which is
still order in, right? That's the idea.
So, cool. Like, we're
going to calculate the area
from under curve A and
B. So, we're going to
do this and three will
do that, as an example.
At the end, they'll do
a global sum and they only
got the answer. So,
they're like, hey, now,
you know, the trapezoidal
rule, blah, blah, blah, blah,
it's just the area of
the rectangle at the bottom
plus the area of that
little triangle piece at the
top. So, like, cool.
So, it's, you know, it's
this area. But it's going
to have a base time
type of this thing at the right
triangle and that's what
you're going to get.
Does everybody see that that's the,
that approximation, of
course, is not great
because it's missing this
area here. But if we
make this really close
together and instead we do
like this, we get it
a lot closer of approximation
than reality. So, and we're
going to have to make
that really small to have
very much work to do.
If you think about it,
if we only made this two
or three million
points, like, your computer
can already do that
instantaneously. We're going to
have to make it billions
of points in order for it
to take a bit of time.
When I said it was a
stupid example to start
with, I mean it's stupid
because the problem we're
trying to solve for a
one-dimensional integration.
So, that's what
this is. It's just f
of x. Now, this was x of x, y, z,
w, a, b, c. Now, that would take a long
time. But just one variable,
that's not too hard to do
already. That's not hard to do. So, it
probably wouldn't be something
you'd be trying to parallelize
these little toy problems
that we're doing here.
Everything just looks like
that. It's a little toy
problem. Then you're like, all
right now, let's go, we've
learned to do it that
way. Let's go do it on
a real problem. Don't worry
about how that works. Let
me show you, you know.
So, that'll be kind of
how they, how they do
stuff. So, we know we're
going to have that, that
for loop. And if we're
going to divide, we're going to
be integrating, you know, from a
to b. And so, from a to b of some f of x.
And that means that
this entire, this entire
interval here is b
minus a. So, we're assuming
that a is less than or equal to b here.
So, you know, we're not,
you know, we're not going to
integrate from the right-hand
side to the left. We're
going to integrate from
the left to the right
like we typically do in
class. So, take the width
of the entire interval and
divide it up in end
pieces. So, we're going
to divide all this up
into end little pieces, right?
So, each one of them
is going to be one-nth
of b minus a. That's
how, this is the width
of each one of these little,
these little triangles, each one of these
little trapezoids, if you
will. All right. Now,
what about the height? And
again, I do not know why
in the hell they, they
call this h instead of w.
It's probably going to call that width
in the middle of height, but whatever.
Well, if, if this is, you know, at a here
and b here, and we
got approximately that divided by that
for the height of it.
And so, we're going to
say, okay, cool. We're going
to start at the beginning
of this thing, going all
the way to the end
of this thing, adding up
one little piece at a time.
And what we're saying is, if we started at
a, and we're on the ith iteration of this,
and the width of each one of these little
trapezoids is h, then it'll
be like a, then plus
one h, plus two h, plus three h, plus
four h, as we're walking
all the way across here.
And we're going to
call our function, whatever our
function is. Like, let's just say f of x
was equal to, you know,
x squared. Then you would
be taking that x sub
i that you're on. So, like,
if this was like, say
you're doing it at point
one. So, it'd be five,
five point one, five point two,
five point three, five
point four, going one
at a time, getting the value of f,
and adding it up. Now, you may say, well,
now, wait a minute now.
That doesn't sound like we're
doing multiplication. Wouldn't we be doing
multiplication? Well, if
the width of every
one of these is the same, you don't need
to multiply it every time.
You can factor it out.
That's what they've
done. They've factored out
the entire thing,
and then they're multiplying
it out, and you're just doing additions.
Does everybody get why that would be?
Because it'd be like, you'd
be saying f of x
times three, plus f of
x sub i times three,
times three. We'll just factor the three
out, and that's what
you've got, all right?
And then when we're
all done, we multiply that
width out there. We've
got that, and we've got
the approximation for it.
And so, you're like,
we got our sequential
program, and that's what we're
going to do a lot
of things here. We're going
to give an idea. You're
going to write it sequentially,
and then you're going to manipulate
that sequential program
into a parallel program.
But why would that be useful? Well, first
of all, it's useful
from a strategic perspective.
If you can't solve the problem in
sequential, you definitely can't
solve it in parallel,
right? I mean, you need
to have a base thing
to start with. What about
if you were at a company,
and they're like, hey, dude,
we've got this
single-threaded,
single-process application.
We want you to parallelize
it. Let's say you go
do that, and you're like,
sweet man, I just ran it.
Look at this thing. It's
so much faster. You know
what the first thing you're
going to want to know
is? Is the answer the same as what I
got before? Because they've been
using this with their clients
or whatever else, and
it's been working. How do
they know that stuff you
just did is the exact
same thing that what
they have before? Well, you
have to have the before
scenario to compare it to
as a part of all your testing and
stuff, right? So we're
going to start with something,
get a bunch of answers, parallelize it,
get the same
answers, compare those things,
see if there's a same. If they're not the
same, then you probably
did something wrong, right? Or
there were some surrounding
issues with floating point
that might be okay if that is like the
difference is only a small within a small
threshold, right? Like if
one of the answers
would be five point one, and you got five
point oh nine nine nine
nine nine nine, you're like,
okay, well that's essentially
the same except for
the round off there. But if you're adding
integers together and you don't get the
same answer, then you
definitely did something wrong
or you had to overflow, right? You got
to think about all this sort of stuff.
So they're like thinking, how do I
divide my problem
into individual tasks? Well,
that's pretty easy here,
right? You just take the
whole thing and say, I'm
going to divide it. This
will be task zero,
this task one, task two,
task three. That means that
the thing I'm going to
be parallelizing is this
loop, instead of going from
one to end, I'm going to go from from some
place to some other place
in here, right? Like if
my if my whole function
was like this, and I was
doing it, let's say
with just three processes, so
it would go from here
to here, here to there,
and there to there.
So process zero would be
working in here, one
would be working in there,
two would be working here.
So the first one blue
would have to go from
here to here. The second
guy's loop needs to
start right after that here
and go to there, right?
And the other guy's loop
needs to start right after
that and go down to
the end. But what does
it mean right before, right
after? That means you're going to have to
parameterize the starting and
ending location for your loop
based on your rank. Okay. So
that's what we're doing here. Now,
we only got 10 seconds left. So I'm going
to say this. Go home, take a look at this,
get the first NDI
program out of chapter three
source code, and see if
you can run that version,
unmodified or whatever, run it
on expanse, on a node,
pick in to be kind of big and see if you
can make it like
get some answers like, you
know, we're going to integrate
say x squared from zero
to a million and see
what you get. You know what
I mean? And then say I
want to do that with two
processes. What about
three processes? What about
four processes? And then
granted that you're going
to be on one node, it's going to be
shared, right? So we're not
looking at performance like speed,
we're just seeing logically
where your program work.
And then when we come in here next time,
we're going to say, okay, we're going to
learn how to add
timing constraints to our stuff.
We're going to learn how
to write a test harness
to test all the stuff
and we'll kind of go from
there. Any questions? All
right, well, have a
great day. And no
quiz next time. We're just
coming in here having work
on this thing. All right, guys.
Do we have a scheduled
meeting time for this week?
I wasn't sure if I could see it.
You mean for the research stuff?
So we do, we resaduled it to be some time.
So you don't see the
thing on your calendar then?
No, we'll see. Or maybe it is.
Let me see if I can find it here.
All right, I do not see it here either.
My question is, is it
because it's on the other
calendar or water? But
the attention was, remember
how we all said
when we could possibly meet?
Can you send me an email to remind
me about that? And I'll take care of that.
Thanks for pointing that
out. I really looking
forward to hearing about
the stuff you found.
Yeah, yeah, there's some cool stuff there.
All right, cool, man.
Take care.
Yeah, you too. What class is this?
Ph.D. and SQL and all that stuff.
We've had travel stuff got
approved for the week before Thanksgiving.
But we're trying to pump the university
for money now to be like, well,
instead of us spending our money, can
you spend a little bit of money
and then let us make
our money go further? Even
if the answer to that
is no, we're still doing it.
But between the
college and the department,
the semester of many
travel grants were due.
And so those were submitted to Cox
yesterday. So we'll see what we get.
Pretty soon, we're going to have to go and
actually get into flights
so we can lock in.
And that November 16th to the 21st, I
mean, you have constraints
as to when you say,
look, you deal with the flights, I'll
be there. Or you need to actually say,
well, I can't leave on that 16th until
this time. And as far as I'm concerned,
I don't have any to worry about.
So the plan will be like to get there so
that we don't get there
super late on the 16th.
And we won't get back here super late on
the 21st. That's just
going to be the deal.
So and more important that we don't get
there late on the 16th than it is
even if we get here relatively late on the
21st, I feel like that's not as bad as
if we were to get there
late because we get it situated.
Whatever the delay is going to be from
the airport to the
place, to this, to that.
And then that very next morning
on Monday, that sort of stuff.
Well, the stuff doesn't
really start until that Monday.
Hi, you know, have you
been to this one before?