Did that work out?
Did you go test the other key?
I have not yet, but I'm not sure.
All right.
And do you remember the
same thing with that door?
Just like making sure that it locks.
It goes to that other
stuff that's in there, you know?
I'll make sure it works.
It's weird.
I realized that I
pushed on actually the key.
It's like hella fun.
Maybe it's hard to bust it into, man.
I remember stuff ruffled all
through and stuff all over.
Yeah, I didn't really
think it mattered though.
I thought it was coming.
You left the office.
All the windows were shattered and stuff.
All right, take care, man.
Have a good one.
So anybody tried
doing the trapezoid problem
on the expanse machine?
Did it go wrong?
Mike, you did.
Did it run?
I tried to...
It was like four miles.
Awesome.
And what did you have to do
in order to be able to do it?
Well, you know, the modules, like,
like resetting exactly what the
modules would come along with.
So that's a great question.
So Mike's bringing up the
idea that you log in
and you load whatever
modules you might need.
Like, let's say you're trying
to load something for OpenMPI
or something, or the case might be later.
For other stuff, other other software.
Like, if you do like
a module list, a bail,
or a module something,
like, you can see, like,
all the various software that's on there.
And I think they have,
like, a utility called Spider
that they use to
do some of that searching.
And if you load the modules
and then you log out of the machine,
they're not in
your environment anymore now.
You know how, like, you
have what's called like your,
well, actually, let's just go log in.
I think the internet's working today.
I rebooted the computer.
And by the way,
there was another professor
that was in a meeting with me yesterday,
but their computer was
doing the exact same thing
where on the third
floor it wasn't working.
ITS, of course, said it's
all me, which I agree.
But I'm like, it ain't just me.
There's, like, at least two other people
that every time they
come to the third floor,
they're like, we just
rebooted the computer every time
you go to the third
floor, you know, process all.
That's good.
That's a pretty much cool solution.
Let's see now. Okay.
Let's talk about, because that's
what you were asking, right?
Like, how do you get around that problem?
Yeah. Okay.
Let me get my
phone here for the two-factor.
Do the same here.
Do this.
Quit this.
Flip this on.
Do not disturb.
Showing everything else.
Open down here.
I don't know what's in that window.
Oh, that's our slides. Okay.
Let's get in here.
Okay.
So, I want to, like, for example,
this is just me talking through it.
Like, I don't actually know for certain
what shell I'm in right now.
I don't know if this is a back shell,
T-S-T-C-S-H.
It's E-S-H.
You know, on the
Mac, it's a different one.
So, like, I mean, I
want to figure out, like,
what shell am I in?
So, if you type E-N-V,
that gives you a list
of all your environment variables.
Like, what are they equal to right now?
So, I'm going to take that,
and I'm going to cat that to a thing
that will allow me
to search for particular words.
So, I'm going to say, you know,
I'm going to pipe it or cat it to a graph.
So, the graph means look for a string,
and I'm going to say dash I
because I don't want it
to be case sensitive, necessarily.
So, that means case insensitive.
I want to type shell,
and it says here that the
shell I'm using is a back shell.
Okay, so that helps me know, okay,
that's the shell we're dealing with here,
which is not unusual for a Linux machine,
but back in the day, I mean,
people would have this enough configured
to use all kind
of weird shells or whatever.
The reason I'm trying to figure that out
is because which shell I'm in
kind of dictates
which shell configuration file
I want to look at.
So, when you're using a back shell,
that means that there should be a dot
bashrc file in this directory.
Okay, so, if I do the dells-lrt,
I'll look for that,
and maybe I'll just play with graph again.
I want to do dash I, mash.
Oh, I'll see that.
Yeah, so I've
got a bash.underscore profile.
Remember, if you do a regular ls,
you won't see any files
that begin with a dot.
So, that's not going to help.
So, I've got to
see logout bashrc bashhistory.
So, I'm looking at this one and this one.
I'm thinking maybe I have
something to do with it.
I have to remind myself also
every time I come in here.
So, I'm going to try to just,
I'm going to cat out the file .bashrc.
Now, you see how I
like that if I'm like this,
I just hit tab and a tab completes it.
So, you guys don't
know about tab completion.
I know the thing starts with .b,
so I hit tab and it's like, all right now,
it's unique up until I get to bash.
Now, there's other things like,
so, underscore profile, rc.
So, then if I type in
r and I hit tab again,
that's the entire file.
So, if you've got some long path,
long string that's unique,
you don't have to
type the entire thing out.
You can just start beginning with it,
hit tab and it'll
do what's called tab completing.
The thing, if it's unique enough, right?
Now, if every damn file
in this directory started with .b,
that wouldn't have helped a lot.
You'd have to keep going until you
get to the uniqueness of it, right?
So, I'm going to cat that out.
So, cat just means, echo it to the screen.
Just print it on the screen.
And it looks like it says,
now look, if this file exists on,
so this is this statement in bash,
so, like I said, if this file exists,
then we're going to execute it.
So, like any kind
of global bash environment variables,
they got set up on the system.
And then it says,
like, specific user path variables,
like, so, at some point in my path,
pass, I installed
some software called endif
and I needed it to
be in my executable path
so I could run that endif command.
But let's keep looking here.
And here we go.
So, load modules.
So, I've got the last line of this thing,
in my case, it's
like, I'm loading this thing
for whatever reason the last
time I was loading stuff,
I was using this
particular version of this stuff.
What you do is, at
the bottom of your file there,
go ahead and put whatever modules
you want to load in there
so that the very first time you log in,
what will happen is, the
shell will first come up here
when you're logging in, like,
literally, I just logged in.
The very first thing it does is, it says,
go load up anything
your global set of definitions.
And then it says, go load up my stuff.
And you can add your stuff to the end.
I don't normally recommend
putting it at the end,
unless there's already a specific section
in your dash and your bash
or C file where it says,
put modules, I don't want
to put them at the end,
that way it doesn't conflict
with whatever might be done
for that, you know, in order.
So, my expression like, man, it sucks,
but every time I log in,
I have to reload the modules
and reload stuff.
That's where you want to do it.
So, if you're going to be
working on MPI for a while,
you might want to go ahead
and preload the modules for that.
Does that make sense?
Now, one other thing you should look at,
what is in this bash profile thing?
I'm just kind of curious.
For this, I'm going to use BI.
So, bash profile.
So, get all the
aliases and functions, all right?
So, now this says, if
my, this means your home directory,
so it totally means your home directory.
So, if I have a bash or
C file in my home directory executed,
so it almost makes it look like
what the system probably does here first
is goes and executes the
profile and then executes this thing,
and that thing then
goes and executes the global
and then your local.
So, it looks like that
must be the order of operations.
I mean, I'm just assuming, I don't know.
I wouldn't mess with this though.
Let's see.
Now, what else is there?
I'm going to set you on RTH.
Let's look at here.
Is there an alias?
Let's see if there's
an alias file in here.
I don't think there is.
I don't have an alias file here.
A lot of Linux machines
will have a file called .alias,
and that would be like,
if you want to like,
say like you're
constantly typing the word,
CD, space, this, this, this, this,
every damn time you get into
the system, you use it a lot.
You're going to have to
type that over and over again.
You could make an alias in there.
You could say, I want to set alias.
Anytime I type the command CDD instead,
it just automatically does this command.
So, you set it like a shortcut.
If you want to find some shortcuts,
you can put it in your alias file.
You can also put them in your, you know,
the aliases inside the Bash
or C file as well,
but a lot of people just
will put all of their aliases
in one file, and then
from the Bash or C file
will say, hey, source the .alias file.
Like, so if you
find yourself repeatedly typing
the same kind of crap over and over again,
you might as well
have some quick shortcuts
so you don't have to worry about it.
So, does that answer all that?
All right, so Mike,
so you ran the program,
so what happened?
So, you logged in, you loaded the modules,
you compiled it using API CC,
and then you ran it with what?
It would be an S run
to get into an interactive partition.
Anybody got a question about how
do you do the S run?
If you forget, what do you do?
Go to the expense user guide.
Go down to the
section called Running Jobs.
Interactive means I want
to be sitting there
in the command line playing
around so I can type
and see errors as they pop up,
or I could run my
program quickly in this debug partition.
That user guide is your
friend to try to figure out,
how do I do this? How do I do that?
They do have some
commands that are not standard,
that are on other clusters.
So, like spider, that's not as,
this is the only system I've
ever seen with spider on it
as opposed to some of the other stuff.
So, anyway, and when you ran it, Mike,
did you get the
same answer from, you know,
if you divided the problem into two chunks
versus three chunks versus four?
So, the only thing you
let me do with TRAP 1
was just run it into your media inputs,
and then TRAP 2,
TRAP 2 let me give an
A, B, and an N input.
And so, they were varying the answers
as well as popping out.
I gotcha.
So, I'm going to go ahead and run,
there's my S run
command from the other day
when I did this.
Now, notice how when I type history,
I can see like, you know,
stuff that predates me logging in today,
like these are commands
I typed the other day.
So, that's nice.
I can see some history
beyond just what I did today.
Now, this is command in history in my log
that this is the 996th
thing I typed in here.
It must be a type history again.
So, well, I guess it's not doing that.
I don't know if it goes backwards
in time with the rolling history or what.
But either way, this is 996,
and I could copy and paste this.
I could do like this, and
I copy, hit paste, and enter.
The other thing I could do is,
I could just hit exclamation point 996,
and that means run the same command
as when I ran on
line 996 above in my history.
So, I'm going to see what happens.
Now, it says I got a problem.
I can't do all of that.
So, what's that?
What's the issue, do you guys remember?
It says it violates the policy.
But now, we know that 30
minutes is okay for the evo partition.
We know that four gigs
is nowhere near the big thing.
You know, you're only asking for one node,
and the nodes have 128 cores.
So, we're not hitting
the kind of problems here.
Like, what's the issue?
What's the only other parameter here?
The account.
Is 108 the correct account?
I don't know.
Is it?
I'm asking you guys.
All right.
So, 108, right now, let's see.
Control C, Control B.
So, this is all of us.
So, the account is 108.
Let's see.
Let's make sure that
Dougie Jones is in there.
All right.
So, let's see what
the issue might be here.
Not sure.
Now, I mean this.
Like, I'm not actually sure
what problem this list is.
Yes, Ron.
The petition is that PTUI.
Account equals this.
Nodes equal to one.
Task for once is this.
Do that.
Not exactly sure what the issue is.
User size and or
time limit violates this stuff.
Now, let's go here.
I'm curious.
So, you know, we clearly have enough stuff
left because that number
is much larger than
this number.
So, we got plenty of stuff left.
I honestly am not sure
what the problem is here.
Maximum jobs per account.
Makes me wonder now, I'm assuming that I
don't already have jobs
running in the background
because if I had of, it should
have been killed already
because 30 minute limit.
I want to just check.
I mean, I just, I don't actually know.
So, let's execute.
There's a bunch of people here.
So, dash UWM Jones.
And there aren't any things
running under my name right now.
So, it doesn't seem like
that should be a problem.
Let me do this.
Let me go back
and look retroactively in history
to the very last time I ran this thing.
So, those are the two
times that I ran it today.
This looks like the time
I ran it the other day.
Also see that I ran it over here.
Those look like the same things.
This is me going into the
directory where I'm
keeping the source files.
Tom, I'm kind of confused.
There was where we did
know what the project was.
I tried 107 and that didn't work.
I tried 108.
And that did work because look at that.
I was on that new node and I said,
hey, let me check what
node, what directory I'm in.
I was in the home directory
and then we switched over here.
So, last time I ran
something, this was the case, right?
I almost made it sound like
something was wrong with my account.
Can anybody else run a job on there?
I'm just curious if it's
going to say there's something
wrong with all of us or is it just me?
Just now?
30 minutes ago, they would do it.
But when I got it, I kicked out.
We've got plenty of credit hours left.
I've only used eight so
far since this new project began.
Let's see.
Mike, you ran one the other day.
What is your user ID over here?
Your access ID.
Right there, right next to yours.
So, one.
So, something must be going on here.
Yours all around right now.
Either way, or can you get in right now?
Okay.
So, at first, I'm like, God,
there's something wrong with my stuff.
It sounds like there's
a problem with our account.
So, I'm not going to be able
to log in to run those particular things.
Or is somebody else able to
get in and just check and see?
All right.
So, note to self, I need to go do that.
Now, the other thing that
we could do here is
somewhere fusion.
I can go over there.
I don't want to run it on the Mac.
I want to run it in
a Linux environment from a processor.
Let's go ahead and start that.
We should get that going.
But anyway, so let's go
take a look at the code.
Then we'll talk about the code for
a bit and look at it and see.
Mike, you said you
got some different answers
depending on how many
different processors you ran.
Yeah.
So, the actual answer, I
was looking at them now,
they come out very similar.
Like you mentioned, there
was something around the differences,
like 100 or whatever.
Right.
Overall, it was.
All right.
So, the one I've
mentioned, like, why that is,
and where the sources of
these errors can come from,
and then, you know,
whether it matters or not.
Okay.
So, we're going to go
back over here to this.
Let's not look and see the code.
Let's look at some real code.
All right.
So, initialize environment, figure
out which one I am,
ask everybody else how many there are.
Looks like we got
some hard code and variables.
Like, for example, the number of things
that I want to divide it into here.
That's hard code.
And, like, Michael, stay in
that because it's in here.
Look at the width of the entire thing.
Figure out what each piece is.
And look at this here.
They're taking the number of things and
dividing it by the number of people
that we get started with here.
So, like, let's suppose that
our communicator size was just one.
It was just one processor.
And that was two.
And you're going to have n divided by two.
And n divided by two, and n is 1,024.
1,024 divided by two is
a whole number, isn't it?
Now, what about if you had done three?
Now, look at the data types here.
Local n is an n.
And if you said that
this is hard coded to 1,024,
and you said 1,024 divided by three,
that is not an even division, is it?
So, when you do that, you won't
have the exact same number of n's
for everybody here.
Like, you're not going to
get all of the right values
because it's not evenly divisible.
And you're not starting and
picking up in the right place
so that the total number of
n's are going to work out.
Does that make sense?
Why, for example, let's
take an early crazy case.
What about if there was only eight?
So, you said there were eight divisions.
So, n divided by two.
And that means each
person's going to do four.
So, their loop will go like 0, 1, 2, 3.
Another guy will go 4, 5, 6, 7.
And that will be all of the eight things.
And each loop will
actually run four times.
They'll calculate the
area under the curve.
Those two things get added together.
I'll get this.
But if I had said eight divided by three,
now what is eight divided by three?
All right, so, is it
going to be a whole number?
I don't know.
So, what's going to happen when
you assign this to an integer?
So, it's truncating off that other stuff.
It's just going to be two, isn't it?
I remember just asking.
Like, local n is an integer.
So, that would be
eight divided by three people.
It's going to be two, isn't it?
So, that means one guy's
loop will do two iterations.
Another guy's loop will do two iterations.
And is that even
the same number of iterations
that the loop would have done originally?
No?
Because we had three.
So, I probably should do
this a little bit better.
There would be three groups.
Process zero, process one, process two.
There's three people.
So, process zero,
process one, process two.
It would be two of them.
This guy does two of them.
That's six total.
Is that the same
number that we started with?
Oh, because of that truncation.
So, this whole thing with integer division
and doing it kind of this flaky way,
that's not going to
give you the same answer.
Now, you might say, yeah, but like, look.
If this number is
really, really freaking big
compared to that number, it
would be pretty close, right?
Because instead of it
being stuff like 2.6,
and I'm throwing away that,
it would be like 2.0,
duh, duh, duh, duh, duh, duh, duh, five.
And if you throw that away, well,
that doesn't really matter as much.
You see what I'm saying?
But the point of it is,
the amount of work being done
is not the same when you
just throw away these chunks, okay?
So, that's one reason why
when you run this program
for different sizes of ends,
for different sizes of P, you know,
for different sizes
of number of processors
and communicator sizes,
you're not going to
get exactly the same answer.
That's one reason, okay?
The other reason is that they're
adding it in a different order.
Like, if you were integrating
a curve from here to here,
and let's suppose you had
divided it, like, into four chunks,
and they're not equally sized,
but you take this area, A1,
you can add it to this area,
A2, add it to this area, A3,
and if you were going from
left to right, like you normally do,
you would have done the
arithmetic, A1 plus A2 plus A3,
and then, like, I get to get A1,
you might be doing a
lot of little things here,
but it would be in order.
And then right after that one,
then it would be in order.
And then right after that
one, it would be in order,
so that when it's all said,
no, no, this might have
involved a bunch of additions.
To get that, this might
have involved a bunch of additions.
To get that, it does not involve
a bunch of additions to get that.
When you go into left or right,
you would have added an
order that particular way, okay?
But if you do it in parallel,
and this guy is
being done on process zero,
and this guy is being done on process one,
that inner loop starts with some
sort of sum that's equal to zero.
So when it first starts adding the
first little bit of error in here,
it'll be zero plus that first
little amount, plus
the second little amount.
If you do that unsequentially,
it would have started
at zero right in here,
it would have already summed
up all the area in here.
It would have started with A1 already.
That means that the round-off
is not accumulating the same way.
Like, doing it the normal sequential way,
it would be A1 plus A2 plus A3 plus A4,
and the parenthesis would then, like this,
this would add the first,
and then this would get added,
and then that would get added,
and then this would get added, right?
Now, you might still
need all the parenthesis
because addition is the social community.
Not for floating point numbers,
in a computer it's not.
That is not the same thing as
A1 plus A2 plus A3 plus A4.
Let's say you did this first,
and then that, and then added.
That is not the same number,
because the floating point
rounding stuff doesn't work.
It's only guaranteed that if you
add it in the same order,
well, you get the same answer,
but when you're doing it in parallel,
you're not adding it in the same order.
You don't think it matters
because they think it doesn't matter
what order you're at, and
if you're talking about the integers,
then that would be
true, roughly, except for overflow.
But for floating point numbers,
you're almost never going
to get the same answer.
There's a lot of effort, actually,
that goes into the parallel community
to try to make this thing
hopefully be as close to what
it should have been to begin with.
There's a bunch of techniques.
Working, like, actually...
I wasn't working with her, I mean,
but I worked with
one of the mathematicians
that had been working on this
sort of problem for a long time,
but she came up
with something pretty cool.
And, granted, it's one
of these things where
you sacrifice a bunch of
performance to get the accuracy,
but if the accuracy doesn't really matter,
well, then you might as well
do it in pretty late, right?
When else does this become a problem?
Well, aside from the round off in here,
you've got the fact that, like,
when you do the global sum,
so what about the global sum,
then, that this guy sent it here,
and they added it, then this guy
sent it here, and then added it,
versus what about if this one
sent it first and then this one?
Now it would be like A1 plus A2,
but the other way would have been
A1 plus A3 and then plus A2,
then over here it would be plus A3.
But also commutative. It's
not the same either, necessarily.
Do you see what I'm saying?
Because it causes
rounding to be different.
So that's why you're going to get
some answers that
don't seem right sometimes.
It comes from two places here,
the way this code is written.
One is, they threw away a
bunch of the round off right here
when they calculate the amount
of work each processor's doing
because they left this
off to just interdivision.
Interdivision is just to screw it and
actually throw away some of the stuff.
It's not even the same iterations.
But even if it were
the same number of iterations,
it still would be equal
because of the order of operations
and the associative and commutativity
with the coding point stuff.
Does that make sense?
So this little thing that they did here is
a cool way to
start because it's pretty simple.
It's like, look, if N is big enough
and P is small enough relative to N,
this interdivision doesn't
really matter too much.
And if you make, you
know, the other things relatively small
and we don't have really, really
big numbers versus
really, really small numbers,
you're probably going to add up
okay. It's probably going to be okay.
The other issue you have sometimes with
adding up a bunch of numbers in sequence
is that you get
what's called catastrophic cancellation.
Imagine you had an array in sorted order.
The start out is
really, really tiny numbers.
Like, really tiny.
And then it got really, really big.
Like, this is over here on this
side, like 10 to the minus 20.
And over here is 10 to the positive 20.
Well, now, if you start off small,
you got a bunch of small numbers together,
they get bigger.
And then when you add bigger
numbers to bigger
numbers, they get bigger.
But what about if you took a really big
number and added it
to a really small number?
What even happens?
Like, literally, like, let's just imagine
we were dealing with, you know,
a fixed number of bits.
That's number 10. We really argue
with a fixed number of bits.
If you're having it in a number of bits,
notice that you can't
have it in a precision
with any capital floating point numbers.
So imagine, if you will, I took
the number, and this is in base 10.
Let's just say I took the number 9, 0,
0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, dot,
0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0.
And I added that to the number,
0, 0, 0, dot, dot, dot, dot, 0,
dot, 0, dot, dot, dot, dot, 1 here.
Well, like, that is, like, way over here.
And this is way over there.
And with the floating points up, you've
only got a fixed number of bits
to hold the fraction over
the moment and the sign.
And when you do that, if
the dynamic range is really, really big
and really, really small,
what will happen is,
this will just round off and go away.
It'll be as if it wasn't even there.
But if you added it in the other order,
much of small
things eventually become big,
then it won't go away.
You see what I mean?
So you get a lot of issues here.
You get round-off errors.
You get catastrophic cancellation.
You get things associated
with the cutitivity break.
I mean, you've got all
these other kinds of things
that will explain why
you don't get the answer.
Now, I want you to think, though,
that if we're
dealing with integers, though,
we're going to tell me
how to work with integers.
That shouldn't be the case.
We should get the right answer.
And unless we also have
the fact that overflow occurred, right,
that's a whole other thing, right?
That has nothing to
do with parallel computing.
That would happen even if, you
know, any kind of for loop
that it had doesn't be too big,
you might wind up getting overflow, right?
So that's not really
a function of parallelism
where that problem comes from.
That problem comes from
just any computer system limited
to find out what it is for stuff, right?
So does that make sense?
A sanity check would be, though,
if I got a program like this
and I wanted to test it as
a coder, right, as a software person,
I'd want to run it a bunch of
different ways to make
sure it doesn't crash.
I'd want to run it a
bunch of different ways with stuff
that should provide the same answer
but with a different degree of parallelism
and making sure I'm pretty close
because imagine that I wasn't off
by just .00005, I'm off by 5 trillion.
Well, that doesn't make sense, right?
Something's wrong.
Either I coded it wrong
or I'm actually suffering from one
of these catastrophic
failures that happens
with numerical instability
in these algorithms.
I say that because later you're
going to want to have a program
that will call your
program repeatedly with different numbers
to make sure that this stuff works
kind of as a testing type thing, okay?
So they wouldn't have said, well, all
right, well, if I know how many elements
each processor is supposed to have,
all right, if I take my rank
and I multiply it by that
and I start at the starting place,
that's going to go and move us so
that when I'm going from A to B
and if I'm processor number
four, then that will start here
at my rank times four
times the number of elements.
So if each element is this out,
it will skip me over to here.
My A will start right there and
then I'll go and do my part.
That's what's happening.
It's figuring out where in that
function is my beginning point, okay?
So it calls the function.
Let me go down to the
function and look at what that is.
The function just is, okay,
cool, starting and adding up.
I'm going to go ahead and take,
let's see, my A value, my B value,
and the other parameters that it
has over here, local N and H.
So that H, remember, that's the
other thing that we factored out
and multiplied by at the end.
And then basically just
add up the amount here.
So starting at this, keep adding it
up, calling it over and over again.
And then F of X would
be whatever it is you're integrating,
like X squared or X to the third
or sine of X or whatever, you know,
whatever the function is.
And it looks like they
actually return it by value.
So they return it by value up here.
And this finds a VN
called, you know, answer local int.
Now notice, you know,
everybody actually calls this.
Just notice that even
rank zero calls this.
So rank zero, because there's
no if statement in here
that it says only do this if I'm a worker.
Everybody knows it.
So like if there were 10 processes,
all 10 would be doing some work here,
including process zero.
But then it says if I'm
not process zero, so like for example,
if you had four processes, zero,
one, two, three, if I'm not zero,
so that's these guys, then I'm
going to send it to rank zero.
So I'm going to send it to
rank zero, send it to rank zero,
send it to rank zero with a tag of zero.
Remember, those have to match for
there to be considered a match
to send and receive.
What am I going to send?
I'm going to send my local answer.
So my local answer that I got back
from adding a little chunk of the area
has to address those.
It always has to be the address
of where the data can be found.
All right.
And since this is not
a pointer to begin with,
we have to take the address
of it to get that value.
But to send one element, think about it.
I'm only sending my
one floating point on there.
And how big is each one of them?
Well, they're doubles.
So internally, it can take one and
multiply it by the size of double
and then it has all the bytes to send.
And this rank is
with respect to the communicator,
which will always be the case
in our code most of the time.
Otherwise, like if I am, so this part
here is like if I am rank zero,
I'm going to go
and just receive from everybody,
and I'm going to calculate the
running sum across all of them,
and that's going to be my answer.
And at the end, if I'm the
head node, I'm going to print it out.
So if I'm rank zero, I'll print it out.
Now, you could have everybody
print it out, you know,
but if everybody printed it out,
what do you think would happen?
Say everybody printed this out.
They printed out total int.
So rank zero would have
this value for total int,
but what would everybody else have?
Who knows?
Because it's never been initialized.
So you get garbage going up in those.
Because not everybody has the answer.
Who's the only guy who's got the answer?
Rank zero.
Now, everybody could have had the answer.
Everybody could send their
answer to everybody else,
and they could all add it up,
and then everybody would have the answer.
Or after the head guy got it,
he could turn around and send
the final answer to everybody else.
But just as it is right
now, not everybody has the answer.
I want you to keep that in mind.
Like a lot of
these programs we're working with,
these intermediate steps of the program,
people, everybody's going to need
to know the intermediate answer.
So it's not always going to be the
case that only one guy needs to know,
but in this case, there's 20 problems.
The answer is the final answer,
and you only need to print it one time.
You only need it written
to the file one time.
It doesn't need to
be written by everybody,
so that's why they
put that thing in there.
Does that make sense?
All right, let's go look at
some of these other versions here.
Let's see what it
talks about about IO here.
If we start up,
and we have a print
that everyone's going to do,
notice there's nothing in here that says,
only if I'm a certain rank, do something.
Everybody's going to
start printing stuff, right?
You might get them in any kind of order.
Notice how they're all printed.
So process zero got to the screen first,
process one, and then
two got to the screen.
But then for some how,
however the standard IO is working
in the background to do the print,
this came out before that one.
If you were to hit an
up arrow and run it again,
you might get a totally
different ordering of these things,
because there's nothing that controls
what order that thing
gets out to the screen.
If you wanted there to
be some kind of order,
you'd have to enforce
it somehow or another, right?
You can't control it.
The other thing that can
sometimes happen with things like this,
depending on how that
printout is being done
and how it's being handled,
you can imagine that
if somebody's doing something fancy,
it could be in the
middle of printing one of them
and then start printing the other one.
And then finish the other one.
You might have like a
string that's all jumbled up.
And normally with the MDI stuff I've seen,
it's not all jumbled up
inside of a single print statement.
It's just jumbled up
among the print statements.
But something's happened
to have handled that
in the background
because there's concurrent actions
that are working with a shared resource.
Think about it. Your screen, standard out,
that's a shared resource
on all the processes
so how is that being handled?
Something has to be
handling that shared access
in the background there.
So it's unpredictable out
but you can't guarantee
what order it is.
And the reason that sometimes a problem,
can you imagine why
that might be a problem?
What about those print
statements with debugging statements?
And you're trying to be like,
okay, process four got to this location
after process two did,
therefore I think I
know what the problem is.
No you don't.
Because the order that it got printed
doesn't have anything to do necessarily
with the order that
it actually happened in.
Does that make sense?
You don't know that
process two actually was able
to do a print before process four.
You just happen to know that
that's the way it came out here.
Now with respect to the same process,
two people print the screen.
Process one prints
something to the screen,
then prints something to the screen again.
His will be in
order with respect to himself.
But when two people print the screen,
you don't know if it was like process one,
one, two, two,
or if it came to the screen this way,
or this way, or this way.
You don't actually know when this is
with respect to time with respect to this.
You don't know.
There's no global
clock synchronization here
unless you were to provide it.
There are synchronization
parameters we can use
to enforce an ordering if we needed it.
Don't you remember something
back in your head?
Every time you
enforce synchronization on something,
you're slowing it down
because you're telling it
what order it has to be in.
Think about it.
What's the most crazy example of telling
what order it has to be in?
A non-parallel program.
A non-parallel program is
like everyone we've ever written.
It's got a freaking
strict ordering about everything.
It's literally one line at a time.
It has to be in that order.
If we wanted a
bunch of ordering to matter,
we would just do it that way.
We're hoping that we can
do stuff at the same time
where the ordering doesn't matter.
You want to use these synchronization
primitives only when they're necessary
because otherwise you might
as well just write
a parallel sequential program,
and it's all secret.
Literally one thing after another.
It says most MPI
primitives only allow for us
a zero to access standard in.
So it says now you use standard out
when you're printing the screen,
and where is standard in coming from?
That's from the keyboard, right?
Literally you'd be sitting
there at this thing
and it's just late in and
you're going to type the number,
like five, enter.
So instead of doing a primitive,
you're going to do a scan app maybe
to get something to end from the keyboard.
Well, who are you scanning it into?
Which process is going to get that thing?
And they're saying generally
you're going to be,
you know, only process
zero will be the guy
that can read something from the keyboard.
Because otherwise who all is getting that?
Now my contention would be,
you don't want any of these processes
reading from the keyboard, right?
You're going to run a parallel program
that's going to wait
on you to enter something.
That means you don't care
about how fast it is
because there's a damn
human being in the loop.
If there's a human being in the loop,
the computer's not the problem. You are.
You're the limiting bottleneck.
So you'll notice that
several of those programs
have some scan S in it to do some stuff
to show some points.
Like it'll scan
something from the keyboard.
It'll send the things out
to the other processes, you know.
The truth is you either
want to be getting the stuff
from a file, like a configuration file
and everybody will read from that file,
or you want to get
it from the command line
when you first ran the program.
If you're just going to say, you know,
you need to enter your name,
well don't ask for your name to be entered
and then enter it into the keyboard.
Like, go ahead and when you run it,
have your name be one
of the parameters you passed
and it's already got it.
It doesn't need to scan
F anything in from the keyboard.
So I mean, look at this thing.
It's like, get some input from the user.
Okay, enter A, B, and N.
Now A, B, and N,
this is that A, B, and
N associated with the trapezoid, right?
I want to enter, I want to,
I got some function F of X
that I'm trying to
arbitrarily allow the users
to say what A I start at, what B I end at,
as well as N, how
many different things I want to,
you know, chuck this
thing up into or whatever.
And let's take a look at this thing here.
So rank zero, ask a question.
Rank zero gets the
thing from the keyboard.
Now you got, how many of
you are familiar with scan Fs?
Not familiar with that, right? Cool.
And then it's like, all
right, starting at everyone else,
the process is zero, extends
to one, and then to two,
and then to three because
this destination keeps getting iterated.
And it's like, so send A,
then send B, and then send N.
Go to the next guy.
Send A, send B, send N.
A, B, N.
What about if there
were a hundred processes?
There'd be 300 messages
being sent around, right?
Because there's three for
every iteration of this loop.
You don't need to do that.
You can just have A, B, and
N kind of in from the command line
and the R and V
array from the command line.
The other thing, I'm going
to send, okay, so A, B,
and N are the types of A, B, and N.
So integers, let's see.
So this is, let's see.
A is a float, float integer here, right?
We're scanning those things in.
So we got double, double N.
So we send eight bytes,
eight bytes, and four bytes.
That is, what is eight bytes?
16 plus four is 20 bytes.
I'm literally going to
send stuff across a network
with all the hundreds and hundreds
of bytes of packets of crap
that have to encapsulate this
thing to go across the network
to send four bytes.
That's not a good idea.
Why don't I just put A, B, and N together
and send them all at the same time?
So that's the other thing.
Every time you send
a message, that ain't good.
That's communication.
You have to communicate to shared data,
but you don't want to share a lot of it
of tiny little pieces of information.
You want to do as few
transactions across the network as you can
with big transactions.
The bigger, the better.
So is it better to send
three messages to send 20 bytes
or to send one message to send 20 bytes?
One, because you only incur the
latency of one of the things.
You don't have to do all this.
It's like, receive, receive, receive.
Well, you just do one receive.
You can receive all three
of them at the same time.
How did you do that?
You could put it in a struct.
The struct could hold
two floats and one N.
You received the entire
struct at one time.
You could receive all 20
bytes at the same time.
I'm sure he did it here
for the purpose of showing you.
Look, if you want to send
it to article, you can send it.
But no real program would
ever do anything like this.
The other thing is, no real program
would have one guy send it
to everybody one person at a time.
They would use a broadcast to
broadcast it to everybody at once
because it's the same
information going to everybody.
Now, we're in chapter
three of the textbook,
and we're in chapter, I think,
it's three of the NPI specifications
for point-to-point communications.
Send and receive is
a hype of point-to-point communication
from point A to point B.
But broadcast is not from
point A to point B.
It's from point A to all.
That's not called point-to-point.
That's called collective communication.
So that's another chapter in the book.
So that's probably why
they're not showing broadcast yet.
But you guys remember
broadcast from my networking class?
If you're going to
send something to everybody,
you might as well broadcast
it, and they all read it.
Don't sit there and go
send to each one of them.
You wouldn't do that, right?
Well, I guess you're going
to talk about collective communication.
Now, you know how, and we
kind of talked about this before.
So when you were doing that
little sum in the last one,
that trapezoid, literally everybody sent
their things to one guy
one at a time.
So that took seven steps for this guy
to receive and add up all of the things.
So seven steps.
But if this one sends to this
one, and this one sends to this one,
this one sends to this one,
and this one sends to this one,
that can happen all at
one time, and that's one step.
And then the next step,
and then the final step.
And I basically got log base two of eight,
because there was that many processes,
I got three levels to this tree.
And three is a lot fewer than
eight, or eight minus one is seven, right?
So as the number of
processes of communicating gets larger,
everybody's going to just wind
up giving this one answer here.
What we're doing is we're just
adding up a bunch of numbers.
We needn't do it one
at a time with one guy.
We might as well do it
in parallel in this tree type structure.
Does that make sense?
Unfortunately, the writing of the
code for that is more complicated.
Because the thing about
the other one is true.
It's like for i equals one to
seven, send, receive, receive,
receive, receive, receive, receive.
What does this guy do?
He doesn't do anything
but just one thing, send.
Send.
There's no is statement.
There's no computation.
There's no weird stuff.
Just send it to the first guy.
You're going to get it.
The other guy's going to
do a single tightly messed loop
and say, receive,
receive, receive, receive,
plus equals, plus equals, plus equals.
He's going to have his bubbles on.
So the number of communication steps here,
we want to go from order P
to order log base two of P
to the number of
communication steps, if you will,
by doing this
tree structure communication.
There's another way it could be done.
Now, you've probably heard of, like, have
you ever heard of, like, a map reduce?
Like, the word map reduce?
You know, a new file system map reduce
some of these sort of things in a database
where you can do reduction calculations
on things in a tree structured way.
A reduction operation is
like what we're doing here.
It's a single map
operation that we're doing
to all of the data that's being sent.
In this case, all
the data, our individual integers,
our floating point
numbers, or whatever, and
the operation we're doing to add it.
So we're trying to reduce all
of this data to a single value.
That's where the word reduce comes from.
So MPI reduce, oh, I guess
I can't undo that for whatever reason.
MPI reduce is a
collective communication which says,
I want to have, you know,
that kind of thing going on.
If I say, if I want to reduce
it down to process zero has the answer,
then process one through P minus one
are all going to get somehow or another
in some sort of tree kind of fashion.
Eventually, this guy will have
the total sum down there.
If it's a sum, or it could
be a product, or it could be this,
or it could be a, it could
be a lot of different types of operations.
But what this is allowing us to do
is to, is to not have to code up
that tree structure send and
receive point to point thing
and do it automatically
with a built-in MPI function.
So if you think about
it, instead of back over here,
having this thing here where process zero
is doing all of the reducing himself
by having to receive
from everybody except for himself
in that loop that's order P.
There's some P processes.
This is going to take, and it's
going to implement this strategy for us
by doing a tree structured
communication thing in the background.
And the cool part about that is, is
that what about if the network was fancy?
What about if the network was also a tree?
That allows the people who implement
the MPI to make the communication pattern
match the network topology to better use
the hardware in
conjunction with the software.
Like, you don't have to have a
tree network to do a tree operation.
But if they were to
match, wouldn't that probably be better?
So the more knowledge you have
about the hardware network you're on,
the better you would be
able to do this reduction.
So by us saying, if
we tried to do reduction ourselves,
we wouldn't know that, right?
We as programmers, but
like whoever wrote MPI reduce,
for this particular implementation of
MPI that's running on this particular
fancy multi-million dollar network,
they figured out a way to do
it that is
the quickest, highest bandwidth,
lowest latency, fewest number of
steps possible to do reduction operation.
They take into account
all the weird scenarios, like,
what about if there's only
this? What about if it's that?
What about if these two processors are
close to each other on the network
and these are far away, I'll
do that one first and this one,
and I'll do it in a way that it actually
matches the structure of the
hardware that it's on, right?
But that's not all that
different than the way compilers work.
You take a language and
compile it down to hardware,
that compiler is not agnostic
to the hardware it's running on.
But it's trying to compile it to be the
best it could possibly
be on that target architecture.
But here, it's not just a
computer, it's a
network, it's everything, right?
Because it's the entire
cluster being used at once.
So, let's look at the prototype for this.
This is a pointer to the
data that you want to receive.
Or send out, this is the
stuff that you want to receive.
This is the number of
elements that you want to do.
It's the data type, like say in this
case float if you're
doing a reduction sum.
And this is where you tell
it, I want to do a sum.
So, there's the MPI operator.
So, you would have MPI
underscore sum here, for example.
So, MPI underscore sum, all right?
And these would be the buffers.
So, the send buffers
and receive buffers here, okay?
And then what you've
got down here is, okay,
we have to send this stuff and receive
it in such a way that, you know,
the answer can be calculated.
How much is everybody,
how much is everybody sending?
They're just sending one double, right?
Okay.
So, let's go look at
what operations that you have.
So, you can do max, min, sum.
Where are you going to find
the max of a bunch of values?
Cool, doing things you've got
to reduce, using the min, max.
Notice some operation challenges.
So, you can send min, max, sum,
product, logical and,
bitwise and, logical or,
bitwise or, exclusive or, the
location of the maximum value,
the location of the minimum value.
Notice you don't have
subtraction here, or division.
Because remember, with summations,
a times b times c is supposed to be
the same thing as b times c times a,
same thing with summations.
But subtraction, that's not the case.
The order matters, right?
Division, the answer matters.
So, you can't do a reduction
operation on those because it doesn't
mathematically work out.
You can't, you can't say what
order it has to happen, right?
It would literally have to happen in
a particular order depending on the thing.
That allows no flexibility if you're
trying to do it in parallel.
Therefore, those aren't things that you
would want to have a reduction operation
on because they don't mathematically
not equal to each other, right?
But it should be the
case, except for round off errors,
that adding a bunch of stuff
in the same order or different order
should be roughly the same number.
Multiplying stuff shouldn't matter.
You know, ordering a
bunch of numbers, should I?
Or it's a or b or b or a.
So, it has to be something,
a set of these reduction operators
for which the math stuff makes sense.
So, best collective versus
communication, point to point.
So, all processes in the communicator must
make the same collective function at all.
That's kind of weird because point
to point, it would be like,
if I'm ranked zero, do a receipt.
Else, if I'm everybody
else, do a send, right?
So, we've got like a
conditional execution of MPI call.
But what they're saying is when
you do collective, you can't do that.
Literally, everybody who's
calling the function
has to call the exact
same function at the same time.
You can't be like, if I'm
this, I'll do
this collective communication.
Else, somebody else is going
to do a different collective.
No, it's going to be the same one.
They all have to call the same function.
You see that's the difference between the
other way where you use your rank
to specify which function you call.
Here, what you'd be
using your rank for possibly
is to figure out which
value you want to do.
If you need to index
into something to grab that,
that might be a function of your rank.
So, if you try to do something like this,
mixing a collective communication with
a single point to point,
that's not going to work.
The arguments passed by
each process must be compatible.
So, it says like, let's see.
So, if one process puts
the destination as the destination process
and another one passes it as one,
then that's going to be a problem.
Because when you do a
reduction, you're trying to say,
which rank is supposed
to have the final answer?
Where's the final answer going?
Is it rank zero?
Is it rank one?
Then they wouldn't be agreeing
on who is the person
that's supposed to have the final answer.
That's often referred to as
the root of the collective communication,
of the reduction operation.
Now, not every argument is
used by everybody in the call.
Think about it.
If I'm going to
reduce down to process zero,
process zero won't be
sending anything, will it?
And if I'm everybody else,
they won't be receiving anything,
at least if they are
receiving something, it's
internal and hidden.
We can't tell because it's being received
by that tree
communication thing internally, right?
We're not satisfying that.
It's like, reduction means
everybody sends to zero,
but how the sending is happening
is this tree thing in the center.
So, they still have to
pass in a valid argument, though.
There has to be
an argument that's in there,
even if that argument
is just a null pointer.
So, you can't just be like,
I'm not going to pass anything.
First of all, how am I going to see here?
So, if there are n arguments,
you have to pass all in over.
There's no, like, stuff like you've
got, say, like a Java Python
where you can pass in one
argument or two arguments or three,
and it calls a
different implementation of those things.
That's not the way this is.
Every call has to have every parameter.
Even if you say, ignore this
by passing in a null pointer.
Same way that,
like, before, with point-to-point,
they had to have a tag.
Well, that's not the case here.
The fact that they're all in
the same communicator is a tag,
meaning they all are part of that.
Everybody's calling it, so they're
all in the same communication.
Yeah, the exercise center right there.
They're doing it by
way of the communicator.
So, let's just get to an actual program,
and let's take a look at
it and see how they did it.
Now, you can do it all in redos.
That means everybody gets the answer,
not just one rank.
Everybody gets all the answers.
So, it's kind of like
if everybody's got separate data,
at the end, you know,
it has to say that
everybody sends all of that data
to everybody else.
If you kind of look at this right here,
they all wind up getting equivalently
what the answer would have been
if they hadn't done it.
If this guy was the destination,
and them, and them, and them, and them,
everybody winds up having the answer.
Remember I said that sometimes you
need everybody to have the answer?
Then you want to do an
all-reduce if they all get the answer.
Now, only one of them did, though.
You'd be better off
calling it just the reduce,
because the all-reduce, you can imagine,
is more complicated because it
involves more people communicating, right?
Let's get down to an actual thing, though.
Okay, so there's the broadcast.
I didn't want to do this next.
I wanted to do...
I wanted to look
at the trapezoid thing here.
You know, let's just start that.
Like over here.
Yeah, this is what I wanted to do.
I want to look at this.
So let's over to this in a
way that it'll look better than that.
Let's go over here.
Let's see what kind of stuff they did
by the time they got to version 4.
So every time the author is
just adding more and more specificity,
more and more control, more
and more correctness to this thing.
Hopefully more and more
performance to it, right?
That's what you're doing.
See, they compounded it the same way.
They executed it the same way.
So that looks the same.
Let's see what the parameters
are there at the end
that we're dealing with here.
Ooh, this got derived data types.
Yeah, so let's take a look
and see what all we've got here.
So go ahead and initialize it.
It looks like they're not
using argc and argv here, though.
What are they still doing?
They're getting to starting at
end of points and stuff
from the user still, apparently.
Makes this bigger.
All right, so...
I'd contend that you'd want to
get it from the command line
rather than having to literally
sit there and type stuff
into the thing.
Maybe they'll make
that a homework assignment
to modify this to fix that.
So let's see.
Initialize and figure out,
you know, who I am,
how many of them some are there.
Pass those two parameters to get input.
And an address, a, b, and n.
Now, let's just go back up here.
a, b, and n should
be the beginning and the ending
and the number of elements, yeah.
So, again, ending,
so, double, double, int.
You'll notice I'm
constantly looking at types
because we're in C now, you know,
and this is a
strongly typed situation here.
We really need to look at the types
because it'll let you do
stuff where the types won't match
and it'll be jacked up.
You've got to look at it.
Looks like they do the
same little deal they did before.
They're still not worrying
about whether or not
it's easily divisible by
the number of processes,
so they're still having
that integer problem, you know,
instead of beginning and ending the thing.
And look at this.
Now, this thing is
not, it's not returning.
It's not returning a thing.
So how is it actually returning
the parameters a, b, and c
that a, b, and n
that it got from the user?
Look at that.
We get input.
There's nothing to be
returned out of this.
How's it doing?
It's doing it by reference, by pointer,
because it's passing the
address of these things.
Remember that from 2010, a, b,
and c, a, b, and n
are sitting on the stack.
So we're passing the address on the stack
wherever those are.
So when this function gets called,
that literally is using
the address of something
that's in the caller's
stack to reach back outside
of his memory space and
touch the other guy's stuff
in the stack, which is kind of weird.
That's dangerous, right?
That's where the problems come from.
That's just the way c is.
That's the way it is.
Probably kind of neat to look at,
to see how they did this.
So the reason they needed to know the rank
and the communicator is
because the way they're
going to wind up getting it here,
let's not worry about this in a second.
The way they wind up doing it is saying,
if I'm this guy, I'll
do the print and the scan,
and I'll be the only
guy that gets the information.
But I've got to get it out to everybody,
because all the other
processes need to know
what those things are.
So I'm going to
broadcast it to them, right?
And this is a pointer
to A, a pointer to B,
and a pointer to N,
because what they came in
are pointers, right?
And not saying that
by default assumes that it's
a pointer to the buffer.
And because these
things are already buffers,
you don't have to have
an address operator over here, okay?
Now broadcast.
What is AP?
Well, that's a pointer.
He's put an underscore
P for a pointer here.
So underscore A. OK, so
they broadcast underscore A here.
Now what is this thing over here?
What is all this?
Now this is interesting.
That was the pointer
associated with this double.
But now we've got to build data type.
What's this build data type do?
Now notice, there's only one broadcast.
There's not three broadcast
for all those three pieces
of information.
There's only one.
So what do you figure
is going on in the background
to make it so that
instead of me having to send
three different things, I'm
only sending one thing?
It's building some kind of
structure to hold all three
of those things at the same
time so that it can send it.
Does that kind of make sense?
So it's building one of these structures.
You didn't need to do this.
You could have just literally
made a typical C struct,
and you could have just
populated it with the pieces
and sent the address of the struct
in the correct number of
bytes, and it would have worked.
Now you could also create
some things that are called unions.
You could do some interesting
things and see to pack stuff
together in a way that makes sense.
But in this case, I guess
since he's going all in on MPI,
he wants to do it the MPI way.
To show you how you
could build an arbitrary data type.
You can build a data
type that's got three ints,
two characters, one float, six bells.
I can build whatever I want.
And then when I go send
it, I just send the entire thing.
And which type is it, but
it's the type that I just created
and I built this thing into.
So that's the data type that's being sent.
Not a double, not a min, not
a float, but this weird data type.
And this weird data type is
a packing of all these things
into a single thing.
Does that kind of make sense?
So that way I only have
to send one of these things.
But now the cost of this
thing here passed this data type
by reference here.
It probably malleaked space
to hold that stuff dynamically.
So it did some kind
of internal call to allocate space.
And remember in C,
there's no garbage collection.
It doesn't deallocate anything unless
you tell it to deallocate.
So that's why this is here.
It says, hey, by the
way, you know, this stroke,
I just dynamically created it
with this type in it.
Now I don't need that anymore.
This function will return.
That stroke will be
sitting out there in memory
and not deallocated.
Because look, even though this
thing here will go away,
the thing that it pointed
to would not go away.
So now we would have
what's called what, leaked memory.
We would be leaking it.
Because we would have that
many data that existed in memory.
It's no longer needed.
We can't access or deallocate
later because the pointer to it
is gone.
The pointer to it is right here.
But remember, this pointer, as
you guys remember in 210,
is a variable inside
this guy's stack frame.
But whenever that guy returns,
his stack gets popped off.
So those variables aren't there anymore.
So even though this
pointer pointed to a stroke
that contained three different
numbers, 20 bytes a sub,
we couldn't deallocate it later.
So they're saying, hey, let me
go ahead and deallocate it now.
Because this variable still exists.
In this case, it's got a scope.
So I can deallocate it.
And then after I return
here, any memory I dynamically created
is now dynamically removed.
Because maybe we're not
going to use it again.
Now, if we were going to use it again,
we would also probably need
to have access to that pointer.
We could do that.
We'd have to return
it some hour and other.
Or maybe instead of declaring it here,
we would have declared
it in main stack frame
and passed it by reference.
Instead of creating it
as a local variable here
and then passing the address over here,
it would already be an
address that I had passed
by reference from main stack frame.
So there's a bunch of
stuff with all this pointer stuff
as I mentioned that's going on in here.
Now, again, what would be a way
to just get rid of all of this?
Just passing stuff in the
arguments in the command line.
Let's do that.
Let's go back up to the main program.
To get the information, we use
it and chop up the problem
like we did before.
We call the integration
on just the sub part.
That gives us a local
sum that we've gotten so far.
Now, look at this.
Look at what?
Let's add up all of the partial sums.
Instead of having that loop that
we had before with main doing it,
it's just one global reduction sum.
So we call it MPI reduced.
Remember, everybody's calling it now.
All of them.
The process is zero and everybody else.
And it's passing an address to local int.
It's passing an address of total int.
Now, here's the thing.
Local int refers to the
local integration, the partial sum.
Total int is what the global sum
is going to add up to be.
So if you think about it,
this is like the input variable
and this is like the output variable.
We're going to take all
of the, everybody's ones of this,
add it together to get
a single one of that.
Does that make sense?
We're going to deal with one
double reporting a sum operation on it.
This is the root.
This is the guy I
want to have the final answer.
And this is the communicator, which is
I need everybody to participate in it.
Now, I want you to think about this.
Let's suppose there
were just three processes.
So we've got process zero, one, two.
Let's look at the variables here.
Everybody's going to have a local int.
Everybody's going to have a total int.
Those things are declared
in the stack up there.
So those are all
variables that will happen.
Total, total, total.
And literally everybody calls NPI reduce
and it passes this and this.
This guy passes this D2.
This guy passes these two.
But not only one of those
ones that have any value in it,
that mean anything prior to me
calling the reduction is a local int.
That's the only one
it's ever written into.
But where's this other
variable, this total int?
It's not ever even initialized.
Yet we're passing it.
Passing the address of this
here, the address of this here,
and the address of this here.
If we go down there, it's
passing the address
of all those variables.
Passing a pointer.
Everybody's passing the
address of this variable.
So let's draw their stack.
Their stack is out there.
These two things are in it.
We're going to pass the address of it.
So like 0x something
and the other variables here.
So like total and local.
Let's say they're adjacent to each
other in any round of the stack.
They probably aren't.
But let's say they are.
He has an address.
He has an address for now.
Now for process 0, does he have a
local int that's equal
to something right now?
Because he did his
part of the travel order.
So there's an actual
real number in an error.
This guy has a separate stack.
But those two variables, he
did his miss guy's stack.
This process over here, those two
variables exist in the miss guy's stack.
They all have a local int value.
But none of them have
anything in this location right now.
That's garbage.
I mean, there's going
to be something there.
I don't know what it is.
But it's going to be there.
And then when you do the reduction,
you're passing the address of this here,
the address of this this here,
the address of this this here.
So what does in the average do?
Don't worry.
The background gets performing the
reduction of all of these things.
And when it's all said and done,
where is he going to have the answer?
Well, only one guy's
going to have the answer.
The root.
Right zero.
This guy right here, right zero.
This will have this will be okay.
But now over here on
these, those don't mean anything anymore.
But everybody had to call it.
Right.
They don't they don't need anything
because they don't have they don't have
they don't have the answers in there.
Does that make sense?
So I worked on the non-root
processes with printout total over here.
I don't know what I would find.
But over here, at least it should
be because that's where the destination is
supposed to wind up being
in that total in capital.
Does that make sense?
So it's kind of weird that
you're passing arguments that aren't used.
But the call has to be the same.
So you got to pass it.
They might say, well,
why don't we do this?
Why don't we just pass
a null value up to it?
Let's just do that
because they're not being used.
They're not being sent.
I'll just pass a null right there.
Would that be totally okay for this guy?
Because he ain't using it.
That'd be totally okay with this guy.
He would be using it.
Guess what's going to
happen right over here?
Use the whole familiar thing
that you see in the scene.
Segmentation fault.
Bus errors.
It's going to blow up.
Because he expects this to be
the address of a valid memory location
into which to put my answer.
Well, if it was null, it's
going to be a null pointer violation.
Never try to direct a small pointer.
It's going to blow up.
And I said, okay, cool.
I got it.
Here's what I'm doing.
If I'm ranked zero, I'll pass a non-null,
but else I'll just pass a null.
Who cares?
If it's not being used,
what difference does it make?
A pointer is a pointer.
It matches.
So don't make the code more
complicated than it needs to be.
In fact, it looks better this
way because once you start out
a bunch of these statements,
you start introducing a possibility
that not everything is actually
being called the right way.
You just have to be careful.
So anyway, it looks like
we're one minute over here.
I'll tell you what.
For Tuesday night, I'm going
to post this thing today.
I really will.
I will start thinking, no, I'm going out.
I've never posted these things.
And I'm going to post it today.
Tuesday night, I want this program
fixed so that it gets the stuff
from the command line.
I don't want it to be
called anything from you get input.
I just want it to be fixed
so that it works correctly as is,
but getting the stuff from
the command line like this.
Whatever this program is
called, trap four, right?
Three parameters, A, B, N.
So instead of getting A, B, N
from the scan F inside the get input,
it's going to get A, B, N from
the R to V from the command line.
So we're going to be using R, C, and R, V.
Okay?
That'll be the thing.
And then it'll be what you're
going to submit is the code itself.
It's going to be a Word document.
The Word document, you're going
to tell what you did.
How you did it, why you
did it wrong, blah, blah, blah.
And you're going to take a screenshot
of the thing working with your user ID
all out of the expanse, assuming
we can do expanse of work.
If not, then better get
a word on our computers, right?
And then that'll be that.
That's all right.
I mean, that shouldn't be too hard.
That's trivial, right?
I mean, that's just like comment out one
line, put in two lines, and that's it.
That's all there is, right?
It shouldn't be too bad.
All right.
Have a good weekend.
Is there any better way to exit out of
the, like, get word
in and interact with section
to get a negative just
in command to leave it?
Like, if you're logged into
a node and you want
to get out of it,
you just type exit, yeah.
Yeah, I mean, exit would be preferable to
you just letting it
sit there because when you
type exit, say you've only used 10 minutes
versus it sitting there
burning up all 30 minutes
or whatever.
Yeah, so it's working out.
I wonder what happened.
That's weird.
I started to do that.
I was really freaking out
on my first grand thing.
I was like, all right, now.
Like, I believe that's the same thing that
I had to go to make at first.
Yeah, it was like just working for me.
And then when I exited and ran
it, it just gave me that error.
Good.
When y'all had the same
problem, I started feeling better.
I was like, okay.
Just like, either my
account's best, though, right?
Literally, it's typing the wrong
thing over here or something.
But anyway, you guys have
a good weekend, all right?
Yeah, you too.
Take care.
Yep.