I need to do that. I'm probably going to mess this up.
How do you say I'm going to try to do it right now?
I'm just going to try to let it GBK.
GBK?
GBK.
I said G is G.
Got it.
Anthony.
William Morgan.
Lakota.
Piper.
Mike.
Mike S.
Farooq.
Adrian Reyes.
Arthur.
Colleen.
Sophia.
Rafael.
Jake.
Rodney.
Amelia.
Damari.
Yeah, y'all.
All right, cool.
See you later.
Thank you.
Thanks.
All right.
So for the first 30 minutes of class here, we're going to have an invited guest that
will tell us a little bit about artificial intelligence and machine learning.
So I'm going to welcome Dr. Nathan DiBargo-Leban here.
I've known him since 1997 when we took linear algebra together.
And he got his master's, bachelor's master's and PhD at Clemson University in computer
engineering.
And then he got a job at Los Alamos in 2004 and has been there since that time.
He's a senior scientist there.
And I'm going to say this too, with respect to AI and ML, of all the people I know, Nathan
is who I've considered the foremost expert in AI and ML that I know.
And I'm sure there are other folks that are more expert.
But in terms of that, to give you some context, he knows a lot more about it than I do.
And he's given a talk later today that I'd highly encourage you to come see at 4.30.
It's in the Johnson Auditorium, which is in the wall building on the first floor.
It's called room 116.
It's right there in the center of the building, a little atrium there.
There are going to be some refreshments afterwards.
And when I say that, I don't know what that means.
That could be cheese and crackers.
That could be something else.
I don't know.
I just know some food will be there.
And in that particular talk, he's going to really dive deep into some very specific science
obligations where AI and ML have come to bear and born fruit and are doing things.
And this is going to get kind of more of an introduction.
So he's not going to talk about that stuff.
So if you're thinking, hey, I'm hearing this and I was thinking about going, that is the same thing.
It's not the same thing.
So I highly encourage you to come to that.
But anyway, like I said, we've got about 30 minutes to do the thing.
We'll have about five minutes for questions.
Then he'll leave, and we'll pick up and start looking at our midterm exam that's coming up
and start talking about what we need to do to get prepared for that.
All right?
Thanks for coming and talking with us today.
I appreciate it.
Yeah, so thanks for the introduction.
Yeah, this is a different slide deck.
Different slides than this afternoon.
So this is more, like Dr. Jens said, about the field of AI and ML.
The one this afternoon is going to be some cool uses of what we're actually doing with this,
how those elements, and also some modifications about where I think the world's going
and how it's going to change the way we write code and influence other industries and stuff like that.
So it'll be a little bit of that for people that come to it from other departments
that don't want to do computing because they don't want to just see all science.
Maybe they're from the humanities department and stuff like that and see how this plays.
The Salomon National Lab may know of, I hope you know of,
but it asks for more and more people that don't know it, so I'll take a moment to say
that's where Einstein, Oppenheimer, Feynman, all work.
John's on Neumann, on Neumann Architecture.
The architecture is behind all of our modern computers.
This is all worked in Los Alamos.
This isn't to say I'm cool.
This is to give you a location for what this is.
This lab was the one that started the Manhattan Project
and where we built the first atomic weapon.
All the national labs across the country,
including even down here in the Savannah River,
what's called the Savannah River site, contributed to that effort.
But the science of the weapon was done at Los Alamos.
These days we do a lot of things related to national security essentially.
There are other labs you'd go to if you wanted to work on open science.
Our stuff is really generally not incredibly open.
And we hire people all the time.
We have lots of relationships with people with undergrads all the way to postdocs.
It's not only PhDs.
I'll think to your club just because anything's got a PhD.
It's not right for me at my point.
We bring in summer students all the time that have sophomores,
juniors, seniors, and stuff like that.
We help train them and give them things for the resumes.
I can't share or wonder what this kind of thing looks like.
I'm in a group.
I'm in a division called High Force Computing HPC.
I'm in a group called HPC Design.
We're sort of more academically of High Force Computing.
And I'm a team lead of an applied machine learning group.
I'll sort of talk about diversity in machine learning and AI.
Actually, that's most of what I'll talk about in this presentation.
So folks here on my team, I just want to comment here.
This lady, Leslie Horace, she did an undergrad here at Coastal.
She's now doing graduate work at Georgia Tech.
Shawn Johnson, undergraduate at Coastal.
These both people work for me.
Stevie Penn is an undergraduate at Coastal.
So I really am serious when I say that we hire people in these spaces.
I have sort of two hats I wear.
I'm in charge of machine learning for manufacturing efforts at Los Alamos.
So we manufacture cool stuff.
They're really expensive to manufacture custom stuff.
And as you've done at Atlanta and can't be off,
user time usually cannot be shipped off to like a fabricator in the area.
So we have a lot of machinery on site to do that.
I hope many acres did mitigate that.
I think sort of gets involved in studying that data
and helping them understand whether they're doing a good job
and what they can learn from it.
And also, I am the co-leader of this area called AI for Mission Artemis.
That's our $20 million a year investment in AI.
That's the biggest AI investment in all of the Department of Energy
across the entire country.
So that's kind of what I'm talking about mostly this afternoon.
That's all I'm talking about here today.
I need to end this session.
I'm going to mostly talk about AI and ML.
The first couple of slides here,
I don't really intend to go through it very heavily.
I just wanted to, for some audiences, there's this,
how is AI changing the world?
And I'm going to hope you guys already bought into this notion
that AI is changing the world.
We're seeing it in areas related to simulation science,
particularly at Los Alamos, drug discovery.
This one's kind of cool.
Oak Ridge National Lab, really close by in Tennessee.
A lot of folks in this area go and work there.
This is in Knoxville, Tennessee.
It's in Oak Ridge.
It's right next to Knoxville.
Frontier is one of the world's fastest supercomputers.
They're in a span of about a year.
Almost all of the jobs that ran on there,
kind of, this is a parallel computing class, right?
Jobs that you run in there, like on TAC, that kind of parallel jobs,
went from what are called mods and modeling simulation,
major multiplication type stuff, solving cool things,
to some version of AI in the course of a year, right?
And so, like, the deep science phase is moving, hammering this.
This is not just Josh EBT.
This is not just, you know, well,
Matt has got some cool bots that I can talk to this time.
This is way, way, way more advanced than that.
And if you do all that you see, that's what the community talks about.
It's fine.
But I want you to sort of take away from this that it is more than that.
We're seeing lots of cool solutions.
There's some really cool computer science problems, like solving things like
new matrix multiplication algorithms,
the first improvement in over half a century,
entirely developed by AI algorithms.
And you might have seen, maybe of course you studied things like sorting algorithms
and searching algorithms and bin mapping problems.
Those were real fun to solve in some of these spaces.
This one actually is about a language, a language space.
The power of energy and our government is pushing very hard in this area.
We'll talk a little bit this afternoon about what we're calling the Manhattan Project 2.0.
And that project is that effort I talked about that was in the 40s,
an Oppenheimer movie.
You know, Los Alamos, this was recently announced at a visit to Los Alamos
by Secretary of Energy Chris Wright.
I'll talk about him this afternoon.
So we're going to start going really heavily into this space as a nation,
investing in this space.
Again, not just language models.
And, you know, Judge, if you don't rewrite my email better or something like that,
this is much more advanced than what you'll see in the coming years.
Power of energy has been putting a lot of effort into this space, sort of preparing for it.
We're seeing things like AI automation and computer programming.
I'll show some examples of that this afternoon if you happen to come to that talk.
So you want to do AI hardware and particularly accelerating HPC simulations
in the spaces that I care about.
I saw recently someone say that the protein folding stuff that was done by AI
might be the biggest accomplishment of AI that we've ever seen.
That's a accomplishment you should really look to for what's going on in that space.
You all probably use these tools besides.
You probably use things like Mid-Journey or Dolly to make cool images and fun stuff.
The algorithms behind that stuff talk a tiny bit about the next couple of slides.
I find most people don't know the difference between AI and ML.
I will say, however, I'll give you a definition of what I think that is.
I will say that I'm not a professor.
It's on my job to make sure you guys know the distinction between these two.
I'll say that generally this space is lowering a lot.
So people usually just say AI for this stuff.
Maybe it'll be helpful for you to understand what I really believe the difference
between these two things are and you can sort of think about them.
Machine learning is a subset of AI, and so we'll talk about what that is in a second.
But it's worth noting that for a second.
Generally, people say AI is this category of things that requires
machines to carry out things that would be what we call smart.
And that's super fuzzy, right?
There's nothing concrete to grab onto in that statement.
So I would regret you if you thought you didn't say anything useful to me yet.
These typically are our human intelligence.
So if we generally define this space with examples,
like problem-solving speakers, speech recognition, decision-making,
particularly with imperfect knowledge, right?
So like, you know, patting from here to a restaurant you want to go to for lunch, right?
I mean, that's, you may know the way you're used to going,
but of course, it's all this data that maybe it has about what's going on right now
with traffic jams and accidents or weather or what impacted that,
other people on the pathway.
And so these algorithms actually employ a lot of those techniques.
So that's not similar to GPT.
It's not similar to some of the machine learning stuff we'll talk about here.
An example of this would also be like playing games.
And so if you think about a simple game like chess or checkers,
you might think there's two ways we could solve this.
We could either take the state of the game at some point,
you know, chess board or checkers board at some point,
and I'm going to be one of the players and then the computer's,
or my opponent's going to be the other player,
and I'll pick the best move I could do
and then I'll pretend I'm playing the other player
and pick the best move that they will do.
I'll run through all possible simulated situations of the moves I can make
and I'll keep like some giant scoreboard
and through that method I can figure out the best move for me
to maximize my score, right?
And that is an algorithm that's very simple, very commonly done.
It's called MiMax.
It's something you study in an early AI class,
not a machine learning class, but an early AI class at graduate level.
We'll talk about it all in a couple of slides.
Obviously that's hugely computationally intensive.
Searching that entire space is, let's call it, impossible.
For any problem that's being complex, if you want to solve it with a chess or checker,
it's essentially impossible.
What normally what these algorithms do is they instead sort of have like a budget
and they say like, well, I'm going to make this many checks
or I'm going to check for this amount of time.
And so when you're playing like a game, often you say the computer takes its turn
and it's got a certain amount of, always takes a second or something like that.
It's actually, usually what's going on in this case is they're exploring
all possible outcomes that they can in the one second
that the programmer is given to make that decision.
And usually it would be a breadth-first search rather than a depth-first search, right?
So you see as many plays you could possibly make quickly
and try to get an idea of which one of those is going to lead you to the best outcome.
When you play an easy computer or medium or hard difficulty video game,
like this literally, that's how these algorithms are designed.
Like, should I check the best option or should I make a sub-optimal option
because I'm playing an easy difficulty?
Machine learning is a subset of that, which is a different way of looking at that problem
and instead we're going to train it based on previous experiences.
And so this example I gave with checkers or chess,
like you're basically playing the game of chess in a simulation.
This way it would be a different way.
It would be like, I've got a lot of historical data from chess games.
When the boards were exactly in this state, when the player made this move,
what's the probability that either they won or they ended up with a better score
or the next move was advantageous?
So that requires a massive ton of data.
Maybe it's larger search data.
You have these databases of previous experiences and stuff like that.
That's not normally how that particular problem is solved,
but it's often the way we're going to solve some very common problems.
And so we'll go through a couple of those examples.
I will say if you're thinking to yourself, you know,
what am I likely to do in my career if I'm going to be in this general area?
I say with high probability of work in this machine learning area,
it's way more common, it's way more applicable to an average company,
a banking company, a factory, anything you work in.
It's almost certainly going to be this.
It's not going to be this deep human intelligence type stuff.
This is a rare space.
Certainly we see lots of this.
It's just behind lots of stuff that you use and you don't really recognize it.
And so there's a couple of main categories this is divided into,
supervised, unsupervised, and reinforcement learning.
We'll give a quick example of each of those in the coming slides.
Supervised learning is interesting because it's the notion of labeled data.
And so it's like if you have, you know, something going on in a factory line,
you know, shoes that are being made,
and you've got employees that are on that line that are looking for
whether they're defective or not, they're going to bin them into good,
you know, sell these shoes or trash them because they're broken.
If you have some humans there, they're pushing them into these bins.
Actually what they're doing is they're labeling that data for you.
So if you had a camera over top of the, that's capturing that shoe coming down,
you actually can connect that with the labeled data that says,
this shoe, and from this photo, some human put it into a bad category.
And you don't know what was bad about it.
And that's going to be one of the challenges.
And we'll talk about machine learning.
Like how do you categorize what made that thing bad
because where these algorithms actually take advantage of.
So if I were to ask you to write code to differentiate these,
your job, you were in a new company,
your factory apparently makes these four things.
You're going to stuff them into four bins at the end of the factory line.
So you're thinking to yourself, okay,
this is the only thing my company makes.
So people do based on color.
We just add up all the pixel intensities.
We'll bin them based on this.
Bad idea.
But obviously if you're a company that starts making different color shoes,
or it's got this thing, it's got bruises on it,
or this is maybe cut open a little bit or something like that,
or the stem is missing.
The color, so maybe people do it in a circular.
The shoe is rotated.
She's never going to be exactly in this position.
That's a really hard problem, a surprisingly hard problem to solve.
It's making it even harder.
These are some funny examples of things too.
There's Joao or a muffin.
This is a classic one that people love.
So maybe you're thinking to yourself, okay, okay.
So these animals have three of these orbs, eyes and noses.
But I can just count these sort of black regions.
So maybe you do that.
And this one's got more than that, so it's clearly not a Joao.
It's clearly not a Joao.
This one's only got three, if you sort of ignore these ones.
Crap, that makes it harder.
This one would certainly pass as a Joao in there.
But your eyes, no problem, right?
There's no doubt that there's people in here that are confused as a Joao.
And so what's going on there?
It's just tons of evolution in us have made it so that this is very easy to differentiate.
But writing an algorithm to do that is surprisingly complex.
And so we're actually not going to solve that by doing things like counting orbs.
And we're going to solve it through other ways.
And that's this labeled data.
That's that person on the factory line that has labeled this.
Here's another cool example.
This one's puppy or bagel.
Those curled up puppies in this example.
So again, maybe hard to write, likely hard to write code for that.
But very easy for machine learning algorithms, out of the box.
You can do this in seconds with these algorithms.
Now, one thing to note, though, is that this is what's called labeled data.
It's labeled data in what you're doing in your head.
You're differentiating this dog and bagel.
How do we get that labeled data?
That's usually very costly.
And so when you go to work for a company, you're unlikely to be actually sorting puppies and bagels.
You're going to be sorting things that your company makes,
transactions, like in a credit card company or whatnot.
And so you won't have this good labeled data.
So you often start from existing algorithms and sort of modify them into this space.
In fact, you probably, you may not know this,
but all those years you've been feeding into these capture kits
where you've been labeling stuff to prove you're a human,
where's the ladder or the street sign or whatever,
you're actually labeling behind the scenes for these data sets.
So you've actually been feeding into this.
And then also when you're uploading photos to Snapchat and Facebook and Instagram or whatnot,
when you put text in them that say things like somewhere in this image,
this is me and Bob, we eat some sushi.
You don't go through it and highlight that sushi in there with enough of those images.
Now, I'll have somewhere, some caption of sushi in it.
These algorithms can actually start to figure out what are the commonalities
between the barriers of sushi-ness that's in these images and can pull that out.
So you're providing that label that's supervised learning.
You have that labeled data.
So we talked about supervised learning there.
So also this area called unsupervised learning,
probably more common but not as awesome to study because these are real clean.
Unsupervised learning is often called clustering.
And so you sort of take data that you don't have the groupings on
and you do algorithms that I will bother to go into explaining,
that sort of cluster and group these into some n-dimensional space.
You can think of it as two-dimensional, but they often are very high-dimensional,
so usually hard to visualize at all.
And then you find that these clusters, you usually have some sort of expert look at these clusters
and say, well, all these clusters, this particular cluster is all people that are close to football fans.
These clusters are all people that are CCU fans.
Does that suggest anything, maybe?
Is there something you can figure out from that?
Oh, look at it. These ones all live in upstate.
These would live in a lower country.
But you didn't initially go from, I knew they would live in the upstate,
and so therefore they were probably cluster fans or something like that.
So this is the other approach to these kinds of problems.
Very common, particularly in a not-clean example of datasets that you'll be using as a company.
Reinforce warning is fun, often hard to apply, but I will go through some examples here.
RL is sort of an area of machine learning and AI, but it's a subset, right? We talked about that.
But this is kind of cool.
This notion here is this is often seen in gameplay.
There's other examples that are not gameplay, like Roomba is driving across your room and whatnot.
But essentially, an agent operates on an environment, and the agent doesn't really understand the actions.
They don't understand the ramifications of their actions.
And then through those interactions, and the reward and the state change that comes out of the environment,
they begin to learn.
There's a lot of words there.
So you put a room on the floor, and you say, you're going to code this thing up.
Essentially, the way these things work is they're rewarded, there's a reward artifact here,
for covering space that it hasn't seen before and vacuuming up dirt.
It's pretty much that simple.
And so if the thing just sits there and doesn't move, it's eating a bad reward for not covering space.
If it runs over a dirt area and it was getting a nice reward for dirt and then continues to move on,
maybe it should have stayed there and stopped all the dirt up until it stops getting a reward.
It's quite literally how these are trained.
And so there's nothing, the algorithm isn't what you might assume,
which is this complex thing of mapping out the space, seeing where the walls are,
and trying to avoid them, oh, I see some dirt, I'm going to go track it down.
It's really not that.
They've trained these things in laboratories to do that kind of thing.
So even the self-driving cars, they're rewarded poorly for hitting people and simulations and stuff like that, running lights.
And so they begin to learn from that process.
And you can imagine that becomes very hard, right?
Like if suddenly there's a truck and you think you can go underneath it, something like that,
maybe you don't want to give the car reward for going underneath the truck is an intersection.
So really cool space there.
In the AI and machine learning breakdown, it's essentially this combination of data, compute, and then algorithms.
And one thing that's interesting about that is that in the data space,
this is essentially either labeled data from your customer base,
or there's people on the factory line labeling data, images that are coming off, whatnot.
You're probably going to buy your storage.
You're going to buy your networks.
You're probably not a company that's going to make these things.
And in a compute that's generally GPUs these days, there's some exotic machine learning hardware,
people like my organization like to play with, but essentially this is GPUs.
These two together, more or less, think of it like cloud today.
We don't do cloud at our institution very much, but it has to really be for security reasons.
But like, you know, if you work for a company, all the companies I know I work with, these two they combine into an AWS-like thing.
I'm using AWS as like a Kleenex, right, for a tissue.
So it's a cloud-like thing.
However, the tailored algorithms, this space is really interesting in a space that you can go and play.
And certainly you might work for a company that builds storage or networks,
or maybe enables data, or works on GPUs, or prevent data, whatnot.
There's not a lot of employees in this space is what I'm going to argue.
However, this space is where most of the employees are.
And it's not just, you know, highfalutin researchers that are going to write cool new algorithms that no one's ever seen before.
It's also people that are going to use those algorithms and apply them to your company's needs.
And so this is where people are really making a lot of the hiring.
In an area called RLHNF, I talked about reinforcement learning, this is with human feedback.
And so often you'll have the, you can connect these in.
And chatGBT has faces that real humans actually augmented the responses from this tool and said,
you know, culturally, we don't use these words or responses, or I wouldn't have chosen that word here.
That sounds too highfalutin and Shakespearean, so we would use this kind of word in our language.
And that's actually human feedback that allows these algorithms to click in.
But most of the work in this space, it is not writing brand new complex algorithms.
It's taking existing tools and modifying those to your company's needs.
And in particular, you can usually pay your way out of these problems, like AWS.
And then this is where you have to hire people.
It's a really competitive market.
I'm not surprised that someone like me would argue you should spend some time considering getting into that market.
But particularly right now, it seems to be a good market.
One thing that might be kind of cool to think about, particularly in a sort of senior level CS class,
is that most of the AI machine learning breakthroughs until recently, some sort of transponderance,
which are sort of 2018 timeframe, actually been invented in the 70s, 80s, and a little bit in the 90s.
But we didn't have the computer hardware at the top.
We didn't even know that we needed hardware liking.
It wasn't just like maybe a find that it was largely shelved.
Dr. Jones and I, even in grad school, didn't have GPUs in early grad school.
So we have led a lot of these algorithms on CPUs and C, and they would perform, do their job.
But you could see how you would need a supercomputer to run this thing on us.
You'll never apply this.
And now your phone is having these technologies on there because of these advances in this space.
So we're largely latent and waiting for the GPU hardware to come, to be inventive, if you will.
Some early grad students figured out they could use these gaming processors by entity of a GPU.
Originally, still using its graphics processing unit.
These days we often leave it as GBGB, the general purpose of graphics processing units.
They don't actually have a graphics portal to what we would use in a data center.
We don't have the actual graphic ones.
So you buy a different product, you're gaming PC, and then you do that we run in the data center.
Deep neural networks sort of came out in 2015, 2017, something around then.
And that's when sort of new technologies sort of developed.
And so what I really hands on is the vision of transformers.
You've probably heard of them, but GPT, general purpose transformer.
That's the T in the transformer in the GPT.
We use a lot of these in Los Alamos, but not so much in the language phase.
We usually use them in the vision space for different data sets.
Like I've talked a lot about factories and stuff.
We do a lot of that work in my manufacturing work.
There's this notion of something called foundation model, which I sort of mentioned here.
Foundation models are a cool term you should think about just so you know what it is.
People will say that GPT is a foundation model.
And essentially what that means is a model, not just a language model,
but a model that is trained for a general task that can then be fine-tuned for a more specific task.
And so believe it or not, these language models like GPT are quite literally trained on two main tasks.
One is next word prediction.
You literally just send in this portion of the sentence, you black out the word on,
and then you ask the thing to predict the next word.
So foundation models are typically large models that are trained blank.
And then you might say and, on, or with.
Those are okay words, it's the next sentence.
But like Halloween is probably unlikely to be the next word in that sentence.
It's literally all of those words to get probabilities.
And so they pick the next highest probable word as the next thing.
And also sometimes what we do is called ablation or masking.
So you sort of take a full sentence, you black out the word trained here.
You say, what word do you think that was?
That's how these models are trained.
That seems dumb.
It seems not very useful.
But once you train this model in this way, it's often called retraining.
You then can take it and fine-tune it for a task, like computer programming, writing comments in code,
maybe parable in size.
All those things are trained on the same foundational core task.
It's sort of akin to, like, for you to do well in calculus,
you probably had to have been trained in algebra and geometry and basic arithmetic.
And so once that information is in you, you can be tasked or fine-tuned for this new area of calculus.
So that's kind of the notion there you should think about.
Rev20, should I stop here a while?
For a canonical example.
Yeah, I was going to say maybe we could entertain some questions.
Sure.
It would probably be a great time to have some, you know, questions about AI and ML
or anything in this kind of space, but job market.
From your perspective, would you say that it might be hard to keep up with the space
and how fast pace this and some research?
Yeah, it's something I will talk a little about this afternoon,
comparing it with some other areas of technology innovations.
I'm trying to use tools to help me keep up with the space.
Yeah, I think that's the real differentiator right now,
is that we're basically on a hockey stick of progress that's come about because of this technology.
And it can feel really overwhelming, but it seems to be touching all areas,
even beyond computing, as I'm sure you're well aware.
So, yeah, I think it's a real challenge.
For a student, what would be the best way to keep up on those developments for AI and ML?
I use things like aggregators, like RCS,
to help bring in the most relevant publications or blog posts
or stuff like that in a sub-area of AI and ML that I'm interested in.
We've heard about one of the things that I use.
I use chat GPT's functionality to help me pull together my daily top five things
that I should know that are new in AI and ML.
And it's surprisingly pretty good at that.
So I get a little update every morning at 6 a.m.
That's where I'm looking at when I'm getting ready.
And each one of them has links I can check out if I want.
Let me know what's going on.
Do you have other things I'm interested in?
Is that something I can do in that space?
It's really, I guess my answer would be probably figure out the area
that you want to care about.
So like language or computer programming or VR or something like that
and then try to focus on that.
Because essentially then you're subsetting down advances to being in an area
that maybe you can absorb.
Question over there too.
So I want to know how did you get into that space
and who is sitting down working now?
Yeah.
So when I went to school at Clemson in 1995 for my undergrad,
I wanted to study robotics.
It was really, that's really what I wanted to do.
I went to the engineering program for robotics.
Interesting, by the time I got into the time with meeting some of the best
professors in the space, we were in an area that,
the time that was called the AI Winter.
You may not have heard of this.
It's okay.
But it was a time when AI was like, it was overhyped
that people could figure out how to take advantage of it.
And maybe we're going to come back into another one of those.
And so I got pushed out of that area and was told by the professors
that were leading that at Clemson to not go into that area.
So I went into parallel computing, HPC computing.
Went to Los Alamos, working on parallel computing.
I did a bunch of work on satellites and radiation effects and stuff like that.
Anyway, sort of around 2018, 2019, I was given the opportunity
to switch into leading the machine learning for manufacturing effort,
applying some of my knowledge from satellite work in that space.
And that's why I made that, I took the opportunity to make that switch.
But you asked also about how that's different from then and now.
I'd say one of the things that we're finding is the job market's really hard right now.
Hiring is getting harder and harder.
And so we're seeing the quality of our hires is going up as a company.
And so five years ago, we were hiring pretty much anyone
and then training them on the job.
These days, we're expecting people to be trained by universities
or a company with other training with another job.
And so generally, my suggestion there would be graduate schools.
I don't think, interestingly enough, something has a PhD.
I don't think you actually need a PhD in this space.
I think my master's degrees are more than enough.
Master's degree and we will usually hire ML people that have worked in this space.
Like a master's degree.
So my suggestion would be that.
The market's still pretty good where we are.
I don't know what it's like at other places.
We're expecting about a billion of the investment for the Department of Energy
in this space that's going to hit across all national labs.
So it's not just going to be in the northern New Mexico mountains
where you may not want to live.
You'll see this in Santa River down in A.K. and Oak Ridge
and all around the country.
So we're going to see these investments all around the country in this space.
And also in D.C. and stuff.
I think it's going to be okay right now.
Do you have some experience with people from Georgia Tech?
Do you think that that's a graduate program that's pretty well known
and can prepare someone for it?
Yeah, so GT has two programs that Indomaster is interested in.
One is an online master program.
I did about five, six hours of myself in there.
Really enjoyed it.
I would say that the online master's program for Georgia Tech
is what people would call a practical master's.
So it's very applied.
Use the tools to solve hard problems.
Demonstrate that you're capable.
And so people that come out of that program are very much ready
to apply their knowledge on our problems.
So I like that a lot.
They also have an in-person master's program, which is more common.
There's more people in the online one, but it's more classically common
than the in-person programs.
I would say that it would better train you for a BHD.
So if you actually do want to go for a BHD,
I would suggest an in-person program.
And then transition into a BHD there or elsewhere,
as opposed to the online ones, which are very good for practical practitioners.
But yeah, that's a good program.
The University of Illinois has a good program.
Texas has a good program.
Purdue has a good program.
Online, these are online ones.
Clemson has a great in-person program.
U.S. is actually like other than South Carolina has a good program too.
But the University has got a lot of great programs.
So you don't have to go to these other ones out in the state.
So as a person that had a lot of education, a lot of experience,
when you got these classes at Georgia Tech,
you were probably in there with people that might be like you
and also students that had just come out of undergrad.
What would you take on the level of rigor and difficulty of those classes
just on its own, but also compared to what your experience was in grad school
when you were sitting down, sitting in residence in the early 2000s?
And it's a good point.
I think everything's harder, a lot harder than it was.
I've got a daughter in undergrad at Clemson right now.
It seems to be a lot harder than when I was there.
I felt grad school was much more intellectual when I was there,
a lot more time to just sort of sit around and think
and read papers and talk about it.
The GT stuff that I did was pretty much nonstop hard work.
I had a full-time job. I did this all full-time.
I was working nights and weekends to get it done.
I always say I wasn't deployed, it would have been different.
But it's hard. I'm not going to say it's not hard by any means.
I'm sure that's the answer you want.
No, it is.
Because I've talked about this before,
a lot of times you have some of my programs that historically have been easy.
And it's interesting that they maintain this level of rigor.
Even in the day and age where things are done remotely,
the nutrition rate in the classes, you might have started with a thousand
by the time you got to the end and how many people were actually left.
Yeah, 300 per per year.
Really, I withdraw it and the university essentially pulls it off
by saying, we'll put you in the class. You've got to perform.
And so they just hit the ground running and it's an onslaught.
I'm not sure. Maybe it's useful for you to know the truth,
but it's also, I don't want to dissuade you from going into these programs.
I don't think that they're easy, but if you put your mind to it,
I'm sure you can do it. It's just a lot of focus.
You've got to be able to dedicate the time and hours to it.
Any other questions?
All right, well, thank you very much for coming today and sharing this with us again.
He's going to be available at 2030 to 530 in the fall of 2016.
And there's going to be a smaller session afterwards.
There's going to be a different talk than this.
So if you're interested in that, you know, really in this stuff,
I'd encourage you to come see it. I'll see you later. Thanks for your time.
I appreciate it.
Feel free to route through to me.
Dr. Jones knows we have lots of internships at the lab,
lots of different programs that are competed for as well.
It's as simple as just sending your resume in.
You can route it to our hiring people.
We hire, as you saw, people all the time.
Maybe more than just those ones that are on my team right now,
we brought through.
And they're also doing all kinds of other stuff from the lab, too.
So it's a good opportunity to pay the internship to come out,
to know that you have an experience, see what it's like for us for a summer.
Yeah.
And like, for example, an HPC, the senior or like,
or maybe like a post back, I mean, it's 2038 and $42 an hour.
Is that right?
That's correct. Yeah.
We pay really well.
Yeah.
So just, you know,
take care of, thank you.
All right.
So let's, let's pull up the email.
I wanted to pull that up separately here, but I sent out about,
I didn't get about the midterm exam,
but I want to kind of talk a little bit about that.
All right.
And also these are the, let's see,
Mike, Arthur, Colleen, Sophia, Rafael, Rodney, Damari,
and then if anybody wants like some extra copies,
this is a practice to play with out there.
They're up here.
Okay.
So let's see here.
I want to pull up that email.
I'm just trying to have someone look at it.
473.
And when you copy and paste this into Word,
close this.
Do not disturb.
Okay.
So I want to look particularly at the Django text here.
So check the chapters one, two, and three.
So let's come back over here and look at this stuff.
We got classes.
We got 473.
Let me see.
I think I got the books right here.
Let's see.
Chanko.
Second edition.
Let's take a look here just at the table of contents.
All right.
So I'm going to kind of look at it.
About the stuff that's in here.
Yeah, you know, this is going to be only 75 minutes, right?
You can't do this so much in 75 minutes, right?
But let's kind of do this.
I'm just going to ask some questions.
We'll get at this saying, like, hey, could you answer these things?
And then we can talk about it, too.
For example, why is it that we have this ever-increasing need for performance?
I mean, why is that the case?
We're surviving right now.
We've been surviving.
Why do we need something that's better tomorrow than what we have today?
Like, what are the driving factors?
So, yeah, we have ever-increasing population,
but we have things that still aren't solved, right?
Like, we still can't predict the weather very well.
We've been trying to do that for a long time, and we can't do it.
Why is it that we can't do it?
Well, you know, there's some science innovation that needs to take place,
but also weather prediction that is computer-based,
and it's based on models that try to calculate
what the weather's going to be tomorrow based on what's going on today.
And even if those models were perfect,
a good example of this would be,
you'd have to know exactly what was going on with weather
in every square inch of the planet right now
to really have a good idea of what's going to happen next.
But we don't have that, right? We've got low-resolution data.
We might have something that's, like, on the lowest scale,
like, pixel size of the Earth.
You know, and I know it's volumetric because it's also in the atmosphere,
but it might be one kilometer by one kilometer by one kilometer.
I mean, that's a lot of cubic kilometers all around the world.
That's a huge amount, right?
Well, what about if it was one meter by one meter by one meter,
or one inch by one inch by one inch?
You were modeling every cubic inch of atmosphere
across the entire surface of the planet.
That would be a lot more cubic inches than there are cubic kilometers, right?
So why can't we do that?
That means your grid, the matrix is bigger.
There's more cells.
You only have a certain amount right now.
You only have a certain amount of cores.
You only have a certain amount of this stuff.
So, like, these science people, they would like to be able to
model everything down to the lowest level.
Like, there are simulations that will model molecules
down to the individual atoms, okay?
But it might take two weeks to actually model that atom
over the course of, say, one picosecond.
Now, that's not going to tell you what it's going to do tomorrow, is it?
Because it's so complicated to capture the reality
when you're on this binary scale.
Because when they talk about modeling,
they're not modeling atoms.
You're not going to have an atom.
I mean, the world made out of atoms, right?
We can just model every atom on the planet.
But we can't do that because we don't have the kind of performance
that it needs.
Every time we make steps towards increasing performance,
so the degree of aerialism, the number of cores,
the amount of RAM, the cooler architectures,
the lower the latencies, increasing the bandwidths, and all this stuff,
then you make it one step closer to being able to do more accurate science
with existing things today.
I mean, kind of like what he said earlier,
like the 70s, 80s, and 90s, these things existed,
but we couldn't run them.
When I was in grad school, I did a face recognition by hand,
hand-coded an artificial feed forward neural network
with nothing but dynamics.
We took pictures of the class.
We took 10 pictures of everybody's face in different ways,
like left, right, up, down, with glasses, without hat, no hat,
smiling, frowning, and then said,
can we detect who these people are?
It took forever to train that.
Like now, on my laptop, it's like, boom, it just went like that.
It needed nothing.
To say I wanted to be able to hit 100 million people back then,
that would have been inconceivable.
So we have this need because there are still things we can't do, all right?
Now, for the time being, I'm like,
why is it that we have to write parallel programs?
Had the programs that you've written up to this class
barring possibly forking and joining in pipes,
maybe with processes in 356,
have you ever written a parallel program?
No.
And that meant that those programs, by and large,
ran on one door, and they only used a small part of the machine.
So you have to write parallel programs
to be able to effectively utilize all the machines that are there,
not only inside the thing with lots of cores,
maybe the GPU and other things, but between machines,
because you need to be able to use all the hardware.
And furthermore, like, you might be able to sell,
like, $100 million to sell on hardware.
You can't buy a single computer that's $100 million right now.
But you can buy several of them,
and you can hook them together with those parallel programs.
So we have to write parallel programs
because we can't effectively utilize all this hardware.
Now, if you think about the difference between, say,
concurrent programming and parallel programming,
think about those terms.
I know they were bolded in that chapter.
That's one of the things I said with things like,
the stuff that's bolded in these chapters conceptually,
make sure you know what those things are.
Can anybody kind of articulate it?
It doesn't matter if you're right or wrong or whatever,
but just dig a stab at, what's the difference between, say,
a concurrent program or a distributed program
and a parallel program?
Now, I'll give you an example.
Let's suppose that we're a company that runs eKarma's website,
and we've got something that's running out of the back end.
We've got this thing that's running at the front end.
We've got our databases over here.
We've got some other stuff.
And they're all coming together to make this one application.
All of those pieces of parts need to be running,
and they might actually be running on different computers,
right, to make that application.
So there are things, quote, running at the same time, right?
Like, that database is out there,
search transactions at the same time as this has had it
and all those other things.
But what's the difference between that and the program we wrote,
matrix measure multiplication?
We've got multiple processes running all at the same time.
What is the difference between what I first described
and the second thing?
That first thing is a bunch of different things.
The database is not solving the same problem
that the front end is solving.
Those are distributed, separate ideas that happen to be
connected together to solve the big problem,
which is to provide this eKarma's website, maybe,
or an app or whatever.
But it's not solving an individual problem,
whereas what we were doing is we were bringing all that together,
that parallelism, to solve a single problem,
make matrix multiplication faster, right?
That's what it was about.
All right, now, we come over here to the von Neumann architecture.
Can somebody tell me in their own words,
what is the von Neumann architecture?
Okay.
Let me draw it.
CPU, bus, RAM.
Inside that RAM, there's two things in there.
There's the program, the data, right?
In order to execute the program,
you have to take the program,
bring instructions over to the CPU.
You have to bring the data that stuff refers to over to the CPU.
Then you perform the, say, addition on it,
and then you have to take the answer
and go back and put it in the memory.
So it's a stored program computer
because the program itself is stored, okay,
which has always been the case.
It's been the case for a long time.
When it first started, the program was more stored.
Here, there's the store, the data is stored.
You can have lots of RAM.
You can have lots of CPUs.
You can have faster buses or whatever.
But essentially, that's the von Neumann architecture, right?
And the so-called von Neumann bottleneck is this thing here.
This is the bottleneck.
Because everything you want to do work on is over here.
And everything that does the work is over there.
They're not in the same place.
Like, in an ideal world, they would be in exactly the same place
because then you wouldn't have to move the stuff around, would you?
But that's not the case if we see it in our motherboards.
Like, if you buy a motherboard,
you get your RAM slots over here and your CDU over here,
and these things are way over there.
That thing's over there.
So your program and data's over there,
and it's got to get back and forth here.
I mean, that sucks.
So then, one of the reasons it sucks
is because there's a big delay from going back and across this.
I mean, literally, for a lot of reasons.
You have to tell them what address you want.
It has to figure out what that is.
It has to take a day to move it around some of the wires,
make up the bus, to get it back over here.
But even at the speed of light, that still takes a while.
And that's assuming there's no electrical things that make it happen
a little bit slower than what the speed of light is, right?
So, you know, there's issues there.
So what technology came to bear to help mitigate that problem,
to make that access a little bit faster?
They said, hey, now, I know that this could be terabytes.
I mean, you could have, you could probably,
you could go easily by a computer with 1.5 terabytes of RAM.
I mean, just right off the line.
You could use it, you know, easily.
It's a little expensive, but it ain't ridiculous.
Most modern motherboards and processors support 1.5 terabytes of RAM.
Not in your laptop, maybe, but in a server-grade thing, absolutely.
Some of them go a bit higher than this, but that's really expensive.
But my point of it is, if you could actually have that much storage over here,
you would do it, but you can't, because you don't have enough space over there.
I mean, think about the actual little processor in here is a little thing like that.
You know, if you blew that up and looked at it, it's like, well, okay,
so there's like ALU stuff, and there's a space for the cache.
And inside this little cache area that's inside this little thing,
that's inside that little thing, there's only much,
there's much real estate on the chip for that cache stuff.
So it's going to be much smaller, orders of magnitude smaller.
Normally, like 1,000 times smaller.
Like, you might have a computer that had gigabytes of RAM,
and you're going to have megabytes of cache.
So that's a factor of 1,000 difference.
So say this was, you know, maybe this was 100 megabytes
for really high-inventing over here.
So caching was done to help speed up access to memory
by copying big blocks of this data from here over here.
It could go and place that block right over here.
So the next time that the CPU, which is over here,
you need to access it.
It's just accessing this inside this little chip here.
Oh, and by the way, the technology that makes up this thing
is radically different than the technology that makes up this.
This is typically called DRAM.
And this is often called SRAM.
SRAM is faster.
It's also much more expensive.
It's also, I believe, it's less dense
because it requires more transistors to make up the thing.
So that's why it's expensive.
There's a small amount of space.
Each thing is actually less dense.
You can't pack as much stuff in it, but it's ultra-fast.
This over here also uses a heck of a lot of power, by the way.
If you actually have 1.5 terabytes of RAM
and you're using all of it all the time,
this uses a ridiculous amount of power.
For something that we won't talk about here.
But that's why that came down.
Because programs exhibit two characteristics
that make this mitigating thing work for our advantage.
What two characteristics, or at least one of those two,
does your program have to exhibit in order for it actually
to be helpful to have this cache?
Or continuous memory access.
That's true.
We talked about that last time.
That's why we're going through all this stuff
with this 2D array allocation.
But continuous memory access, the reason that's good
is because it has temporal locality and spatial locality.
So locality, reference.
So your program, your program counter,
refers to the location of memory where the program is.
So it has a reference to it.
The loads of store instructions here compute addresses
that point to where the data is.
So there's a reference.
So when you have locality, that means those references
are close to each other, either close spatially
because they're adjacent to each other in memory
because it's contiguous, like Anthony said.
Or it's close with respect to time,
meaning that I use this memory allocation
and there's a good chance I'm going to use it again soon.
Does that make sense?
Now, in here, they talked about, in chapter 2 here,
they talked about different types of caching.
There were things called direct mapped cache,
fully associative cache, and a thing called set associative cache.
This was the cheapest.
This was the easiest.
This was also the least efficient.
Go in this direction, more expensive, more complex.
And this was very efficient.
And so direct mapped, fully associative, set associative.
And right here in the middle, it's kind of the best of both worlds.
It's like it's pretty efficient.
It's relatively cheap, not as cheap as it is.
It's more efficient than that.
It's a little more complex than that,
but it's like it's the best of both worlds kind of deal.
And if you look at the book here,
they talk about these cache mappings here on page 23.
You can go down there and look at it.
But I would certainly make sure that you know
what the definitions of direct mapped,
set associative, and fully associative are in terms of caching.
Now, this idea right here, 2.25 ILP,
you need to know this term.
Destruction level parallelism.
Now, we talked to the class about two types of destruction level parallelism.
In fact, it was not the quiz I think right here, right?
What were those two things?
Correct.
Pipelining.
That was the washing machine dryer example that we gave in class.
And then the other thing was multiple issue.
That is actually executing two instructions at the same time.
That would be like having two washing machines and two dryers,
so that you can actually start two loads at the same time.
And then actually you can do both of those things.
You can do pipelining and multiple issues at the same time.
You could issue an add.
You could issue another add at the exactly the same time.
And in the next time step, you could issue two more instructions.
So it's pipelined, but also each time two things are issued at the same time.
In fact, in 2.10, in Chapter 4, that's what it talks about.
It talks about the very first thing we did in 2.10 was the single issue.
And then they had a thing called multiple issue later.
We probably didn't do that.
It's complicated.
But like if we had gone further to the end of that textbook,
they would have gone and explained all of this stuff.
But as far as this class is concerned, you just need to know that one way
that we can get things done faster on the computer
is by executing more instructions at the same time,
either at the same time because they're overlapped in pipelining
or at the same time like it's actually running at exactly the same time.
So these are running at the same time
because all of this is happening at the same time.
These are running at the same time
because they actually got dispatched at the same time
because they were issued at the same time.
That's what it's called, issuing an instruction like,
go do these two adds at the same time.
So therefore, two adders would be engaged at the same time
because the computer had two adders
to actually be able to do addition at the same time.
Virtual memory, I would say, don't worry about
virtual memory too much.
You're supposed to have already talked about virtual memory in 356, right?
So we wouldn't worry about this too much.
We wouldn't worry about multithreading too much.
But I certainly would know, you know,
understand what is the von Neumann architecture
that got modified to have a little bit of caching here
and to overcome this latency thing
that there's caching, there's three types of caching,
direct mass, set-associative, plea-associative,
what's the pros and cons to those things.
What are the types of instruction level parallelism
that we've talked about thus far?
Don't worry about multithreading.
Now what about parallel hardware?
Well, that was also a part of our quiz, right?
We had Flynn's taxonomy.
In fact, let's go down in here,
keep that up, and then look at Chapter 2 slides here real quickly
so we have a picture.
There were a bunch of other things that were interesting about this.
Here it goes, shows the examples of those.
You don't need to worry about the translation look aside,
but I'm not going to ask questions about that.
Instruction level parallelism, I will ask questions about this.
High-binding mobile issue.
I'm not going to talk about speculative execution on the exam.
I'm not going to really talk about hardware multithreading either.
But I'm going to talk about Flynn's taxonomy.
Typical programs that we've been writing are like over here.
And when we do this, the computer actually executes it like this.
One instruction happens on one or two pieces of data,
like add these two numbers again.
But it's not like lots of data, it's just like one or two pieces of data.
That's all that happens.
Then you've got single-structure multiple data.
What's a good example of that?
If you had someone said,
I want you to write a program that seems to have
a lot of single-instruction multiple pieces of data in it.
I want you to think about the canonical example.
What about if you had a for loop like this?
You had something like,
you had A, some size, some stuff.
You had B, some array, some stuff.
You had C, some array with some stuff.
Let's say these links are 1,000.
We've got N4, I equals 0,
I less than 1,000, I plus plus,
C of I is equal to A of I plus B of I.
That's got single data,
single-instruction multiple data written all over.
Because what instruction do you see?
But it's happening on a thousand different pieces of data,
and none of those pieces of data have any dependency of one another.
Literally, if I had A in memory and I had B in memory,
that algorithm is written to do like this.
As you know, this is equal to that plus that,
this is equal to that plus that,
this is equal to that plus that.
Why does it have to be then?
It can happen right now.
Literally, I could add every one of these
to every one of those at the same time,
and to be equal to every one of those.
You don't have to actually do one after the other,
because there's no dependency here.
If you had some way of writing a program
that could do that single instruction
on multiple pieces of data, you could.
The book talks about the fact that our computers,
like for example, our modern day computers,
you'll go see that they have instructions called
like the AVX instruction set.
You know how when we did 210, we did MIPS,
we said like add R2, R3, R4,
where this held one word,
this held one word, add them together,
and you put them right there.
That's a scalar operation,
because it's only happening on one number,
versus a vector operation.
You like a math class.
You could say like, you know,
vector A plus vector B is equal to vector C.
That's literally saying both.
Now, this is the way you might implement it
with a regular program, with the math thing set.
That's just simply equal to the vector addition
of those two things.
These are vectors.
So they have instructions over here,
like say you have a vector add.
Vector register two,
vector register three,
vector register four.
And in those registers,
they don't hold one value,
they hold four values.
So that whole thing is in a register B2, B3.
These four values are loaded into here.
And then literally when you say add,
it adds this to this, this to this,
this to this, and this to this.
All in one fell swoop,
puts the answer right over there
into this register is the vector register.
So if you have registers that hold local values,
you can do a single addition
on more than one piece of data at the same time.
And all of our processors,
the ones you have in your phone,
in your laptop, in your computer,
they all have that stuff.
They all have these so-called vector instructions,
which can be utilized to do this type of parallelism
automatically by the compiler.
Because the compiler will come over here
and they'll look at this.
They'll be like, all right,
I got some RAM, all right.
There's no dependency.
It does a little algorithm to check to see
if there's any dependencies between the loops.
It's like, oh, heck yeah, man.
I'm just going to convert this thing.
Instead of going from zero to 1,000,
I'm going to go from zero to 250.
But each time I do one,
I'll be doing four at a time.
You know what I'm saying?
Yeah, four times 250 is 1,000.
So you'd only have to say
250 iterations of that loop,
but every iteration of the loop
is doing four editions at the same time.
Does that make sense?
Now, you have to have hardware that'll do this.
You have to be able to bring four things
from every array to every register at the same time.
That's okay. You already put it in cache.
It's already right next to the CPU.
So it's an interesting array of one value.
Just bring them all.
However wide these vectors are.
In our modern day computers,
these vectors might be 128 bits wide.
So you could add two 128-bit numbers,
or you could add,
what do I understand?
You could have that one register be 128-bit thing,
264-bit things,
432-bit things,
and so on and so forth.
They're configurable like that.
Vector integer add,
vector floating point add,
vector blah, blah, blah add, whatever.
Literally that same register will hold all those things.
You can either treat that as one big number
or treat each individual subfield as that.
So when you go look in the book
and it talks about this,
that's the example that they give.
That's what we're talking about.
We're talking about that conceptually
the high-level program has a bunch of independent instructions
that happen to be doing the same exact math operation
on different pieces of data,
and those math operations are not dependent on one another.
So it can be, quote, vectorized automatically
by the compiler to perform this sort of
instruction-level parallelism
by using these specialized instructions.
That's why when you say a new chip comes out
with some new stuff,
that's why the manufacturer,
Intel, they might want you to buy the Intel compiler
because it's got all of the stuff completely maxed out
to be able to use all this stuff,
whereas, let's say, a frequent compiler,
it might take them a year or two
to figure out how to export this instruction
or the Intel instruction or whatever in a way
that are going to be the most optimized
than it possibly could be.
I mean, that's kind of like the idea.
Because you don't have to use these instructions.
You can just ignore them.
You can be like, I'm just going to use the regular integer.
I'm just going to use the regular scalar instructions.
And your program would run.
It's just that it would run, in this case,
four times as long because it's not making use
of all the stuff that's there.
But in this case, we're not talking about
that you and I are necessarily writing that program
to do the parallelism.
We're saying the compiler's doing this,
but now we could.
If we were just going to be doing this,
we're going to break it across machines.
And then we can parallelize that out of our loop
so that this machine is just doing these.
This other machine is just doing those.
And then inside of that machine,
the individual cores are doing their part.
And then inside of each core,
they're using the vector instructions inside of it.
So that every level of parallelism that's available
is being used.
But you have to think about how am I going to break
the problem part?
How am I going to do all these things?
What about it's not divisible?
What about this?
What about that?
So the regular way instructions work,
the vector instructions here.
And then over here, you've got different instructions happening
on different pieces of data or whatever.
That's kind of like when you think about
like a standard program.
And several programs are working at the same time.
They're either the same instruction
nor are they the same pieces of data.
So our three big ones are this, this, and this.
That one over there is not a big deal.
SpinD.
Yeah, so there we go.
That's the prototypical example here.
It goes to drawbacks,
vector processors, you know, so vector processor GPUs.
I'm not going to have anything on the exam about GPUs.
Okay?
Not on this exam.
MinD.
I'm going to certainly talk about that.
Shared memory system.
We're definitely going to be talking about shared memory,
so I'll make sure you know about shared memory.
Uniform memory access.
Ooh, a multi-core system.
Uniform memory access meaning that it takes the same amount
of time to access all memory locations.
But that's not really true on a lot of computers nowadays.
They might say, this thing is in one UMA domain
and something else is in another UMA domain,
meaning inside of those domains it takes the same amount of time,
but between domains it doesn't take the same amount of time.
But what's happened, like, how do you think you get
1.5 terabytes of RAM into this machine
and have it all equally accessible by every core?
That's not how it works.
Like, they had to hierarchically break it up,
and it would be better to have certain cores accessing memory
that's inside their, you know, UMA domains,
and in real life they call it a NUMA domain,
it's non-uniform memory access, because it's not really
the same amount of time.
Here we go.
.naxs.
Clusters, you know, that's a word that we've been talking about.
Clusters, that's the stuff that we've been playing with,
that's the type of machine that expands it.
Now, have we actually run a job across multiple modes yet on expanse?
No.
But we are using the cluster to run a parallel job
inside of one node.
So where does our kernel system come and run?
There's multiple processes that are being spawned
by MPI run or MPI seg.
But our parallelism is coming because we're leveraging all cores,
because presumably if I spawn 128 processes
and there are 128 cores, I'll use those 128 cores.
Now, that's presumably, you know,
maybe, you know, for example, you only asked for 64
and you had to oversubscribe,
and this 128 would share the 64 that you got,
you know, that kind of case.
And the issue is then, of course,
these nodes have to be connected together
via some sort of network, right?
And we talked about how this network can be a big deal.
Like, if this was just, you know, a thousand or, you know,
one gigabit ethernet, standard ethernet
like we're used to plug into our computers,
ethernet does not have a really good latency at all.
It can have a pretty good bandwidth,
but the one gigabit isn't anything nowadays.
I mean, 50, 100, you know, a thousand gigabit.
I mean, that's where the thing's at,
because what about if these two things have to communicate
at the same time,
and if these two things are communicating at the same time,
well, like, depending on how this internet,
interconnect is done,
whether it's a full crossbar switch
or whether it's not or all kinds of other stuff,
they might interact with each other,
because if this was, say like this was an old-school bus,
first networks were just buses,
and I remember in middle school,
I think coax cables coming out of the wall,
and when they sent something from one computer to another,
every computer on the network could see that message,
because there was no routing.
It was just like, hey, here's a packet.
Well, then switches came along, right,
so actually we're going to route these from the right
destinations associated with these ports,
but I mean, if this had a thousand ports on it,
what about if it had a hundred thousand nodes?
You're going to have a single switch
that's got a hundred thousand ports in the front of it?
No, you're not.
It's going to be a hierarchical thing.
So the network starts playing a really big deal
in how well these computers look,
and there's lots of different topologies,
the central topology and the bus topology,
so you should definitely know what a bus is.
What is the pros and cons of a bus topology
if you were going to use it to provide,
you know, networking between the nodes.
Switched stuff, so, you know, from like two,
so the network is supposed to be something
that you already took as the previous system here,
and they should be talking about how networks work
and how the hardware actually works,
but if not, at the very least,
make sure you know what a crossbar is,
when people say what a switch is,
what does it actually mean, what is a switch, all right?
And then they start talking about
different kinds of topologies,
like, you know, a ring network.
So literally, like this computer,
the way they have this thing drawn,
it looks like it has two network interface cards.
It's got one with a wire a little bit over here
and one with a wire a little bit over there.
But then also this one is connected around this way,
you know, so like, for example,
if you wanted to send something from here to here,
you wouldn't send it this way,
you'd send it this way because that's fewer number of hops,
you know, versus, say, like a bus,
but if it sends something over here,
then it has to go all the way, you know, over here.
Then, like, if you take a mesh network,
that says I'm going to hook it up into a 2D matrix pattern,
I'm going to have every computer connected to a thing,
that thing in the network here
has a north, south, east, and west neighbor,
okay, so that's a 2D mesh,
and then toroidal means that I took a mesh
and I added wraparounds,
both from the top and the bottom
and from the left and to the right.
So, you have bus, ring, mesh, mesh with wraparound,
which is called toroidal, and you can see that
as you increase the complexity of this network,
you have the ability to get later
from one place to another faster.
You also have more reliability,
like, let's say this network connection right here,
you're going to click and cut it.
Can you still get from this node to that?
Sure, you can just go this way and set it, right?
So it has more reliability,
but the other part is the cost of it.
This implies that literally every thing here
has to be connected in every direction here.
So what about if I went up to say,
instead of this being a 2D mesh,
it was a 10D mesh,
or some kind of thing with a higher dimensionality,
you start having a lot of wires and a lot of connectors,
so the cost of these things are a lot, right?
What about if I had a network that was like this,
said four nodes,
and I connected these four together,
and also connected those four together.
Well, this computer is directly connected
to every other computer.
That's just as good as it gets.
But how many wires does that require?
A lot.
What about if it was a thousand?
You know, I mean,
you'd have to have,
if you have a thousand, n-zero-thousand,
so this one here would have to connect
to 999 other ones,
and then this one would have to do it for 9,900 ones.
So it's about, you know, something like this over two.
I mean, it's a gigantic amount,
about in square number of connections.
So you could see that the kind of network you choose
has a dramatic impact on what the cost network's going to be,
but it also has a dramatic impact on how fast it can be.
Like, what about if every one of the computers over here
wanted to talk to all the computers over there
at the same time?
That guy wants to talk to this guy,
this guy wants to talk to this guy,
and this guy wants to talk to this guy.
That's no problem at all.
Because this guy,
he can talk to here at the same time
that this one's talking to here,
it's talking to this one over here.
They don't conflict at all.
There is no contention in the network.
That's pretty sweet.
Would you have that over here with this?
If everyone wanted to communicate with everybody else, no.
You wouldn't have that over there.
So you get kind of what you pay for
with these so-called network topologies.
And they go through the bisection width of it.
That's like, how many links would you have to cut
to separate this network into two pieces?
Like, for example, over here.
Bisection width is...