Six years, raised. Six years, raised.
Oh, cost of living adjustment,
six years. The teachers also
have cost of living and
every year is a guaranteed
percent, or not percent,
sometimes it's a percent, sometimes
it's not a grade. So if you got like, say,
he had 20 years of experience practically
from teaching English in
Thailand and then teaching
Spanish in America, then he could move
it. I know he has a Ph.D.
So the highest little scale, like
that puts it up there, right?
But she's amazing. I
think she's the assistant
department chair now, or
she's the associate chair.
Okay, I would say
I'm putting together my schedule.
Am I your advisor? Yes. Okay, cool.
Alright, that sounds cool.
Have a good one.
Thanks for letting me
know about that student.
No problem.
Okay, let's see. I have one second here.
Okay, alright, so we'll close all
this stuff down here
with that. Don't save this.
Alright, so let's take
a look at something here.
So here's the plan. You know how I, so I
graded that, the most recent,
so I still haven't graded
the trapezoidal amount, I don't think, but
the one that was the most recent about
matrix vector multiplication,
where you got
it running on your local computer,
you got it running on Expanse, and you
didn't do a report, but you did a
presentation. That's the thing
I graded. So for
a week from today, at night,
is when the next thing is going to be
due. But the next thing
is, I don't have it
exactly figured out, but I can guarantee
you that the biggest part of it
will be writing a complete report in LaTeX
for the stuff you've done. But
now, you'll notice that some, you know,
there were very many
people that didn't get
a hundred on it
because there were things that
still needed to be fixed
to be done. Some people
were able to get
certain things working. Basically,
I'm guessing that what I'm going to
say is I'm going to have a
very minor code
change requested. Very minor.
But then I'm going
to expect extremely good
reports. And let's talk about what
I mean by that.
You know, I'm going to
want that report, you know,
I'm going to want it to
explain, you know,
matrix vector multiplication
in general.
You know, like, I'm expecting to
see some examples of some major
disease. You know, I'm
expecting to see some samples
but I expect to see the pseudocode
board. I'm expecting to
see basically a lot more
detail than what I saw in the
presentation. Because for
most people, not everybody,
but most people, the only thing I
saw was they just posted in there the
pictures that our scripts generated.
Okay, well that does prove that
maybe you got yourself going.
By the way, like, I want
to see screenshots of these things
not in the report that show
that you, in fact, were the person
that was really generating these plots. A
lot of people, when they took screenshots
to the command line, I couldn't see who
was logged in. And
I know that doesn't prove
any. Make pictures. But I mean,
is it possible that we can?
You know, for example, if you say I was
on the system at this time at eight and I
generated this thing and
these images right here and
I did an LS on it and I see
that it's in my directory and
these are the sizes of the
image and then when I look
at the sizes of the image
that you actually submitted to
the zip file, they should match.
You see what I
mean? Because that would mean
that it got generated
right there. You show these
to me and then it matches over here. I
don't need that in the
report, but I need that
documentation because I get the feeling
that on a couple of them
I was looking at images that weren't
really generated from the stuff I saw
in the other screenshots. And I'm not
going to go into it, but like,
the number of proceeds
counts don't match the
number of proceeds that
were in the diagram.
Does that make sense?
So, please make sure that
something's turned in. It's what
you got out and that it
is self-consistent. Okay.
I'm going to want to see
the algorithms. I want to see more
stuff about the computer architectures.
You know, I want to have
something that's going to tell me
like what the number of floating
point operations per second that you
ought to be able to get
like peak on the computer. And then
I'm going to want to see the number
of floating point operations
per second that your
actual program got. Okay.
So, like, let's imagine your
computer could do, you know,
1.7 gigabytes, but your program
only got 0.2 gigaplots.
And then that tells us, like,
hey, you know, regardless of how
fast it was, it certainly wasn't using up
the entire computer because
it wasn't maxing out.
So, I want you to
figure out how to calculate
the floating point operations
per second that your program
is doing. I want it
to be two different numbers
here. The overall
floating point operations
of the entire program versus
the floating point operations per second
of the computational part.
You should be able to
instrument your code with
that. You should be
able to have something
that will figure that out.
At the very least, you could
do the following. If you know
what the values are, like, you
know, this is order n squared, right?
And if you know that n is 1,000,
well then, what takes place in
here? Like, this times this plus this
times this. What's this times
this? So, you're doing 1,000
multiplications plus, you know, 1,000
additions. So, you actually
can figure out how
many floating point ops you're going
on. And you could measure the time
into it. And so, you could actually
calculate the number
of floating point operations
per second that's
happened because you know
the total number
of floating point operations
that the program does.
And you know how long
it took to do it.
So, you can divide, right?
That would be a way, that's the worst
way to do it, but that's a way.
Another way to do it is to use
some sort of thing that will measure that.
Some sort of profiler. So,
I tell you what I'm going to say is
I'm not going to have
any kind of requested modifications
to the program, but I am going to
request that you do whatever you guys do
to calculate these things here,
to use profilers on this
code and figure out how close
your program is
getting to actually approaching
the actual capability of
the machine. Because your architecture
has the ability to do a
certain number of operations per second.
How close are we getting to that?
And the rest of it is
get all that stuff on all
the details on it. I mean,
it needs to be a complete report.
It needs to be on the tech.
And I want the PowerPoint updated
to whatever the new stuff is.
If you've had stuff that went right
before, you've fixed
some stuff, or you've,
there were some you
didn't have done before,
but you haven't done
now, update the PowerPoint.
And finish the report.
And that's due at 11.59 p.m.
a week from today.
Then a week from that
day, so two weeks from today.
There's going to be the in-class midterm
examinees in pencil and paper. 75 minutes.
Close book, close notes, close computer.
Okay, so I want to go ahead and get
that out there so
that you can schedule it.
You know that that day, that's what
we're going to have the midterm exam.
And midterm exam is worth
how many percent of your grade?
30 percent. The only other thing
that is going to come up here
other than we're attending class and I'm
talking and stuff, is there's going to be
one more reading in the Pacheco book.
So over the next couple
of weeks, what's happening is
we're learning stuff, we're
going to read a thing,
we're going to take the
exam, and you're going to
do this with this stuff that I just
mentioned. And if you need to go back and
watch the video to get a full
list of stuff I just mentioned, do that.
Okay, so let's get,
let's get started here.
So if we go to Moodle
here and we look at this,
this morning I sent an update
for what we talked about last time.
And one of those things
was the chat GPT thread
that we had as well
as this pointer visualizer thing.
And I just want to show
you that this can be very, very
good at helping you understand exactly
what your program is doing. In fact,
I find it very useful to even
understand what your program
is doing. Like when
you've written a program and something,
something gets messed up, you know, like
it crashes, you get a segfault. Well,
you can put that program in here and
as long as that program is not too
intense right now, if it's going to go
millions of, you know,
millions of executions, you
can't do this, some web thing, right?
Well, cut the number of indices down, cut
stuff down, stick it in here, just, you
know, instead of it being a thousand or
good is ten, you know, and watch
it. You can watch
what's happening. So let's,
let's take a look at this. The
other day, the last one that we did
here was the one where it was like the two
mallocs because it had
left off that one to
to try to figure out how the
mallocing worked. You
remember you didn't, you
didn't originally have that and I
had to like ask it to
do some of that. So
we're going to take that code,
just take it and I'm
going to paste it over here.
Now, what we've got here, if you look
at this URL, we're like, it's how in edit
mode, all right? And if we
come over here and we say,
all right, I want to
go and edit this code.
It's already got some code
in here that is an example.
All right, we're going to, we're going to
erase that. I'm just going to hit ctrl v.
I'm just going to literally just put it in
there. And you can
say, okay, it's cc17 plus
the new extensions. Apparently that's
the only thing I can
choose. We don't want c++. So
even though we've been learning about c99,
this is c2017 that's in here. But
for the stuff we're doing, it's the
same stuff that's been around
from CSS. It's really 1989, okay?
So we come over here and we say,
okay, cool. I want
to visualize execution. Now,
if your program takes more than about
10 seconds for it to actually compile and
run internally, it will just
crash out and say, I'm
sorry, I'm not letting you run a
program. It takes 10 hours on our website.
You know, you're just going
to kill it out. If
you get to this point,
you know that you're okay here,
okay? So this is the output screen.
This would be like what the command line
would be printing out to
the screen. So that's the console.
This is a picture of the stack and the
heap. Remember how I
drew the stack and the
heap in here last time? This
tells you what line you're on,
all right? So here we go.
The stack already has rows, calls,
c, and data because you've got, main
has already been called at this point,
which means that stack
frames has already been allocated.
We haven't initialized
anything in there, but
because these local variables
are inside of main,
rows, calls, c, and data, there's rows,
calls, c, and data. So here we go.
We're going to hit x. Okay, I haven't
hit that. There's the three and the four.
Then it's going to malloc a block and it's
going to return it
and put that address inside
of c like we did the other day because
here we go. So malloc that is on the heap,
the stuff that's inside
that thing are pointers
themselves because this was a pointer to a
integer pointer array. So pointer
to an array of integer pointers.
So there's c, links up over there. Come
down here, come around
and malloc another thing.
Bam. Remember, this was
the rough set of row
pointers and this was
the payload from last time.
This is going to
contain the actual data in
the matrix, but this is
going to be the thing
that helps us link up the rows like
we did last time. So it comes in here
and then it's going to go through
every row, but it'll link up that pointer.
I think this is cool like this because
it comes in here and it goes and shows
this pointing at each one
of the rows now. So
you got row zero or row one and row two
out of the three
rows. In the columns you've
got one, two, three,
four column. One, two, three,
four. You see just like
that and then you can
kind of execute through it
because it does the stuff.
The print statements
themselves are actually happening
up here. So if you wanted to have
some print statements you
can print. You can't do
a whole lot of stuff like you try to start
doing stuff. It's got a
bunch of crazy extensions and
stuff to see or use a large use of code.
That's just not going
to work, but just for
trying to see if
you understand how corners work,
this is fantastic. There
are better ones of this
available, but a lot
of them involve you having
to install some large
thing that I don't know
whether you can trust
or not onto your computer.
So this will turn on
the web browser. It's pretty good.
All right. Now last time we were saying,
you know, looking at
the matrix vector code,
try to see if we could understand what was
going on with 2D
allocations. I'm assuming that between
last time and this
thing, we're going to be
good with 2D allocation.
So let's turn our attention
back to the matrix
vector multiplication code and look
at a couple of things.
All right. Let's see here.
So this is the NPI
matrix vector multiplication
thing and let's
I guess make this a
little bit smaller so that
we can get more of a row on this thing.
All right. So I'm
just going to walk through
and talk about what these
things do here. Now remember,
I suggested you take
this whole program, stick it
in a chat gbt and
ask it, explain every row
in detail. I would
certainly, I would recommend
that you do that
so that you understand what
this code is because
we've been using it, right?
So what does memset do?
Memset says that, you know,
how like when we were over here in the
visualizer, these things weren't
equal to anything when we
first started to just
put question marks. That
means it's garbage. It
hasn't been initialized yet.
So what memset does is
it takes a pointer to
the location and memory that
you want to set something
to and it goes and
writes whatever you want to
do into those stuff. You
want to initialize it all
zero, you need to initialize
it all zeros. Now, if
open means I want to
do a file open command.
All right. And the path,
this has to be a string,
so char star. Okay. And
this is also a string and
it tells you what mode
you want to open something in.
So here we want to
open it in read access and
it's not an ASCII thing here. So we do an
fopen and what does fopen
do? It returns a file pointer
or a handle. So the file type is file star
which means it's a file
pointer. So that's why they call
it this, fp. And then
they do this thing the
same reason they did that
stuff the other day to make
sure that it actually
works because it's possible, right,
that if you tried to open this file, like
let's suppose that had
didn't exist. You tried to
open it. Now, it's not
going to, like with this
mode here, it's just trying
to read from it. It's
not trying to write to
it. So it doesn't even
make sense to say, well,
if it doesn't exist, I'll
create it. No, it's not.
Because if you read from
it, like you're going
to create something that you
don't even know what's
in it. Yeah. So like,
it's going to fail. It's
going to set this to
the null. It's going to
check to see whether it's null.
And if it is null, then it's going to say,
hey, some stuff jacked up.
Now, let's look at this.
This is called fprint f. So print f means
print, you know, the typical
print thing. But f means
print to a file. But now what file
are we printing to?
We're printing to the stream
this, the standard error
stuff. So we're printing
out to the standard
error. And this thing tells
us which error it was,
which error number it was.
So like, for example, say
you tried to open the
file and the error
code internally was set to
file doesn't exist. Then for
you to get at the
screen, something that says
file doesn't exist, you
have to print out
what the error number is.
And this error number
is actually a variable
that's defined outside of
this code. It's part
of the thing that you linked in here. And
it gets set asynchronously
by the operating system. When
this system call happens,
it'll say not only
will this be null,
because notice this thing only
returns one parameter, null or
not null. So if it's
null, there's no way for
it to tell you what
the actual error was to happen. The way
that happens is the
variable called erno, which is
again, not defined here,
it's linked in outside of
this file, it gets
set by something inside of
the open to whatever
the number is. And then
this thing takes that number
and translate it to a
string. So it takes
this error, and it converges
to a string. And then
that string, it gets put
inside this string, along
with the path of a
file that you tried
to open that didn't work.
And it says it's rank zero, because I'm
guessing that the way this thing is here
is probably the only
guy doing the reading is
rank zero. I mean, remember
we had, the way we
told this thing start
was, the only dude that
was going to open the
file would be one dude,
the main dude. So rank
zero. Does that make sense?
Okay, cool. So then, now
we know that the first
two items that are in the file is the
metadata that describes the
number of rows and numbers
of columns. And those
are both integers. So the
very first thing that happens
is, it says, let me
get the number of
rows and number of columns,
I'll initialize it to zero.
And then I'm going to
use file read to read one integer. And how
many bytes does an
integer have? Size of n.
What file do I want
to read it from? This file
pointer. And where do I
want you to put the data
that you read out of the file, I want you
to put it into this
variable. But I can't pass this
variable by, by value
here, because that won't
actually write it into
the variable, I have to
pass it by reference, which
means I have to take
the address of this thing
and pass it in there.
Just the same way that scanf requires an
n percent, this thing
required an n percent,
since it's the thing you're
trying to do, because if
you just pass i rows
to a function, that's not
a reference to i rows.
That is the actual copy of
i rows. So if you
wrote i rows, what would happen
when an fread returned? Bad
i rows would go away. So
you have to pass a
pointer to it so that fread
can reach outside the stack
frame for fread and go
back and write on top
of the variable that was
in main stack frame.
That's what's happening there.
So read the rows
out, read the columns out.
You've got an or
here. Okay, does anybody know
what's happening when you
do like this whole thing
and you or it with
another thing? What does that
mean? And you see this
a lot in computing, both
at the command line and script, but also
in programming languages. Say
you wanted to do a
bunch of things like
this, this, this, this, and
this, but if any one
of them failed, you don't,
if you tried to read the rows out of this,
it returns null, then if
it's not equal to a one,
meaning that it's, you
know, that something bad
happened here, then we
don't even, then this
whole thing is a zero. And so actually we
got to come around
here. Actually, hold on here.
Might have, I think I got it backwards
here. Let me look at this real quickly.
Read this. So it's saying that I thought
this was going to
do short circuit evaluation,
but it didn't do that. It checks to see if
this either was a problem
or if this was a problem,
then it tells you there was a problem. I
thought this is going
to do short circuit evaluation,
so it would break out of the loop and I
keep going, but that's, that's
not, I don't think that's
what's actually happening here.
And then kind of in
here, you know, print out that there was a
problem, blah, blah, blah.
Then we go ahead
and call allocate matrix,
rows, columns, and n. Now,
this is getting back to that stuff we did
last time. It's going
to allocate matrix somewhere in
memory because now that we
know the metadata out of
the file, we know how
big to allocate the 2D
array. We haven't read that in yet, but
we're going to write
that dynamically allocated space
and then do some kind
of fread to get the data
in there. Now, the one
we did in class last time,
if you guys remember, it was all inside
a main. This one is inside of a function.
So we passed it the number of
rows, passed it the number of columns,
and we passed it m. Now,
what is m in here? Anybody remember?
The matrix. And it's not just the matrix
struct, it's a pointer
to the matrix struct.
So that's important because
it was actually passing
the struct to be a copy of the struct.
This is a reference
to that struct, which was
actually already passed to
this for main. I bet
if we came back over
here and looked at main, we'd
see that it was passing
it that way. So we come
back over here and look at main. And
there's the thing, right?
Like, if I'm ranked zero,
I'm going to read the stuff out of the
thing. And it's passing the
address of a full. Well,
full is not a
pointer to that structure. It's
the actual structure. And it's
like, oh, by the way,
the structure doesn't have
anything in it. So
that's why down here, since that's not a,
that's not a pointer already. That's why
you have to pass a pointer to it.
So you have to pass the address of that
thing. And then that's why
when we get down here,
that's got a star in
front of it, because it's
not a copy of the
stroke is the pointer to that
stroke. And then that
pointer, this goes to set
of stuff in that in
that in that thing zero,
when we come down
over here, and we allocate
the matrix, so we're passing
it a pointer to that.
And that's probably important
because what does the
struct have in it?
That's the type step, right?
Come up here to the top, look at the type.
It's got a copy of
the rows, copy of the columns,
it's got a pointer to the row pointers. So
that's a pointer to that
thing I mentioned earlier in
here. Let's actually, let's
just go back through here
again and do the same
one again. So we have
it sitting there. Look
at it. Actually, there's
right there. That's a
pointer to that row of
pointers. Because that means
that's, that's what this
is, the row pointers.
And this is a pointer
to where the data is.
And this appears to be
a pointer to the very
beginning of the entire block.
So now I don't know if this, oh, it says
one, one at one. Oh,
that's one of those things.
It's not that's not the
two, that's not the two.
Well, we better get back
over there and get a
copy of the one that
does one of them. That
was this one, let's copy
that. Let's come back over
here. Let's say we want to edit this
code. Control V. Visualize
execution. Okay, let's, let's make
sure this matches the thing we did in
class yesterday. So this,
remember, this thing's just
doing one malloc. The
very beginning of the malloc,
it is spaced for the
row pointers. And then there's
the space for the data
all in one block. Now
we can't see that all
over here because of this.
So let's do kind of
like this. All right. And
then we go through and
we set up these pointers
to point to the right place. Now it's not
drawing with the pointers.
Maybe that's because we've got
to do like this here.
Switch views. Yeah, there we
go. Can't see it, but
what it's doing is it's
saying first row pointer
points over into here
where the data, the
next one's pointing over there.
For some reason it's
just not drawing them like
this, but that's that
thing where we said the
other day where it was one big thing here.
So if we did three
rows, maybe three row pointers,
and then these would be
the rows. So like row
zero, row one, row two.
So this pointer would point here,
this pointer would point
here, and this pointer
would point here, and
that's what this thing's doing.
So they must have in that matrix struct a
pointer to the base
pointer of the entire thing.
So the base of it. Why would you want to
have that have a pointer
to the base of it?
Because you can't free a block if you're
not pointing to the
beginning of the block. Because
when you do a free, it has to be the
same address that was returned
from a malloc, which is always
the first byte in that
block. And if you don't
keep track of that, then
you can't free it later.
So that must be
something, that must be why
it's why they're doing that.
I don't, I mean, I'm
speculating. Okay. All right,
let's get back down in
there where they do the
alloc. So they pass that
a copy of the rows, I was saying copy,
just because I mean, at
any time you pass something
that's not by
reference, you're passing about
copy. So it's a copy of the rows,
a copy of the columns, and a pointer to
the matrix. Okay. And let's
see what we've got here.
It's doing all the
allocation. So it's all right.
So cool. Let's look for
the word malloc in here
somewhere. So there's the
malloc. So malloc is
the total number of
bytes. And what's the total
number of bytes? The total
number of bytes, right? It's
the stuff that it's like
the size of all the
elements plus the size
of all the row pointers
adds up to that number
of bytes. That was that
thing we talked about
earlier was this times this
times this plus this
times this, that thing from
the original thing. Hook up
the row pointers, that was
what was going on right
here where it was going
click, click, click in there. But now in
their case, this stuff
is actually inside the matrix
struct. Okay. So it's
like inside of another thing.
So if we were doing
this here, we would have
main, but then we would have another thing
that was dynamically allocated
struct. And inside there,
there would be pointers to these things.
And they didn't have
pointers to those things.
It's like it's
another level of indirection
because it's inside of
not only a function,
but it's inside of a
struct. All right. Let's see.
Let's keep going. So cool.
They take the copy of
the rows hard coded
into the matrix, copy the
columns, put it in
there. It's got where the
data is in a copy of the original thing.
Now, right now, I'd argue
that the reason they needed
this thing here is
because right now, while
this points to the
offset behind those original row
pointers where the data
starts, I would say that
like right now, though,
this ought to be pointing
to the very first row. And it could be
that this gets modified later
and gets moved around as
you're accessing it. And
then after that happens, you
still need a pointer
to the beginning. I don't
know. I'm curious to
see what's going on here.
All right. So that
now, like all that stuff,
so it made the
space into the pointers, allocated
the stuff. So by the
time it returns from here,
you didn't have to
return anything other than that
everything was okay and
think not being okay is
the central value negative one. So it
didn't actually return the
matrix that got allocated
because what got allocated
was just the dynamic
memory that was linked
inside the struct. The
struct itself was not
valid, which is kind of
interesting. It was hard
coded in the stack of
the guy they called
it. They could have added
that too. But they
probably didn't think it was
necessary because the struct
is just to handle
the bytes. It's a
bunch of fixed size things.
So it's not a big
deal. It doesn't matter if
it's a copy of that on the stack, I guess.
All right. So let's go back to main.
All right. I like K matrix. Okay, cool.
So the number of elements
at this point, as long
as it didn't blow out,
we know that we've allocated
the matrix directly. So
now we have read the
metadata out of the
file. That means the file
pointer is not pointing to
where the beginning of the
data is because it read
one int, read the next
and it has a method and it's ready to read
the rest of the stuff
in. How many stops? Well,
it's as many items as
those times calls. And how
big is each one of
them? Well, we said that our
matrices were holding doubles.
So it's going to
take this many items
times the size of double
because every needs to
know the number of elements
and the number of bytes
per element so that it
knows how much total to read. It takes the
file pointer to the string
it's reading from and the
destination is m arrow data.
Now the way arrows work
here in C is bad if you don't know it.
If you have a struct
that's not a pointer, then you
say like m dot data. But
if m is a pointer to
a struct, then you say
m arrow data. So if you've
got an actual copy of
a struct that's dot, if you
got a reference to it,
it's arrow, but it's the
same thing. It's just that
in C that matters because
one of them is a
constant offset inside of any
of the struct. The other
one is a pointer that has
to be dereferenced. So
it's somewhere inside. That's like
doing a star. A lot of people don't like
this because it seems
inconsistent because that's not
the way it is
in other languages. But that's
because in other
languages if everything's an
object, then you don't have to think about
not everything in C is
an object though. So let's
get to the every read.
Let's see what we've got here.
F read. So how many F reads did it
take to read all that they did? Just one.
But can you see that
there's only one F read.
Why would there only be
one F read if there's
actually a bunch of elements
we've got to read in? Why
not just put it in a loop and read in each
element one at a time?
Any idea? You remember the
other day when we said
why don't we do a bunch
of mallets instead of one
mallet? It's the same kind
of thing. You don't want
to do a bunch of F
reads because every time you do an F
read that's another system
at all. Number two,
is that idea of the
kind of stuff about being
on the internet, right? What
do you think would take
longer for you to
individually transfer a thousand
one kilobyte images or
transfer one image that was
a thousand thousand
kilobytes. It would take
longer to translate all
those small ones because
you have to pay a
startup penalty every time you
do it from the latency.
But it's just one gigantic
image. You're going to get a better
throughput generally. Now
that's a hand-waving explanation.
But if you can get
by with doing fewer number
of large reads that's better
than doing a lot of
one read. So because
that memory location is
continuous that's that is
a critical part of this
thing. Typically when people
learn how to do the
2D matrices in C they
learn this technique that it
does this. But in fact it was the one that
chat GBT tried to throw
out there at the beginning which
was that you're going to
mallet the row pointers and
then inside of a for loop if you wanted to
have five rows it
would do like mallet, mallet,
mallet, mallet, and then
it would have this pointed
to here, this pointed
to here, this pointed to
here, and this pointed
here. But the only thing
you're guaranteed is that
these bytes would be
deciduous. But that doesn't
mean that this row
is right after that row in memory. This
is a different location.
So you'd have to literally
read it one row at a time. You'd have
to read, read, read,
read. But the other way,
the way that it did it here, the payload
itself is all continuous. That
means you can just go
around here and say read all of it, all
of it at once. Because
you're guaranteed that every row
is right after the other one because it
was guaranteed to be
in row major order, continuous
memory. You might be
accessing this array in
row major order but
it's not necessarily stored in
memory in row major
order because you can't tell
where the hell these
things are. They might not
even be after one after
another in memory. One of
them might be a year,
one of them might be down
there. They put it
wherever space they can find.
And they don't need the
space to find space for
one row, not four rows.
They needed to find four rows
and one time it can
put it in there one big
chunk. But it might have decided with the
memory allocation process to
put it in the fragmented
holes in memory where it
can find. If I didn't
put one up here and
one down there or wherever.
Does that make sense?
So it's not just about
the overhead of doing
it. It's the fact that
you now can do one
big contiguous thing. And you
may say, why is he
making such a big deal about
this? I get it. You know, this can be
used. Because all these
NPI calls, some assume that
the stuff is contiguous
in memory. And if you
didn't know that and
you had allocated your thing
the way that chatgbt had set the
allocated initially, this wouldn't
have worked. It would
have crashed. It would
have segfaulted. And you'd be
like, I don't have any
idea how to apply segfaulted.
And then you would try
to find out like, well,
is there a debugging tool
that will help me find
segfault? And you might
find something called Vowgrind
just for free on the internet. And then
you would find out one or two things after
that. You'd be like, oh,
Vowgrind doesn't work real well
on NPI programs. I mean, it can. Then you
go read about a product
called TotalView. This may be
$10,000 for one license
or one person per year.
It's amazing. It is not
free. Then the Intel would
have one that you could
possibly use. But only if
you bought the license for
the thing. Or if you
were using an Intel chip
that was a premium chip,
what about if you had
bought an AAMD machine? I
ain't going to help you.
I'm going to do it for
you. You see what I
mean? So the issues are is
that a lot of
the tools that make debugging
easy are not free when
you're talking about Herald. So,
okay, so you have to really make sure
that you're really thinking
about where everything is, where
all the pointers are,
to explain to yourself and
really read the API and
say, well, if there's only
one pointer to the
buffer, but this buffer holds
a bunch of different
stuff, a little better down
when we can continue
this. Because if it's not,
there's nothing else in the
API where you can tell
this is the pointer to
the middle of it. This
is the pointer to this.
This is the pointer to that.
But you can build data types for NPI
to pack them all
into a continuous location.
You know, like, say
your stuff's all thrown out
in memory. You can do
the following. You'd be like,
let me mail it back.
I don't think I'll copy
all these little chunks, put
it into one big buffer,
and now they're together.
But that requires a
memory copy. Copy this
from here. This from here.
Well, memory copy, every time you copy
something, remember, you're wasting
time. What about that's
inside of the for
loop? Then you're copying
it over and over and over and over again.
It's best not to avoid
having to copy anything in
memory. In that case, you
have to have it be
continuous. And that's why
we're, that's why we
made a big deal
about this thing. Now, sometimes
you can't help it. What
about if it's not a
matrix that's in memory? What
about if it was a dynamically
created tree where the
the degree of every node
is variable. It's not
a binary tree. It's just,
it can be anything
arbitrary number of trees.
Well, stuff's going to
be all over everywhere.
That's called unstructured
data. That's the worst
kind of thing for very little computing,
because if it's
unstructured, it's not continuous
possibly. That's why
we're playing with matrices,
because matrices are
dense objects. They're
all structured. They
have a guaranteed structure,
m by n by what however many dimensions it
are, is structured. Okay, let's
get back to the thing
over here. Read it. But
when you read it, one
of the things is after
he returns is the number
of items that were read.
Now, what can happen is you
could read at you could
say I want to read a
thousand items. But what about
if it only read 900
of them and they got
to the end of the file
before it had gotten
to a thousand elements. So
it was short. What
that's called the read count
was short. Then if the read count is not
equal to the number of
elements, that means that while
this thing may have read
some data, it didn't read
all of it. And it's
like, hey, crap, move out.
Let me go ahead and deallocate this matrix
because it is totally
messed up. Like, yeah,
there's no guarantees. Now you said read a
thousand items. I read
something less than a
thousand. So it's true.
You might say, well, what
about good read more items?
I mean, I guess you
could say it would never
be more items than what
you asked. You could do
less than or equal, but
they just go ahead
and say not equal because
it's not exactly the number
you said and it's something
bad. Right. All right.
So we've allocated the
matrix, we've read the
matrix. And I'm trying
to, this is what I'm
trying to get to here.
Only one dude read the
matrix. But who all needs the
matrix? Everybody needs their
chunk, right? So there's
got to be something in here that is
doing something to get
the various row chunks
to the different processes.
And I honestly, I don't
know. I didn't look at
it. I don't know how it
got to things in the
process. I want to check out.
I want to see like
how the hell do you actually
do that? Because I want to
know whether or not what it
did make sense. But the
very before we get to
that, though, I want you
to think about the following.
Okay. I want you to really think about
this. What about if
this matrix had been gigantic?
Okay. Just think about this. Okay.
Let's suppose that I'm on a computer
who the amount of RAM that the computer
has is say four
gigabytes. I'm just choosing that
as a number. Okay. So
you got the computer. This
is the hard drive that
is in here. Let's say that
matrix M is 16 gigabytes. All right. And
the number of servers
that you have right now
to do this on are four servers. So, and if
you spawn one NPI process
per server. Now we haven't
done that yet on Expanse.
We've only asked for one
node at a time. But
we could ask for four nodes.
And then one copy of our program would
be running on every
node. Or there might be
key copies of our
program running on every node
because there are key
cores on every node. But
for the time being,
let's just imagine that
it was one process per node, not per core.
So, train zero, one,
two, three. This is 16.
And these things all
have four gigabytes of RAM.
Now I've got four
servers. Collectively, they have 16
gigs of RAM. My data is 16 gigs. Now let's
assume our racism is
no problem. So collectively, do
I have the resources
to operate at the same
time on 16 gigs
of information? Yes. But will
this NPI program work? No.
Because this thing tries to
read this entire thing
into this guy's RAM. And
you're trying to read
16 gigs into four gigs.
Now you might say,
okay, here's what's going
to happen. It's going
to start swapping the disk
because it's got virtual
memory. You're right. And
you know what's going
to happen when that happens?
You're either going to
see that you're going
to have the whole
damn computer blow out because
you're out of memory. Or
it's going to be swapping
the disk. And it'll be
so worse that you wish you
had never even run
this thing. All right. My
point is, is that sometimes
variable computing is not to
make a computation faster
alone, but to even
accommodate the amount of
data that has to be
operated on at the same
time. Okay. So in this
case, if the data is
16, so the data is larger
than we did in RAM
on one computer, but collectively
it would have been here,
then what you would have
needed to have, some of
them would read a four
gig chunk, a four gig
chunk, a four gig chunk,
or this one read four
gig, and now you read
four gig, and whatever. But
the way this term is written,
this one tries to read all of that. And I
don't know what it does
next, but this won't work. So
the last time I said, I asked chat GPT to
build this thing. It clearly
works. But this is obviously
a problem with the way
it wrote it, because it's
not designed in a way
that makes sense in terms
of the amount of RAM. It makes, it assumes
that you're limited to the
amount of RAM that one
machine would have. But
I thought about four
machines. Why is this program in the way
that this won't work for my situation?
You get what I'm saying?
Because this F read right here,
said read 16 gigs. You can't read 16
gigs because they ain't
16 gigs worth of stuff.
You see what I'm saying? But now, there
is enough collectively in
this distributed system. Let's
say every one of
these things cost $50,000. You
get $200,000 in computers.
But the way this program
is written, it will
only work on something that
is big as the
$50,000. So something's wrong with
this. I don't know how wrong it is. But I
know right there, this is
an issue. And this might return
if you've got enough
memory and swapping all this
stuff out of you.
But I'm saying, this ain't
great. Because in the
ideal world, all of your
data would fit in memory at the same time.
But that won't happen here. So what I want
you to imagine is, the next steps will be,
let's identify what it
did and just talk about
how it could have been
fixed so that it wouldn't
have this problem. Now,
on Expanse, we'd have to
create a file that
was larger than 256 gigs
in order to have
this problem with it. Actually,
we don't really have
to do that. Remember how
before we ask it for
the full memory? We only ask
it for eight gigs. If
you made a 16 gig thing,
it ain't going to
work. Because when you try
to mallet the damn space
for it, it won't work.
When you try to do a mallet, it'll be
like, oh, a mallet, 16
gigs. It's like, because already,
you only got eight
gigs. Boom, it blows out.
Heck, yeah. This thing's
going to blow out before
it ever gets to the F3. It's going to blow
out when you try to
do the mallet. It makes most
lot of it. I
don't know. Because he couldn't
say, well, I'll tell you
what, it would be lazy.
Yes, for 16 gigs. But until such a time as
he tries to use it,
I won't worry about it.
It might do like that. I don't know.
It depends. Those are
some organizations. Because a user
could ask for a bunch
of stuff, never use it.
Well, why blow out early?
You can blow out later
if they try to use it. I don't
know which way this
thing's written. Which way it's
implemented underneath. So
let's go back into
main. Right after the matrix was read,
and let's see what happened here. So
if the matrix was being read here,
then we'll go back over
here. So it read the
matrix. So it read A.
Then it had to read B.
OK, so that small vector. So I mean,
unless that happened to
throw it over the boundary,
like this is probably
going to be OK. Because
the B vector is very
small. It's just one vector.
Then it checks for
matrix compatibility. Like if the
rows and the columns don't match in such a
way that we can't do matrix vector
multiplication. So that's the
matrix vector compatibility issue.
Remember how, like, if this thing was
rows by columns, this thing, this was like
n by m, then this one has to be m by
1. This has to match this.
So those two things don't match.
Then the matrix is not compatible for
matrix multiplication. That's
what we're checking there.
OK, guys, does everybody,
does this make it
sense? OK. So then
it does some other checks
after all these checks pass.
I guess it goes to
set m and n equal to the rows and columns.
OK, so we start broadcasting. Send m and
n to everybody. OK,
because not everybody opened that
file. Only the main guy
opened the file, right? So
they don't know what m
and n are. And we couldn't
pass it from the
command line because we didn't
know what they were
at the command line. Now,
that last example we
did that not last somewhere,
but the one before that,
we knew what we were
talking about when we ran
it from the command line.
So not everybody had to do a scan app or a
broadcast or whatever. But in
this case, they don't know
what it is. So chat gdt chose to do a
broadcast, two-setter broadcast, mind
you. I would argue that
putting m and n inside of a single data
structure and doing one
broadcast that sends 16
bytes instead of doing
eight bytes or four bytes
at a time, that
would probably be better. But
it did it, et
cetera. Why? Because it's probably
easier to read. You need to read this. OK,
and then, you know, if
this stuff doesn't work or
whatever, you know, blah,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
So allocate b. OK, so I had to allocate b.
All right. Now, let's see what's happening
here. It says allocate b on all ranks.
Now, why does everybody
have to have b? Let's
think about this now.
We've been dealing with a,
but remember, like, if
this had been a year,
let's say the rows
were like this, one, two,
three, four. And b was this, five,
six. And we're going
to have two processes.
So this would have been divided like this.
And our people, like
our processes are doing this.
If, say, process zero is handling these
two and process one is handling those two,
which part of b does process zero and one
need? Unfortunately, b is
not divided up here because
for p, zero, to take this row and dot
product with this column, it
has to have both things.
So this got divided in half. This did not
get divided in half
because everybody needs a copy
of the way this is written. So that means
that over here on
process zero and over here
on process one, it looks
like process zero. So far
now, I mean, it looks
like process zero has got
all of a. And then it looks like process,
and then they sent this
thing out. So everybody's got
mn now. Okay, so everybody's got mn, mn
because they broadcast that.
So everybody's got, I guess,
two and twos. We got two and two, two and
two. And then we allocate
b on all the ranks.
Okay, so we made space for b on all
the ranks, but it hasn't been read in yet.
And let's see what happens here. So if I'm
the rank here, it doesn't
mean copy from one place
to another. So be and be full. Hold on
now. Be full. What is
this? It's coming up here
where be full is that must be some
kind of thing called
be full in here. Okay,
be full is the matrix
struct. But be itself is
what all ranks will be
be full only ranks zero. So
now everybody's actually
got everybody's got both
of these structures. But only one of them
is pointing to something
that's the entire full
thing, whereas everyone else
has a copy of it.
Okay, so let's see.
Because I'm trying to get
a picture of where
is this data add actually?
Where is it? Come back down here. Now,
unless unless you look
this up, you wouldn't know.
But where is the source and destination
in for mid copy? So come down here.
And we do like a man page on this.
It's source destination. So
it copies this many bytes
from this buffer into
this buffer. So source
destination. So it's going
to copy from here
to here. So that
means over here, it's copying
from here. So it's
hopping from the data section
of the matrix be full and putting it into
the matrix section of this
thing here on right zero.
But on everybody else, they have to wait
for rank zero to
broadcast this out to everybody.
And everybody is going
to because so that's
interesting. Now look at
this. So that means
that rank zero actually
has, does it actually have
two copies of B? Like if that vector were
say 100,000 rows, is it
got 100,000 rows in there
twice? I don't think so.
Because in one of these
cases, there was a struct
B full dot data that
pointed to this. But then
there was also just B
dot data. And it says
that's E, that's mid copy.
Okay, so what is what
is what is that copy here?
So this times this, so
it looks like it actually
is a copy of it.
So one might argue you didn't
really need to do
that because you could have
just had this data equal
to that data and you
would just add two
pointers to the same place
because nobody's going to
change B. But B doesn't
get rid of two dozen. But it looks to me
like it actually had two
of these things over here.
And everybody else had
one. And then after having
copied this from here
to there, it turned around
and the rank zero sent
just the data, not the
other stuff. Okay, why could
you send all this stuff?
What does it say
like, if remember that the
way this this allocation
is happening is if this
thing say had four rows, then it would
have been would have
been like pointing to this,
and pointing to that,
and pointing to that. This is the saying,
just send this, don't
send the whole thing.
Why don't you just send the whole thing?
Why not send the whole thing to the
other guys? Because these
pointers are addresses that are
only make sense on the notice being sent
from because those are
memory addresses on notice
sent from. Those memory
addresses don't mean back
on everybody else's. So
that's a whole different
from RAM. Like whether
this was an address 75,
but over there it needs
to be an address 74,
it would be totally jacked, right? So
that's why it's saying
you can't send this.
Over there on this other computer, it had
to go ahead and set these row pointers
itself. So these make
sense relative to this guy's
RAM, these make sense
relative to this guy's RAM.
However, after it did the copy, it said
instead of sending this
crap, because it's not important,
I'm just going to send
this thing over there, and
it's going to write this
in here. And now these
things have already been
pointing at the places they
need to point to. So
you can't send the whole
thing. And likewise, if
this was your answer, your
answer is going to be a vector. You can't
write this entire thing
to the file because
these pointers don't are
not part of the data.
The data itself is just
the thing. So we're going to
have A, we're going to
have B, and I don't know
what they call this over
here. Maybe it's going to
call it C, I don't
know. Now I'm going to see.
But it's going to be
the same kind of thing
where this is the data,
and that's that little pointer
stuff. So it seems like
at this point, now I
might be reading it wrong,
but it seems like at this
point, everybody allocates space
for B on their
machine. And then rank
zero sends to everyone
a copy of the data B. Okay, so if this was
like five, six, so like
five, six got copied, and now
this guy's got a copy
of five, six. Okay, so
that hopefully, like this guy
will be able to take
this row at dot
product with five, six, following
the other guy, hopefully
takes this row and dot
products with five, six.
I'm trying to get it
though. Where is A over
here? I might have missed
it now. I mean, I'm
being serious. I mean, I'm
looking at this with you
live. Like I have not
looked at this before. I
don't know. I don't know
what it's in there. I'm
just trying to try to read
it like you guys would
be. Where is A at over
here on the other one?
Because all I saw was that
that the head process
read the data fallout. The
head process read B,
and then B got distributed
to everybody else. Where is
A at in this thing?
Let's go see. Where is
A being handled? Because I
know that everybody, when
it's all said and
done, everybody needs to
only have their trunk rows,
right? So where is that being done? Well,
that's right here. Partition
the rows and figure out
the counts and displacements.
Oh my God, what the
hell is happening? I
tell you what, this is
one of those places where
I want to chat to you
to help explain it to
me. Like I know what these
are referring to, but I
imagine I had no idea
what it is to count
the displacement. What is the
displacement? I'd be asking
at that. Because an MPI
and also in C
Perdome in general, a displacement
means like how far
into something you have to
jump to get to the
place you want. Okay. Let's
see. It takes M, it takes the number of
people that are in the
common world, so that's basically
the number of processes
P. It takes a pointer
to count rows and
a pointer to displacement rows.
So this thing appears to be doing two
things. It appears to
be doing the arithmetic that
calculates how many
rows everybody should have.
Like, and depending on
how divisible it is,
like if it's not divisible evenly by P,
it's handling that. That's
what it looks like doing
because look at this.
It's doing energy division here.
And we know that's not going to work in
general. We saw
that happening with Pechenko
stuff. But it
also calculated the remainder,
which Pechenko did not do. So when
something's not evenly divisible,
there'll be other remainder,
right? So then it's
like, okay, we're going to
go starting from zero
to the number of processes
one at a time. And we're going
to say that the number of rows
are, right, and what is this here? That's
a, that's just a
temporary variable inside this loop,
is equal to the base.
Okay, so the base was
the number of elements that
I was supposed to have,
floor function basically,
because of the fact
that the energy
division didn't work there.
And it plus either a one or a zero
depending. This is what's
called a ternary operator. How
many of you are
familiar with this? Anybody not
familiar with this? Okay,
this is like an if-then-else
statement. This thing says
that, like, if this is
true, then it's this. If
this is false, then it's
that. So it's going to
be plus either a one
or a zero depending on
the true value of this thing.
And you may say, like, Kyle, why did they
even do that? If I
was to see what's built,
computers didn't have gigabytes
of RAM. They had kilobytes
of RAM. So every line of a C program
mattered because even on
the storage device where
you're compiling this stuff,
like, there was very
limited space to even
hold the source code. Back
in those days, the
amount of space that your
thing took up in
ASCII might actually even be
bigger than the amount of
space that it took up
in the binary because of the fact that
the instruction might have
been, say, eight bytes,
but the damn ASCII thing
was 20 bytes. You know
what I mean? So if
they could express it in a
short compact way, that
saves space in the text
file. Now, nobody cares
about any of that today.
But the space part,
at least. But, you know,
sometimes you'll see people write
some crazy stuff with this.
Anyway, all this thing
is doing is starting to
craft any of your out in that main matrix,
how to partition the
main matrix into pieces,
how many rows that
each process that I'm going
to send it to is going to need to have,
and where in that matrix
each chunk is. So what's
happening here is it's
like, oh, the displacement for
the first guy is going to be right here at
the beginning of the
thing. So it'll be right
here. But then the
displacement for the other one
will be down this plus
this space, you know, times
the size of our byte,
this place is down here.
So this guy is going to be put into here
when it goes to send
it. It's just how everybody
calculate how many rows
they're going to have,
and how far down
inside of that original continuous
buffer, you need to jump
to get to the place
that points to who you're
going to be sending or receiving
from. This will be
an excellent thing, just
as function, to put
that function in that pointer
thing and have it run. Because if you did
that, right, these are
pointers, so it's doing arithmetic
on the pointers. Look
at that. This displays rows
equals this, and this is
plus equals that. I mean,
you would actually be
able to see the pointer
again hook up to
the right places inside these
things. Now, are you going
to be able to put
in PI code up in
there in that learned visualizer thing?
No. But you could,
you could copy and paste
chunks. You could make
yourself a little pretend main
program to call it
from to simulate it, and
you could visualize it
and look at it yourself.
All right, so that, that here
has something to do with that.
Okay, now, okay, so at that point, the
number, the displacement, and
the counts have been calculated.
And then that means
that we're going to have
to be able to send
those counts out, and we're
probably going to have to be able to
send these displacements out
when we have this mallogating
stuff here. At some point, we got to
get some kind of
sending or receiving down here.
So allocate rows that are only as big as
needed, and then receive
them via scattered vectors. So
scatter B, that's an
NPI collective communication from
chapter three or four
in the reference guide.
So who is executing this? Allocate on an A
that's only as big
as needed. Well, count rows
was declared up here.
So count rows had already
been figured out based
on the size that everybody
needs to be. So there's an array that
contains everybody's size, and
the index into that array
is the rank that
that corresponds to. Okay, now
it does seem like
what it's doing is saying,
look, okay, cool, I
might have read, I might
have read the entire damn
array of A into this,
but everybody's not going
to need that. They're only
going to need a matrix big enough to hold
a little chunk I'm trying
to send into it. So in
this case, I'm going to
kind of do it like this,
imagine that this was
the top half, and this
was the bottom half of
this matrix. So over here,
this guy is only going to need the bottom
half. Because he only needs
this to multiply by that,
and this guy, now he
already has the top half,
because here he got he's
got the whole damn thing
in memory, right? But
it does seem like it's
having everybody only only make
one that's big enough to
hold the part for itself. So it looks
like everybody's allocating a
matrix that's only big
enough to hold the
number of rows that your
rank should have. But what's
kind of crazy about this
is looks like
everybody's allocating this block,
even even process zero
doesn't that seems weird
because process zero
already had already had
his block in there.
But after this happens,
it does go ahead and
free the other matrix. And
you know what, this seems
like it is going to be
happening here. It seems
like, you know, we're
making copies of stuff
we didn't really even make
copy of. But that's as
a result of the fact that
it had one guy read
the whole thing is versus if
everybody is just writing
their shop, we wouldn't have
to do any of this.
Okay. So after you've got
all the buffers made,
then that's when you have
to send stuff out. So
we're going to send out
the part of the buffer that can approach
is associated with this
process of where you're
going to send from
and where you're going to
receive to based on
the fact that everyone is
going to send it with this guy being the
rank being the guy who's
got the stuff. Everybody else
is going to be
receiving into their buffers. Scatter
V. So let's go look at a picture of what
Scatter V looks like.
The process zero has the
whole thing and you want
to get the whole thing
divided up into pieces
and just send out everybody
else. You want process
zero to have this first
little chunk. Everybody had
that chunk. This guy's
going to have this
chunk. And these things about
sizes and displacements are
about how far into this
thing you have to
go to the individual chunk.
Okay. Because Scatter V means
that they don't have to
be the same size. If
it was all the same size,
you could just use
scatter because then you
would have had to
calculate the displacements because it
would have been fixed.
But with this remainder
stuff and all that,
we had to manually compute
every displacement. Alright. So
this Scatter V is
how you get something
from one person scattered
out to everybody including
yourself because you're one
of the people that is being scattered to.
Does that make sense? It's kind of
screwed up though because
you already had this.
But it does mean that
everyone executes the exact same
piece of code, which is kind of the way it
works because when you
run your program in an
MPI, it's a copy of
your program running on every
process. The only thing that makes it
different are these if
statements. But with collective
communication, everyone has
to call the same
function. Like you know
with point to point,
that doesn't have to
be. Like either the sender,
I'm going to call
send. If you're the receiver,
you call receive. But when you're doing
scatter, collective, it's like
everybody calls the same
function. So you can't
have some special thing like
oh you know you got to have the same thing
happening in every
process. Extra capabilities. You
can actually leave out
chunks that you don't
want to send. The Scatter V has the
ability to send any
collection of sub-contiguous pieces with
gaps in it to
other people. That's really the
kind of interesting part
here. It's so versatile that
you can send any arbitrary amount. But it
also means it's the
most complicated one to use
because you have to calculate
all these displacements and stuff.
Versus if everything
was perfectly divisible,
you would need to do that.
So does that make sense?
So apparently what I'm trying
to get to here is that this code has done
some things that weren't
great. Now, I want to
ask chatgbt if it agreed. I'm not going to
lead it. I'm not going
to lead it into this.
I'm going to say hey,
tell me some of the limitations
of the code as it
is written. I want to see
if it even identifies that
the thing we brought up today
is the limitation of this
code. So I'm going to
come in here. I'm going
to cat MPI matrix vector.c
to the clipboard. So that's
me copying it. And I'm
going to paste it up
here in here to chatgbt.
Let's not lead it
at all. See what happens.
I'll see what it says.
And that's probably going to
find all kinds of things
it doesn't like about it.
But let's see if this
is among one of the ones
that it says. And then Simmons doesn't
take forever. Now the thing is, you know,
it created this and
now it's going to evaluate
it and say that there's
things it doesn't like about
it. How would you have
been able to do chatgbt
in a way where it
would have already done its
own evaluation before giving
it back to the
gentleman? You could have it set up in an
agent agent generate
the code. Another agent
evaluating the code, even
though it's the same
model, they're not
the only communication they're
having with it is
they're interacting with each
other. You can have it
sit there and provide a
piece of code to sit
there for an hour or two,
actually running it on a real computer
and eventually get something
back that you never
had to look at it because it's testing it
live. I believe that
chatgbt is already providing this
capability in the cloud where
it's going to say, you
know, you give it a
prompt, you give it some
stuff and let it go
off and work for a while.
But it was also on
testing. Instead of me doing like,
what do we all
do? Copy, paste, execute, run,
copy, paste. Well, that's just
a fancy way of copying
and pasting. Let's just
sit there. Let's just sit
there. You just have to
have a resource to run
it on. And if you're computing, that could
be problematic because you
might need a super
computer to run it
on, right? But anyway, let's
see what it says. It
says it works okay for
it. But there are several real
limitations. There's a
root IO central bottleneck.
Rank zero reads all of A, which is
what I said was
the problem with this thing.
Then B, then it broadcasts this
and then scatters
that. The consequence is,
A becomes a bottleneck.
There's no parallel file
system. There's a memory
pressure. That's what I
was talking about. Memory
pressure means you've run
out of memory because
A had to process zero,
had to read all of
A, even though process zero does
not need all of A in order to do its math.
You don't want anybody
to have to allocate more
memory than they would need
to do the math part
of their stuff if you could help it. So
that's just to prove that
apparently it does C without
me leaving it, that it sees that that was
a problem. In fact, it
was within the first two
bullets that it saw that.
If we had set this
chat TV thing up and
I had a paid version of
the agentic thing in this, it would have
just sit there and
iteratively refine on it, right?
Well, what it would take is it would take
this feedback and then it
would give itself a prompt
and say, fix this,
it is, and evaluate that
subject to these prompts,
go back and evaluate it.
And if you've got enough
of this time and money,
I mean, you iterate it
right on out into a nice
solution. You see where all this is going.
I mean, it's even
worse than the co-pilot telling
you how to do stuff,
just doing it. If you've
got resources to execute on,
you don't even need to
sit there and do any copy and paste. You
take even totally out of
the loop, especially for anything
that you, there's an easy way to determine
if it worked, right?
Well, you could say, hey,
I've got this base
program in here and sequentially
I know works. So
go test it, exhaustively test
it, test all
the test conditions, automatically
generate this, automatically
do all of this.
I'm going to go get
some coffee. I'm going to
go, I'm going to do
it, I'm going to come back.
And then it'll have
checked the correctness, it'll
have checked all of
the timings, it'll check the
throughputs, it'll check
the absolute maximum speed
we could have gotten. It'll tell you, hey,
this invitation would hit
80% of the theoretical
maximum of what you
can get with this machine.
That's all we do.
I'm like, cool. Anyway, I'll
see you guys later if
you have a great weekend.
And see you next
time. Remember the stuff, that
timeline I put at the board at the very
beginning of class
about the upcoming stuff.
Yes, sir. You do the
same. Have a good one.
Trying to stay dry. It looks like
it's going to start raining. It says