is that address one eight. Let's go over to address one eight.
That's this number.
And he may say we're number 16.
That is the number 16 because this is a minor.
So that number becomes
one zero and exit decimal is zero zero zero one.
This becomes four bits, zero zero zero zero.
So this is one, two, four, 16 columns.
There it is right there. So the values of stuff are not over here.
The value itself is actually physically encoded inside the instruction.
That's all it is.
We'll look over more on that next time.
How are you, David?
All right.
OK.
OK, so how about the thing that was due last week about the
matrix vector multiplication.
How did that turn out?
Did it work out?
Who's got a report that they're willing to use as an example?
Anybody?
Anybody feel really good about what they did?
I mean, you don't have an answer.
That's fine. I'm just asking.
All right.
Well, let's just keep on going.
That sounds like nobody has felt good enough about it to show.
So let's take the program.
Let's see.
Oh, that's on the other computer.
That's all right.
Let's go in here and download it directly from here.
Class undo to my sins.
OK.
This one here.
Let's go in here.
We'll download this.
Then that also referred to a set of files that were located in here.
That was a matrix that was up.
OK.
Have I not done this since I was a period in my computer?
You have not agreed to it.
You must agree to it.
Press enter to display the license.
I'm a little bit concerned here, honestly.
OK.
Let's see what the parameters are.
All right.
So we need to do starting, ending, increment.
Starting, ending.
OK.
So what was kind of the biggest thing that we did?
About 40,000?
Yes.
About 5,000.
All right.
About 5,000 to 40,000.
Let's just do 20,000 to 40,000.
Another zero there, I guess.
Ingrants of 5,000 from 1 to 12 in increments of 1,
because I've got only got 12 cords here.
Let's see.
Let's let that run and do some stuff.
Now, the next thing while that's doing, I want to go over there
and look at the code itself.
I'm going to go over here, specifically the C program.
All right.
Let's start looking through this.
So I want to start talking a little bit about C
and make sure we're all on the same page about this stuff.
If there are questions about this stuff that's in this code,
I want to make sure that we feel good about it.
So when you say struct and then you say open curly braids,
closed curly braids, what you're doing
is you're defining a thing that can contain other data.
So data encapsulation.
So like in a programming language like C++ or Python or whatever,
you have objects.
And in these objects, they would have methods
and they would have data values.
But then see, that's not how it works.
You just have function calls and then you have structs
to hold data together that's related.
So it looks like that what we've got here is a struct
that will contain, has a couple of data numbers, rows and calls.
And it's got this double pointer thing over here,
a single pointer thing over here,
and then also whatever this is, which looks like a pointer.
It's a void pointer, which means we don't know the type of it.
And then the name of this thing is called matrix.
If you didn't have a typedef, if you didn't typedef something,
every single time you wanted to talk about the struct,
you'd have to keep saying struct this, struct that, struct this.
And this way you can just say matrix.
That way you don't have to keep saying struct.
So you can type it up anything.
You can say, I want to type it up in integer to smiley face.
And then you can just say smiley face x equals 5.
And that would mean index equals 5.
So typedef just means literally like alias this thing to that thing.
This is what that means.
Now, the way that this 2D memory is allocated,
does anybody actually look at how this worked in here?
Probably not, right? You didn't need to, right, to do it.
But we certainly probably would benefit from understanding
what's really going on in this program.
Because what about if this thing hadn't worked?
We had to, like, say, and ask Chats, you need to help us do something.
We've got this solution that didn't work.
We need to, like, debug it.
So I want us to make sure that we actually understand really what's going on here
because that's, that's what matters.
But clearly there's some kind of thing that's going to be a container
to contain matrices.
But now certainly there's nothing in here.
So this thing by itself hasn't actually allocated any matrix
because you don't know what the number of rows and columns are
until you open the file, right?
Like, the matrices are going to multiply together.
Say, like, matrix A times vector B.
I don't know what their sizes are,
and I have to compile this program and then run it, right?
But you get in C, if you don't know what something is at compile time,
that means you have to figure it out at runtime, right?
Well, normally when you allocate memory, like, if you use a static array,
like, make a bigger array that's 5,000 by 5,000,
well, you could do that at compile time if you wanted to.
But then what about if your matrix was 10,000 by 10,000?
It would be big enough.
So there is no great way to dynamically allocate something
with a regular array nomenclature at compile time in C, unfortunately.
That's why this is all being done dynamically when you execute it.
So when it opens that matrix file and it reads the metadata out of it,
the rows and columns,
at that point it will then go allocate storage space and memory for that file, right?
Because that's how this is happening, right?
Our matrices, when they were created, you know,
if this was like 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, what's actually in the file,
if you thought about the file that's out there on the file system
as a linear array of words, then it would be the number of rows
followed by the number of columns, then followed by the data.
So when you got to read that first thing, read that second thing,
now you know the number of rows and columns,
then you can allocate the memory for it, all right?
So that's kind of what's happening.
So let's go take a look here.
We've got a section that talks about, you know,
giving us a usage statement.
What is all of this stuff here?
Wow, it's got some stuff that checks to see whether overflow is taking place.
Because in standard in C, if you just go and multiply and add things together,
overflow can happen and just keep right on going.
I mean, it doesn't check.
It doesn't check to see if everything's okay or not.
Even though the computer could be checking and it's not doing that,
because it's kind of saying that check typically takes a little extra time
and you guys are supposed to be programming.
You wouldn't have asked me to do something that would have caused overflow
because you guys know what you're talking about, right?
The data, you shouldn't add things that are too big.
You shouldn't multiply things that are too big, right?
But this thing is then saying, hey, actually, we're going to go figure out
whether or not overflow could or occur whenever you're doing this stuff.
And if the computer has a built-in thing that will do this sort of stuff
and it has a built-in thing to check to see if multiplication's happening here,
then it's going to return this multiplication with overflow.
Like, in other words, if there's an assembly instruction
that actually have something that would set a bit equal to something
if overflow's occurring, then I would take my numbers
and I wanted to be multiplying together and do it.
Obviously, there's some stuff going on with that.
I don't know about that.
These are helpers to try to ensure whether overflow occurred or not.
Now, I don't expect you to know.
I don't expect you to replicate this.
I don't expect you to know that.
I'm saying that just that's what it's there for.
It's checking our architectural dependencies and library dependencies.
Like, hey, if this thing's capable of dealing with this,
we should take overflow to a count.
But if we don't, if we can't do that, then we're not going to do it.
We're just going to do regular multiplies and adds and stuff.
Alright, because the range of multiplication just involves multiplication and addition, right?
So it's got two helper strips to see whether or not overflow took place with respect to add,
whether overflow took place with respect to multiply.
Now, this thing is the thing that apparently allocates a 2D matrix.
And it says, do it using one malloc.
Now, I, you know, normally like in the class 207,
does anybody think 207 here?
That's the C or C++ programming-only class.
Like, where did it do that?
Nobody took that, right?
It's not a true revisit for this class.
You would typically go over the three main ways to allocate a matrix.
So I want us to do that using chat GPT
so we can compare and contrast the different ways of doing 2D array allocation, okay?
So, and then we'll see that one of them is this type.
But I would say that this is an important thing that you need to know
because this comes up all the time in straight C, okay?
Because if you want to do something that's multidimensional,
it doesn't have multidimensional available to you.
So you've got to be able to fade it with this stuff here, okay?
So, let's go over to chat GPT.
All right.
You know, straight ANZC.
So that's, you know, what about international standard ANZC.
So let's say, God, I'm not spelling this horrible.
Let's say C99 standard because that's the standard that we're using, right?
Show four ways to declare and initialize
or declare a 2D array.
Let's see, one, statically.
It is known dimensions at compile time.
C number two, dynamically.
Let's see, using a 1D array, using a 2D allocation with two mallets
and a 2D allocation with one mallet.
And then let's see, if you put this code inside of a function,
it even makes it harder to understand.
So, let's do this.
Show these three methods
directly as if they were in main
without being hidden or separated into a function call.
Explain it to us like you would a student
seeing this for the first time.
Let's see what happens.
We're going to do it all inside of main.
The reason I'm doing it inside of main
is because if you put it inside of a function,
there's an additional level of indirection with pointers,
so there's more stars.
Show it this way.
First, now we're going to say, now, let's factor those into function calls.
And look at that, because that's what the people,
the chat GBT did in this original implementation of this thing over there.
It's a hard-coded dimension, it's the simplest,
but it's totally inflexible because you have to know in a priori
how big the matrices are.
Dynamically using a flat 1D block and simulating 2D indexing.
Dynamically with two allets, so rows and columns.
Ooh, so there's actually, so we need to have another way.
There's a fourth way I didn't think about right here.
And then, with one malloc, everything together.
Okay, cool.
Let's take a look at this.
I want us to look at this, just, I mean, we're really,
we're trying to learn here, okay?
Old school would be like, I'm going to declare an array A.
It's got two dimensions, it's three and four.
And there you go.
Fill it up with some stuff, print it out.
There we go.
But the problem is, when you compile it,
this is three and four, you had to know that before you started it.
Like, you can't do the following.
And even if you could, you might find that unless you compile it,
you would never be able to factor it into a function call
and everything needs to be in a function call.
You might come in here and say, let this be X, let this be Y,
and I'll scan F, X into here.
I'll scan F, I'll make it variable.
You might find that that worked.
But that's because it's inside a main, it was inside of a function
because anything that's inside of a function is allocated on the stack.
But when the stack returns, when the function call,
everything on the stack has been allocated.
What about if you want the matrix to live after the function call?
Like, allocate me a matrix, return.
If returning means the stack gets popped off, that ain't going to help us, right?
So even if you wanted to do what's called a VLA, a variable length array,
that only works as long as the lifetime of the function in which it's embedded.
And a lot of students get confused over, I wrote my main program and it worked fine.
That's right, because main never returned until the program was over.
But if it had been inside of a function call,
as soon as the function returned, that damn matrix is gone.
So you can't do this in general.
This is not how to do this.
This would only be useful if you knew our priority,
that every matrix you're going to deal with is exactly the size,
and every matrix you deal with is only going to live in the lifetime
of the function within which it is embedded.
Because if you did this in a function called food,
and then you called food,
matrix A would be gone as soon as it returned,
because this is an immediate thing inside that stack.
It only lives in the scope of that function.
Does that make sense?
Okay.
You access it with two things, I and J,
like you would normally think you would do for a 2D array.
That's why it's simple, totally easy.
Does that make sense?
And by the way, I'll share this conversation out with folks.
It's good that you're writing.
I think it's important to write stuff,
because I think that helps you commit stuff to memory.
I'll share this, let me just share this conversation.
That's why I didn't close the one from 210.
I'm going to share that with the folks.
I know I can get to it, but I just like having it up there.
All right.
The compiler knows it beforehand,
and all the memory lives on the stack.
As I said, it won't help later if it's in a function call,
so we might as well screw this.
This is not ever useful.
Unless the matrix size is non-forehand,
and it never changes and only lives inside the function.
It's like if you need a tiny little place to play with something.
It's just there and gone.
Cool, that's cool.
But nothing that stays around.
Now, one-dimensional with a block.
OK, cool.
So before now, we just had standard IOs
so we could do prints.
Now we've got standard IOs, and we have standard lib.
Because malloc, the functionality for memory allocation,
is inside standard lib.
That's why I'd have to include it.
So now here, we're like, OK, cool.
Rows equals 3, columns equals to 4.
And they did it this way.
You might say, well, that's hard-coded, too.
That's true.
But you could also have just done rv of a to i.
Rv of a to i of rv.
That would work here, too.
But it is right.
This doesn't prove anything, because this is also
hard-coded in here.
You know, if you made a compiler call to do this,
it might not even allocate a variable of memory to call rows.
Because look at this.
The rows never change.
Literally, that 3 could be inside of an instruction.
It might even optimize out those variables.
If you really want to make sure that it stops working,
you would pass it through the argument list
and grab it dynamically.
That way, you know that it has to be working dynamically,
because it couldn't have done it in compile time.
Does that make sense?
You know, a weird thing.
Like, if you compile this into assembly code,
you might be like, there's not even
a place where we did a store word into this memory of 3.
Well, because it doesn't need to be.
You never change it.
Why move stuff to and from memory if it's just 3?
It's always the 3.
It won't change it.
So you need to be careful with stuff like that,
if you ever look at assembly code that comes out of this.
So it says I want to allocate some space
of a certain number of bytes.
And this thing says I want to take the number of rows
times the number of columns times the size of each one
of these elements, and I want it dynamically
allocated to be that big.
But now, malloc returns a void saw, a pointer to something.
But now, in this case, it's not just a something.
It's a pointer to a bunch of integers.
Because so what this thing does is, like, literally, what
just happens in here is the following.
On the stack, you've got rows equals 3.
You've got calls equals how much?
4.
You've got, now, b.
You've got b equals the return value of the malloc.
Malloc returns a pointer.
Like, I don't know.
This is the stack from 210.
If this is address, let's say that this is address a.
Let's say this is address 0.
This is address 4.
This is address 8.
And this is address c.
And this is rows.
This is calls.
This is b.
And let's say when you dynamically allocate it,
of course, that doesn't happen on the stack.
That happens on heat.
So you say, hey, malloc, go make me some space on the heat.
It says, cool.
Address 0, x, f, 7, 7, 8 is where these bytes are.
How many bytes are there?
Rows times columns times the size of each thing.
So the size of an integer, let's say, is 4 bytes.
That's going to be 3 times 4 times 4.
That many bytes, the beginning address of that is f, 7, 7, 8.
And therefore now, f, 7, 7, 8 is the address of where that is.
Because now that means b is a pointer to the address of the memory that just got malloc.
OK?
We've got them happening.
This is like a review from 210, probably.
And then it just says, cool.
I want to access this.
And what is it doing here?
Anybody got any idea what it's doing right here on this line?
If not b, what does that mean?
Why are they doing that?
Making sure that the allocation of b works.
OK?
Because when you malloc something, if malloc blows out and screws up, it's going to return
a null pointer.
And null pointer just means the number is 0.
There's nothing inherent about any of the values that it means as a pointer.
Pointers and numbers are literally the same thing, like the pointer a and the number a
are the exact same thing depending on how we use it.
So when it screws up, it returns to 0.
So 0 happens over here.
If it were to screw up into the 0 here.
And if you say, if not 0, so when you say not 0, the complement of 0 is a 1.
So if true, end early.
Else we know that if it gets past this, the mount must have been OK.
That's what's happening here.
And then after that, what happens is it goes and sticks to stuff in memory.
But what's happening is it takes i times columns plus j.
We already discussed this in this class, I believe, when I'm out of this, right?
So this is this way, the one malloc with the 1d malloc.
Let's move on to the next one.
The memory is contiguous.
That's important.
What's important about the memory being continuous?
It says, because it's for performance, why?
Why would it matter if the data for this matrix was next to each other in memory?
That's true.
Why would that matter?
Let's say you didn't have to search.
You knew exactly where they were.
Why would you not want to do that?
That is true, but that's not the reason.
It has to do with caching because the way hashing works in the computer is that this is a,
let's suppose that this were equal to, I don't know, let's just say this was 40, 96 bytes.
I know it's not, but let's say it was.
And let's say every block in cache was 20, 48 blocks.
So the very first time you tried to read this memory, if it's in cache,
or if it's in cache, this is RAM.
That's where this thing is.
Cache is located right next to the processor.
This is way across on the motherboard when there's such a motherboard where RAM is.
You had asked for this block.
CPU says only an address 0x7FF8.
It comes over here.
There's a thing in here that's checked to see whether that address is in here in cache.
It has a miss, so there's a cache miss.
It says, damn it, it's not in here.
It's over there.
So then it goes and grabs this block of that.
It takes that block and puts it right there.
So if this is called B, I've got like one half of B is up here,
and one half of B is still over there.
So this is the first half of B.
So in that loop, the very first time you access it,
I is 0, J is 0, 0 times this is 0 plus 0.
We asked for B of 0.
B of 0 is this very first element.
We looked at here to see if it was in here.
It was not.
We came over to the main memory, the architecture,
grabbed this block and brought it back over here and stuck it there and said,
cool now, now that it's in there, I'll give you that first element
and you can start doing your work on it.
Now, granted, this thing is doing a right to memory, not a read.
But let's just not worry about that for a second.
Well, the reason is the second, the second location.
But the point of it is that took a bunch of time to get it from here to here.
If it had already been here, it would have been like, oh, there it is.
Now, that loop goes to the very next element.
That very next element is this element.
So it takes that and adds 1 to it, 1 element.
This is the next one in that array.
It comes here and it's like, OK, that's not a miss.
That's a hit that's right there.
And why does it matter to this continuous?
Because if you're accessing memory in the order that it's so ordered,
then it's going to be brought over in blocks in that same order
and you're going to get a lot more cache hits than misses.
But now, if I had written this code the other way,
like where it wasn't accessing in the row major order,
that second element might have been down here.
This is like cache miss.
Oh, bring this over here.
Oh, cache miss.
Imagine your cache is only one block wide.
It'd be cache miss, cache miss, cache miss,
cache miss like that over and over again because you're not accessing it
in the order that it's ordered.
So if you can, not always possible, right?
If the algorithm in an alien order, well, that's just the way it is.
But if you can access it in order that it's laid out in memory,
then you're going to do what?
You're going to really speed it up because the memory hierarchy
has been designed to have two features, spatial and temporal locality of reference,
spatially closed.
So if you can write your algorithm to access things that are next to each other,
then it'll benefit from cache, which all computers have
because almost all programs have some degree of spatial and temporal locality
except for programs that simulate things that are totally random,
like a Monte Carlo simulation might have that problem.
Well, then maybe that code that exhibits spatial and temporal locality,
nine times up to 10, nine times up to 100,
they benefit from caching because if they didn't,
you'd think people would pay for cache.
If it didn't help, someone else would do it.
This is the reason why that works.
Does that make sense?
That's why you want it to be contiguous.
You're right.
You don't want to be strung out.
But the reason you don't want it to be strung out
isn't that accessing it over here versus over here takes any different time.
It's the second time you access it after it's brought into cache
that it's faster that second time.
But the very first time it's a miss, it doesn't matter where it is in memory.
That's not totally true because in real life,
let us say you're on a motherboard that has 16 RAM slots.
Those RAM slots have things where they're just not the same amount of time
for all of them.
So there's some heterogeneity there.
You know how RAM stands for random access memory
because memory before that couldn't be accessed randomly.
It could only be accessed linearly, the RAM,
the stuff that was existing before RAM.
People were really pumped and like,
oh man, RAM is awesome because you can randomly access it.
But you still can't.
But accessing it randomly ain't near as fast as accessing it linearly.
It costs caching and it costs of other stuff.
Caching is talked about in detail in the Pacheco text.
So please read the part in there that the first couple of chapters
have to do with caching because that is the bare minimum
that you need to know about computer architecture in this class.
You know, you shouldn't ever graduate from college
without understanding what caching is
and why it is that it actually helps, okay?
But simply, you know, so that's what's happening here.
Now, with two mallets, a pointer to the rows and one for each row.
Now let's do this.
This is not what I had in mind, but this is, in fact,
this is an intermediate one that's also a possibility.
This is probably the absolute worst freaking way
that you could possibly do this.
It's way worse than the previous way.
Because at least the previous way to touch, damn it,
is continuous in memory.
This thing here, let's look at this.
I am going to draw a picture of what happens here to make this clear.
And if the web app that does this still works,
you can actually take this code, put it in the thing,
and it'll draw you a picture of memory with all the pointers
to where your beginnings are,
and you can see how this sucks, how bad this sucks.
All right.
Now, I'm going to draw it like the way it's actually laid out,
both on the stack for main,
as well as the heap for the dynamic memory allocations, okay?
And I'm going to draw a stack right over here.
So this is the stack for main.
So this is the main's stack frame, right?
Sometimes it's called activation and record.
So this is stuff, variables related to main.
And then this is the heap.
This is where memory is at where dialects are concerned.
Now, really, it's all in RAM,
but it's just logically this is one place and that's another place.
And hopefully they're not near each other.
That's kind of the idea.
Okay.
Here we go. Let's go write all the variables now.
Rose calls C. Awesome.
Rose calls C.
Now, I'm going to make up some addresses here, okay?
Now, really, these addresses can't be like 1, 2, 3.
Because each address is probably 32 to 64 bits wide,
and so the numbers wouldn't be next to each other.
But the purpose of this example,
I'm going to use addresses like 10, 11, and 12.
Even though it wouldn't be 10, 11, and 12.
It might be 10, 8, 10 to 10, 14, 18, 1, C.
It might be stuff like that.
Like from 210.
You remember how the stuff, like, let up, get a go at 1.
But I'm going to do that just to make it easy.
So I'm going to say that this thing is at address 1,
address 2 in memory, and address 3.
I don't know what the values are yet.
Oh, it's 3 to 4.
Okay.
So that got allocated to a 3.
It just got allocated to a 4.
And C got allocated to a single mallet,
which was equal to the number of rows this thing had,
which is 3, times the size of a pointer.
Now, a pointer is 8 bytes.
So we're over here.
We've allocated that.
All right.
Now, it was 3 times size of int star.
Int star, the size of this star, is 8.
It becomes pointers on most computers that are 64 bits.
You know, 8 times 8 is 64.
64-bit architectures have 64-bit addresses.
So 64 times 3 bytes here.
Okay.
But technically, there's only three elements in here.
There's rows elements.
But each element of this chunk represents a pointer
to other integers.
So I'm going to draw the three elements here.
It contains three things.
But these three things are not integers.
These three things are pointers to other integers.
So it's going to be a pointer like this.
It's going to point somewhere.
Yeah.
Okay.
But mallet's that thing.
Now, somewhere on the heap is the very beginning
of this chunk that it just had.
Now, I want to pretend that the very top of this address
right there is an address 100.
Like, the very first byte in that chunk of 64 times 3 bytes
starts at address 100.
So literally, if it was in this picture,
it would be like way down there at 100.
But I'm drawing it over there.
So 100 gets returned from here
because it's the address of this block it just allocated.
It allocated its block at that 100.
So this is 100.
But because this is a pointer,
we're thinking of that like it points right over there.
It's a pointer to a pointer to an integer.
Check it out.
It's a pointer to a pointer to where an integer will be here.
But that hasn't been allocated yet.
Those are all nulls still.
Then we come down here in a for loop
from 0 to the number of rows.
And we're going to malloc columns times size of n.
OK, well, I'm going to draw a matrix here.
So it had how many rows and how many columns?
Three rows?
Four columns?
So it's got three of these.
It's got four of those.
Logically, this thing is named C.
So this is some sort of matrix called C.
And let's suppose it had the numbers in it.
5, 6, 7, 8, 5, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16.
Let's say that was the numbers that were in this thing.
It's got row 0, 1, 2, and columns 0, 1, 2, 3.
This is the way you and I think of it.
This is how it's actually being done.
So let's take a look.
So it allocates a block that's equal to 4 times the size of an n.
Now, the size of an integer is 4, because it's 4 bytes.
So this thing allocates enough space for 4 things that are integers.
Does that make sense?
So somewhere else, there's another block,
because an alloc goes out here and finds a block.
And that block logically holds 4 things.
Let's say that this is an address 200.
So that means that when it allocates and does the very first row of this,
it allocates 100, excuse me, 4 items worth of integers,
where each one of those integers is 32 bits, 4 bytes.
And it provides the address, and it sticks it in C of 0.
Well, wait a minute.
Where the hell is C of 0?
Well, C of, well, this is of 0 of 1 of 2,
because remember when we first did this, it had 3 elements in it.
So that location there, 200 comes out of now.
So 200 goes to, say, C of 0.
So it goes to 200 here.
So that means that actually the first element of this points to this.
OK?
It's two levels of indirection.
Then it goes.
It checks again, making sure that the amount of work,
because if it blew out, it needs to continue.
Then it does it for the next one.
And then it does it for the next one.
One for every row.
So it goes and does another malloc.
So let's say that malloc happens here.
All right?
And then let's say the other malloc happens here.
Each one of those things has got enough space
to hold column numbers of integers.
Columns, those equal to 4.
So each one of those things have got 4 in it.
Let's say that's at address 300 and 400.
I'm taking numbers that are far apart to make it easy to look at.
But they won't be far apart.
They're probably close together, but they might not be.
Who knows?
Because the operating system is the thing that's actually grabbing those.
All right?
So C of 1, so C of 1 equals to the return value of that malloc is 300.
So that pointer points here.
And then the very next one, C of 2, C of 2 is equal to 400.
So that one points here.
And then it loops over to the array, C of ij.
OK, so let's do the very first iteration of that loop.
C of ij is equal to something.
I don't even give a crap what it's supposed to be.
Actually, let's do it.
C of ij is 0 times 10 plus something.
It's making up stuff really easy.
It's just making up something.
Let's see what that is.
0 plus 0 is 0.
OK, so here we go.
C of 0 of 0.
So that's this one.
C of 0.
Shit.
That goes here.
But then remember the way this is 1, 2, 3.
This is 1, 2, 3, 3, 0, 1, 2, 3.
And I don't even care what it's actually putting in there.
Let's imagine that it was putting in the numbers
that I sent here, OK?
So it would be a 0 here.
It would be a 5, 6, 7, 8, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, and then
13, 14, 15, 16.
That's how it would be laid out.
So when you send something like C of 2, let's say 3,
let's say C of 1, 2.
Let's find that.
Let's say I want to make that equal to smiley face.
OK, where is C12 over here?
Well, C12 over here is right there, isn't it?
You agree with that?
It would be a row 1, column 2, that would be a stylus.
Where is that over there?
Now, we know it's right there, but let's do it.
C of 1.
So C of 1 and then of 2 means that we follow this
and we come down to 2, and then we say that's
equal to smiley face there.
That is how this one works.
Look how many mallocs it is.
It's one malloc to hold a pointer for every row,
and every one of those rows also have to have a malloc.
So for this matrix, how many mallocs are actually done?
So the number of mallocs equals 1 plus the number of rows.
Because the very first malloc makes a thing to hold
the pointers for each row.
So there's three rows, so it's going to be 1 plus 3 is 4 mallocs.
Does that make sense?
That's how this one works.
Now, and then now it goes and frees it up.
Now, this is not the one I want to go to next.
I'm going to ask it to give me the example that's
supposed to be between this example and this one.
This is the way that you could do it with just one malloc.
So we did it with a variable number of mallocs just now.
I want to do it with just two mallocs,
because you need to do that first before you can understand
how the one-with-one malloc works.
So, yeah, you're right.
I'm right.
I asked one.
I didn't say 1 plus rows.
I said 2.
I was about to say that.
That ain't right.
I'm like, OK, but it can't continue.
All right, cool.
Have you written down?
I mean, can I erase this?
If you want to take a picture of it,
I mean, if you go ahead and do it,
I'm going to erase this, because I'm going to show you this way.
I'm going over this because, like,
every single program that we write is going to be dealing
with data structures.
It's probably going to be a lot of it is going to be matrices,
so this is going to be in all of the programs,
and I don't want it to be a mystery.
And plus the quintex look, which has some code that we're going
to also use, they do it this way right here in that book,
and I don't want you to get freaked out when you see it.
Like, what the hell is all of this?
And it's like, oh, that's just making this due to your array,
but here's why they did it that way,
and here's the reason why, and here's how it actually works.
I think it's worth seeing.
OK.
So I guess I could have left C up here,
because we're taking the same stuff, but whatever.
Let me just do it over again here.
I'm going to do it by this way.
So I'll draw the stack.
I guess this thing's starting to dry out here today.
Let's see.
What about this one?
Oh, yeah.
That was solid.
That was awesome.
Those little tiny things in life, you know.
All right.
See, now I'm not allowed down.
It's not looking good, but this is the stack.
What are the variables in it?
Rows, calls, and C. Oh, and data.
Rows, calls, C, data.
That looks like you can identify everything that's on the stack,
because it's the variables that are declared in this,
between this and the end down there.
So it's rows, calls, C, data.
That's on the stack.
But anything that's been maliqued,
the space for this stuff is actually over here on the heap.
OK.
Let's do this.
Three, four.
C is equal to maliqued of the number of rows times the number
times the space it takes to hold the pointers.
All right.
This is starting off like the previous one.
OK.
So it allocates space for some pointers.
And it's going to have rows, numbers, and elements,
so it's going to have three elements.
OK.
And the address of that, let's say it's at address 100 in D,
that becomes equal to the value of C.
So C points over here to here.
Then it comes down in here.
Now look at how much space that thing now is.
Now it allocates enough stuff for rows times column
number of integers.
So 12 integers.
So now four, we did four at a time.
One row, next row, next row.
But here it says no.
I'm going to just allocate all of the space that it wants.
So here we go.
This one's bigger.
All right.
I have 12 elements.
I don't know.
I'm not really counting here.
It's all mine.
I just did.
So row three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten,
eleven.
So it's 12, 12 elements, right?
That's how many elements are going to be in the matrix.
And let's go ahead and do our matrix.
Draw it logically over here.
And we set five, six, seven, eight, nine, thirteen,
fourteen, fifteen, sixteen.
The row indices are one, zero, one, two.
Zero, one, two, three.
And this thing is called C.
Get us the logical diagram.
All we've done so far is this.
But now we're getting ready to map that.
This thing's at address, say, 200.
And that gets equal to this pointer called data.
So that means this is equal to 200.
And this thing points here.
You see that?
Now, check out this for looping right now.
I'm glad I did it this way because the Quinn textbook doesn't do it quite this way.
And I was worried that it was going to do it more esoteric way.
But here we go.
So C of zero, the very first time, is equal to the data.
But what is that?
The data is equal to 200.
So this is 200.
So C of zero equals 200 plus zero.
This is the very first element.
So we'll say zero times the number of columns is what?
Four?
Four, so this whole thing becomes what?
200.
Okay, here we go.
C of zero is equal to 200.
Let's go to the next loop.
This is one.
One.
200 plus four is 204.
So this is 204.
The next time, this is two.
This is two.
Two times four is eight.
Eight plus 200 is 208.
This is 208.
Okay, but these things are in C.
But what is the type of C?
The type of C is a pointer to another pointer to an integer.
And look at what this is going to be.
C is a pointer to a pointer to an integer.
Let's check this out.
Because really, if that's 200, it's represented as a damn pointer.
Because down there, at the bottom, it's going to be like C of zero, zero is equal to five.
So C of zero, that points to 200 of zero is five.
So that thing is pointing here.
But now where is 204 pointing to?
Well, that's 200.
204 is right there, isn't it?
So 204 is pointing here.
And what is the next one pointing to?
To the wave.
And that's because, even though we did one malloc, this represents row zero.
This represents row one.
And this represents row two.
And each one of the rows has its own pointer.
This thing, the C here, is called the array of row pointers.
Because this doesn't actually contain the data.
It contains pointers to where the beginning of all those data's rows are.
Does that make sense?
How many mallocs did we have to do?
Just two.
Here's the thing.
Every time you call a malloc, that's a system call.
I don't know if you discussed it in operating systems, but that takes a long time, relatively speaking.
So you could somehow minimize the number of mallocs that you do that is generally better.
Now, that ain't always true.
But right now, we're just trying to understand, what in the hell does the code do?
Does this make sense?
And you see why I don't have this inside of a function call.
Because then you'd have to be passing a pointer to the pointers to the pointers.
You have three stars instead of two.
I'm trying to do this first, slowly, so that when we go and move it inside of a function like they did over here,
hell, that stuff's also inside of a struct that we understand all these pointers.
Because I know everybody gets crazy when there's stars everywhere, and I totally get it.
The very first time I saw pointers, I was about to have like a stroke.
I didn't understand what was happening.
I didn't understand what a reference was.
I didn't understand what pointers were.
The only programming language I had ever seen prior to C was BASIC,
Beginner's All-Purpose Symbolic Instruction Code.
And it didn't have pointers.
It just had line numbers.
At least I don't think it had pointers.
It might have, and I just didn't know that.
But I was just like blown away when I saw COs, and I didn't know what was going on.
You guys had the benefit of having a Python, which means you already know about references.
That's what these are.
They refer to things.
It's just that these references are actually numbers that are actually physically the memory address.
Whereas in Python, you can't actually address things directly using your addresses.
You can only use their references.
C says you can do them both at the same time, which is both very cool,
and it's also very destructive if you use it incorrectly.
Everybody deal with that example.
Let's move on to the last example.
The one where it just happens using only one mallet.
This one's a good intent.
This one certainly probably most people consider the most complicated one of these things to understand,
but it also uses the dualist number of mallets.
Now, we're going to go through this one somewhat slower.
I know you're not already going slow, but that's the only one to discuss this one time.
You might have to keep going over that.
This is about going over one time, okay?
That's why we're going so slow.
All right.
We've got a stack frame for main.
We've got the heap, all right?
Let's look at our variables that are in main.
Rows, calls, d, data.
That's it.
Rows, calls, d, and data.
Okay.
Rows and calls amply are equal to 3 and 4.
Okay?
Let's keep going.
Do this part next.
D, and it's declared here, but it doesn't get equal to anything.
It's telling us a mallet.
So any time you do a mallet, it's going to go over to the heap and find the space.
Now, how much space?
Rows times the size of an star.
Now, rows here is 3.
So 3 times the size of an star is 8.
Okay.
Plus rows times columns times the size of an integer.
3 times 4 times 4.
So the actual space is the space for 3 pointers and the space for 12 integers.
Do you see that?
Now, that last way we did it, we had one mallet that had space for 3 pointers,
and we had another mallet that had space for 12 integers.
Now we have a single mallet with enough space for both of them.
See, it's making space for both the row pointers and the data itself
inside of a single mallet.
Do you see that?
So there's going to be some space at the very beginning that represent the 3 row pointers.
This is going to be the 3 row pointers.
And the rest of the space inside this is the data.
All right.
And how many elements is that going to have in it?
That's going to have 12 that come right after these 3 elements.
So we'll go ahead and put that in there.
Actually, yeah.
Let me not put the numbers, but let's do so.
1, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.
Let me make sure that actually adds up right.
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.
So 0 through 11 is a total of 12 integer elements.
I'm not going to put the addresses on here yet because that's where this gets a little bit weird.
Let's suppose that the very beginning of this alloc block is 100.
So 100 comes over here into 8.
I can do it 4.
So we're going to say this is address 100.
And that's equal to d.
So that's 100 here.
And this d then points to this location.
That's all that's happened so far.
Are we good on this?
Cook up the row pointers.
God almighty, look at this.
OK.
It's OK.
It's going to be OK.
But actually, I'm going to write on top of this the values
everywhere is on here, OK?
What is d?
100.
Plus, what's rows?
Huh?
3.
Then it says take that and add it.
103.
Now, d is a pointer.
And this is an integer.
But they're really both just integers.
But it's saying, hey, now, but going and cast that to an integer pointer.
That just means the type of this thing should be an integer pointer.
That's not changing the value of it.
It's a damn integer.
Pointers are integers, aren't they?
Doesn't 103 look like an integer?
This is just to make sure that C understands that.
I just took two things that were different types.
This was an int star star.
This was an int.
And I added them together.
And I'm going to convert it to a type that was neither one of the things I started with.
This is an int star star.
This is an int.
And by the way, I'm going to treat it as if it is a single dimensional integer pointer.
But when it's all said and done, use just what?
103.
So data becomes equal to 103.
And it's an integer star.
So where the hell does it point?
Well, what do you guys think?
This was 0, 1, 2.
So this thing comes over here and points to right there.
So the data pointer is pointing to where the data section begins inside this thing.
Does that make sense?
And then they go and say, OK, now, I've got to get my row pointers to point to the right places in here like we did before.
But before, on that last example, we just had a for loop that hooked up the pointers.
All right, that's what's happening here.
d of 0 equals 103 plus 0 times 4.
So d of 103 is equal to, I mean, d of 0 equals 103, right?
So d of 0 equals 103.
That means that that row pointer points to the beginning of row 0, which is at the beginning of the data section of this whole block.
So that means that this points to right here.
Then the loop comes around.
It increments to 1.
So that becomes 1.
So 103 plus, what is this?
4, so that's, what is that?
Now, here's the thing.
Where's 107?
This is 103, 104, 105, 106, 107.
And when we looked at our matrix before, and I don't know, what number did we start with before?
Somebody said 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16.
This first row has 5, 6, 7, 8 in it.
5, 6, 7, 8.
So this first row is pointed to my first index.
The second row, though, points to row 7, the beginning of the second row.
So the second row is going to be 1, 2, 3, 4.
So that's 108, 109, 110, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.
So when it comes back around here, this becomes a 2.
6 times 4 is 8.
8 plus 3 is 11.
So this becomes 111, and this pointer points here from the last row.
And then the loop beyond that just goes and fills in the matrix with the data.
That's all it does, right?
It just has a double-nested for loop.
Yeah, there it is.
It just fills stuff in.
It just goes and says, loop over every row and every column, put some crap in it.
That's all it says.
It's just making up something.
I'm just saying, let's pretend that what we put in it is 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 9, 9, 9, 9, 9, 9, 9.
Okay.
Here it is right there.
So when you go and say, I want c of 1, 2, let's actually follow it.
When you say c over here, they call it d.
That's because every time we make a new way, it keeps incrementing like the variable.
Like Wikipedia, like, you know, it's supposed to all be a name.
We couldn't have the matrix call the same thing if it was a name.
So it's called d here.
So we would say d of 1, 2.
So we know that d of 1, 2 is right here.
But where is it over here?
We go d of 1.
Well, a 1 brings you down here.
And then of 2 inside of it is 0, 1, 2.
Do you see that?
That's how this works.
This is often referred to, this section here,
this is often referred to as the payload section.
Because this is the thing that actually is the data.
That is not data up there.
Like if I wanted to save d to a file,
am I going to f right d into a file?
Because d contains this stuff.
That is not the data.
This is the data.
This is just temporarily some pointers that point to the right place
so that I can do that.
So what that's called is we're pre-computing all of the addresses.
Because you're pre-doing that for loop one time.
And that way, every time you use this array after that,
you don't have to do that computation again.
You do unfortunately though.
If you were writing this in MIPSA,
you'd have to be like load address for d.
And then load d of zero.
Then take d of zero, load address, add half of that.
You know, you would be so many MIPSA instructions.
The problem with this is you have to read that location in a minute.
First you have to read this location to get to here.
Then you have to read that location to get to here.
And then you have to read that location to get to there.
That's a bunch of damn reads.
So unfortunately, like doing it this way is nice, clear, and concise.
You might say it's not clear, but it is.
But it certainly involves a lot of reading and writing the memory.
So one might argue that while this is the coolest in terms of number of mallics,
it is not the coolest in terms of numbers of memory transactions.
So which one costs more?
Well, if you're going to only use the array one time,
and you've got a lot of rows, it's probably not a bad idea
to not be mallicking a bunch.
But if you're going to access it lots of times,
one might say, you know what, it's better maybe to not have this in here
because think about that cash example I gave you.
What about if a block represented eight of these things?
It's like one, two, three, four of these things.
I don't know, say four.
Remember, that doesn't make sense because these are eight mites.
Let's say they're the same.
This might be a cash block, this might be a cash block.
So for you to do D of something, it has to grab D, bring that in the cash.
You have to read that thing that has to go here and bring this in the cash.
You see what I'm saying?
And depending on how that cash is going, you could be thrashing cash.
You know how they talk about a 356, the working set of a program?
That's the concept they talk about 356, the working set.
It means your program may be an acetone of instructions and acetone of data,
but any one time, are you actually accessing every instruction in your program one at a time?
No.
Most of your instructions in your program are accessed one after another
because we learned in 210.
That's their own next to each other.
What's that?
Spatial locality.
So programs also exhibit spatial locality,
which means that programs would benefit from cash.
And the question is, is this layout and memory the best thing for memory performance?
I don't know, but you could evaluate it.
You could write it all sideways.
You could make tens of thousands of matrices and programs and invest marks
and you could measure it and you could say experimentally,
well, which one of these is better for my particular scenario?
And then that's what you pick.
But that would be different for different scenarios, different access patterns.
Does that make sense?
Okay.
So when we go and look at this thing here, look at this,
payload number of bytes, the pointers, the numbers of elements,
the address of these things.
So they now look at the total amount of bytes
and then they took the row pointers thing,
had it point to the same place that the block pointed to
and then inside of a single loop so that for every row it took the beginning of this
and added it to this and set it equal to that.
And does that not look like the thing that we just did?
It does.
And you might be like, oh my God, there's a bunch of other stuff.
Yeah, there are.
There are others.
You know, could we go in here and take this code and ask chat GPT,
what is this exactly doing?
You could say, in class we just did this thing and you got all this other stuff.
What is the purpose of that?
You could do that, right?
So I would encourage you to do that.
I would encourage you to look through this code,
and I know you probably haven't because you were working hard
on just trying to get the solutions and stuff and then stop it for the last thing, right?
You probably desperately try to do that.
You probably didn't look through every single file through the line of this, right?
It's okay. I'm just asking.
How many of you know how all these purposes actually work?
We don't know that yet, right? We haven't covered it.
We're going to cover it now.
We've already seen it in operation.
We've seen it work.
We've seen it get answers.
We've seen it get performance metrics, and then we've plotted them.
Well, now let's go back and actually look at the program
and understand exactly what it's doing so that we can then take the next step.
And you know what that stuff's going to be?
It's going to be to say, okay, what could we do to this program to make it faster?
Because right now this is not very fast.
Even if we threw away some of the stuff that we did here, what's the bottleneck?
The bottleneck seemed to be the silo that we were doing.
We can move to the solid state drive on the node and do that.
There's also a bunch of other things about this program
that are not great in the way this is currently written.
How it was written, I asked Chat GPT to give it to me.
I tested. I saw it work.
We measured the performance in here.
So literally, what have y'all done?
Y'all all spent a bunch of time trying to figure out how long it took
and what kinds of speed-ups you could get with Chat GPT's implementation
of matrix vector multiplier.
Because I didn't write that.
That GT did.
Did it do a good job? Because that's one of the questions, right?
Like, how would you get something from Chat GPT?
Do you know if it's okay?
One way is, can you run it and it gets you the answer?
Didn't blow up. That's one answer.
But in parallel computing in this class, it's not just about the answer.
Hell, you don't need to write a parallel program to get the answer.
You could write a regular program.
It's got to be faster.
And you want it to be the fastest it could possibly be.
So now, we have baseline numbers that you've all measured on your own computer.
You've measured it on expanse.
So we know that any changes we make to this by looking through this
and trying to intelligently do something
should at least perform as well as what Chat GPT gave us.
If whatever we do sucks worse than what Chat GPT gave us,
that means we're going in the wrong direction.
If we can't make it any faster, then maybe that means it did a pretty good job.
So we're going to evaluate everything that it did.
We're going to talk about how it worked.
And we're going to talk about the things that at least I perceive as being wrong with it.
And we know that it works.
I mean, you could take every combination.
I've tried it.
But every combination of rows and columns between this and this,
run it sequentially, run it in parallel,
compare the two answers, make sure every answer is actually the same.
It is.
It doesn't crash.
It doesn't do any of these things.
It never over-corrupts a file as far as I can tell.
It seems to be working.
And it speeds up some.
Okay.
But is that the best it could be?
What are the limiting factors of this program the way they are?
Because that is totally not written the way you would want to write this program in real life.
That's what we're going to do.
You see kind of where I'm going here?
That's what we're doing.
Because I know that in real life you're going to be using tools.
You're going to be using what's ever available.
You're going to use the APIs of stuff that you didn't write
because you're going to build the shoulders of the stuff that's already there.
Some of that stuff might be something that came with something that was already built.
Some of it might be built by some sort of a system of tools.
So I see this as two-fold.
Like, this assistive tool didn't help us.
Well, you know, it did give me an answer like in three minutes.
Like, imagine that all you had was, like when I was in college,
you had a textbook.
You didn't show how to do this.
You didn't have the Internet.
You didn't have chat GPT.
You had to write this.
It took me forever to write this program the very first time because I didn't have it.
It was awful.
It took me three minutes to write with a chat GPT or less.
I literally only had to ask two things to be fixed when it gave me the thing I had to do.
There weren't things that needed to be fixed that were wrong.
They were just stuff I just wanted differently.
In fact, it was right the very first time.
So that's what I want us to do, all right?
I'll see you guys later.
See you on Tuesday, excuse me, Thursday.
I will share the thing that started with that chat conversation
that we've been playing with.
And I want you to start looking at just the place where it allocated the memory
and try to map it back to what we just talked about and understand
what memory allocation it does to see what one of these it is
and see that it actually does the same thing that we said today, all right?
See you guys next time.
Yes, sir.
Do you see recent stuff on the accommodations on the last year?
So, yeah, did you do anything?
Did you extend anything or any of the stuff?
Now right now, the thinking comes up in the silence.
Sounds good.